<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- LEADER_TECUMSEH -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_TECUMSEH_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The American colonies' westward expansion bred consistent conflict with Native American tribes. Native communities struggled to rebuff the colonial advance independently, and they struggled to unify and face this threat together. The social, political, and cultural divisions between them were deeply established and difficult to overcome. But in 1783, a confederacy of tribes rallied around the Great Lakes region and won several major victories against the United States. Although the alliance was short-lived, the idea of a united front took hold in a young Shawnee warrior who witnessed its rise and fall and who was determined to recreate it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tecumseh, whose name means “Panther across the Sky,” came into the world in 1768 while a meteor soared through the night. Despite a challenging youth, he quickly stood out among his peers as a promising leader and warrior. Tecumseh was a skilled hunter and fighter; while he ran from his first battle at age 14, he was embarrassed by his behavior and was determined it would never happen again (and it never did). He was also charismatic, clever, and a talented orator, with a penchant for humor and an eye for diplomacy. Growing up amid the conflict between colonists and his Shawnee community, he chose to learn English at a young age, though he often hid his proficiency and spoke only Shawnee in diplomatic meetings. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>By the 1780s, American colonists were pushing into the Northwest Territory, a region between the Ohio River and the Great Lakes. A loose confederation of tribes, including Shawnees under Chief Blue Jacket, opposed their advance with help from the British. But after this confederation's defeat at the Battle of Fallen Timbers, in which Tecumseh took part, many chiefs signed away their land to the United States in the 1795 Treaty of Greeneville. Tecumseh firmly opposed this act. Over the following years, his influence over local Shawnee grew – but the unexpected rise of his younger brother changed the course of his life. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Contrary to Tecumseh, Lalawethika had never shown great promise. He was cowardly, inept, and an alcoholic who had accidentally shot out his own eye as a child. Still, in 1805, he began to experience visions in which the Master of Life, the primary Shawnee deity, showed him the fate of those who followed (and those who turned away from) a virtuous life. Lalawethika changed his name to Tenskwatawa, “the Open Door,” and began to proselytize a new form of spirituality, one that rejected European goods and practices, embracing only traditional values and ways of life. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tenskwatawa the Prophet established himself as the village’s new spiritual leader. Tecumseh, as political and war chief, decided to align with his brother’s beliefs. The two gained several prominent followers from nearby tribes but faced pushback among other Shawnees – while former confederacy leader Blue Jacket joined their ranks, the powerful Black Hoof of Wapakoneta refused to recognize them. The brothers also attracted the attention of local colonial officials, who were uneasy about the new spiritual movement and its potential to unite the tribes. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>In 1808, Tecumseh and Tenskwatawa moved farther west and established the village of Prophetstown, where they amassed followers in large numbers from many different tribes. Their peaceful existence was shattered only a year later with the Treaty of Fort Wayne, in which Indiana Territory governor William Henry Harrison negotiated a land purchase with several tribes while excluding the Shawnees. Tecumseh was outraged by the treaty’s deal and confronted Harrison in person to nullify the treaty, declaring that the land belonged to all tribes and therefore could not be sold by anyone. When he returned home empty-handed, he began to earnestly build an intertribal confederation, promoting a dual goal of unity among Native Americans and the preservation of individual tribes’ traditional ways. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>As more and more warriors flowed into Prophetstown, Tecumseh left Tenskwatawa to manage the home front and began to travel widely. He voyaged far to the south, covering several thousand miles and speaking with many communities, encouraging their young warriors to join his cause. The journey was largely unsuccessful as a recruitment drive, but Tecumseh’s rhetoric planted seeds that bore fruit in later conflicts. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>During Tecumseh’s absence, Harrison led an army to Prophetstown to depose Tenskwatawa. Tecumseh had warned his brother not to exacerbate tensions with the Americans, but the Prophet ordered an attack before negotiations with Harrison could commence. Though Harrison lost more soldiers, the Battle of Tippecanoe ended in an American victory, and Prophetstown burned down in the aftermath. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TECUMSEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Tecumseh's confederation appeared in tatters, but he began rebuilding as soon as he returned from his odyssey. Mere months later, he led his followers into an alliance with the British as the War of 1812 ignited. His personality and military ingenuity quickly gained the trust and admiration of British commanders, and he was put in charge of orchestrating Native American forces until he was killed at the Battle of the Thames in 1813. Although his death brought an end to his confederacy, Tecumseh’s vision and legacy transformed him into a folk hero that has survived into the modern day. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_SHAWNEE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SHAWNEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The origins of the Shawnee tribe are murky, but they are widely believed to have emerged from the Fort Ancient culture of the Ohio River Valley (c. 1000-1650 CE). The Fort Ancient people emerged from the Late Woodland period with a new understanding of corn agriculture and farming techniques, leading to a more sedentary lifestyle and larger settlements. They did not form a single polity; rather, they shared a common culture of social organization, religious beliefs, artistic styles, and mound-building that spanned across diverse political and linguistic groups. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SHAWNEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Fort Ancient villages, run by chiefs and councils, only exercised power within their walls – their political influence did not extend to other villages, and no major centers of power existed. Summer villages, built to be permanent, were agricultural and could house up to 500 people. These were abandoned in the winter as the people scattered to mobile winter hunting camps of up to 30 people. As the spring rolled around, the Fort Ancient people reunited back at the summer villages, a cycle of migration that gave root to rituals celebrating the changing seasons. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SHAWNEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Through trade with the Haudenosaunee, many European goods reached the Ohio River Valley during the 16th and early 17th centuries. But when the first Europeans arrived in the 1650s, the Fort Ancient people were gone. Exactly why they migrated remains unclear. Archaeological records indicate that diseases like smallpox (likely borne by traders) impacted the Ohio River Valley in several waves. Neighboring societies were also becoming increasingly aggressive, as the Beaver Wars ignited violence and expansion from the East. As the Ohio River Valley became more dangerous due to these outside pressures, the Fort Ancient people seemingly chose to relocate rather than risk remaining in their homeland. As these people traveled, their tribal differences coalesced, forming a new era of new identities. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SHAWNEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The Shawnee were among these transitioning tribes. As with their Fort Ancient predecessors, the village remained the focal point of power and loyalty, and leadership was divided between a civic chief and a war chief. Seasonal changes were celebrated with important rituals, particularly the spring and fall Bread Dances. The tribe was subdivided into five bodies – Chalagawtha, Kispokotha, Mekoche, Pekowitha, and Thawekila – each of whom contributed a designated social role to the larger tribe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SHAWNEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>By their first appearance in the colonial historical record in 1674, the Shawnees were already travelers. Throughout the following decades, they could be consistently found at the intersections of European and Native American contact, acting as intermediaries between two worlds. They settled up and down the eastern seaboard, often serving as traders, translators, and diplomats. The Shawnee language even became the lingua franca for trade. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SHAWNEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>As the 18th century progressed, antagonism between the colonies and Native peoples grew increasingly potent. Many Shawnees, along with other Algonquian tribes, returned to the Ohio River Valley where their Fort Ancient ancestors had once lived. However, the U.S. colonies continued to push west, seizing territory and pushing tribes from their lands. Several Shawnee war chiefs took a stand against this expansion, most prominently Tecumseh, who formed a major intertribal confederation to unite diverse Native American peoples and repel the U.S. advancement. After his death in battle in 1813, the confederation dispersed, and Shawnees steadily migrated farther west. Today, three federally recognized Shawnee tribes are based in Oklahoma: the Shawnee Tribe, the Absentee Shawnee Tribe, and the Eastern Shawnee Tribe. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- WONDER_SERPENT_MOUND -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_SERPENT_MOUND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>On a plateau in modern-day Ohio, at the site of an ancient crater, indigenous people erected a winding mound in the shape of a great serpent. The site was likely selected because of its unusual terrain and was built up by a variety of different peoples over the course of more than a thousand years, between 320 BCE and 1400 CE. The mound coils across the land, settling into the landscape, and the mouth of the serpent appears to consume an oval object, perhaps an egg (possibly once the site of a temple).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_SERPENT_MOUND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The exact purpose of the mound remains a mystery, given the lack of written records from the time, but the people of this region have long built mounds and held ideas of a great mythological serpent. For example, the Mississippian culture (related but not directly associated with the serpent mound) is famous for its great mound constructions at Cahokia, and the figure of a horned serpent also appears in Shawnee and other mythologies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- IMPROVEMENT_MAWASKAWE_SKOTE-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MAWASKAWE_SKOTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The mawaskawe skote, “council fire,” is the focal point of tribal and intertribal discussion. Historically, the fire was lit when decisions had to be made that impacted the whole Shawnee community, and chosen representatives would congregate to discuss each matter until a resolution was reached. The mawaskawe skote was a space of mutual respect where those affected were given the opportunity to speak and be heard. The maintenance of the fire itself was a sacred practice.  It remains a vital part of Shawnee tradition today. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVICS_SHAWNEE-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SHAWNEE_WYEHI_SIMEKOFI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shawnee communities were organized under a philosophy of wiyehi simekofi, a form of egalitarianism. Most social positions were not hereditary; instead, one’s position was determined by their merits and accomplishments in life, and leadership was shared by several political figures. The administration was divided between a civic leader and a military leader. Civic chiefs were selected from the Chalagawtha clan, and this was a life-long role. Meanwhile, war chiefs were elevated into leadership based on their personal skills and accomplishments . Shawnee villages also had a ruling council of elder men and women who moderated and guided the community.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SHAWNEE_MIYASKA_LATOWEKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Shawnees were travelers, inhabiting settlements and facilitating trade from the Chesapeake Bay to the Savannah River Valley. A significant symbol of their presence was the adoption of the Shawnee language as the dominant trade language – miyaska latoweki, “lingua franca” – across the eastern seaboard. Shawnee, a Central Algonquian language, was considered straightforward to learn by other tribes and colonists alike, allowing it to connect a wide variety of people across cultural lines in an era when such communication was paramount. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SHAWNEE_TELWATIKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Despite a historically small population, the Shawnee had a significant influence on early U.S. history, largely due to their great skill in diplomacy. They thrived in the liminal space between European and Native American worlds, coexisted in the villages of other tribes, and fostered alliances on all sides through their work as traders, guides, and translators. Thanks to their understanding of complex socio-political landscapes, Shawnees leveraged their diplomatic knowledge through telwatiki, the practice of playing parties against one another. By moving the world around them, they ensured the longevity and prosperity of their people. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SHAWNEE_MALEKI_KINTAKE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shawnee settlements were often built in areas that offered natural advantages, usually in ecotones that provided access to a variety of resources. At the same time, the Shawnees sustainably reshaped the land to meet their needs. These maleki kintake (“planned habitats”) maximized the amount of food that could be harvested while promoting regrowth and repopulation of natural bounty. Forest management was a key element of this process. Tree cutting and planned forest fires cleared excess vegetation to create space for agriculture. This space also allowed for the proliferation of berry bushes and other wild food sources that attracted larger animals, like bears and deer, which could be hunted. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_KISPOKO_NENA_TO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shawnee warfare relied as much on knowledge of the land as it did martial prowess. Each kispoko nena’to, “warrior,” trained from a young age to master weaponry and develop a relationship with the woodlands, often through hunting. Shawnee tactics relied largely on ambushes and the use of terrain to gain tactical advantage. Warriors could wait for several days in the same position, motionless in the underbrush, before striking unsuspecting foes. Moving quickly and quietly, unhindered by armor, they blended with the woodlands, emerging to unleash deadly attacks before disappearing as quickly as they had arrived. These strategies amplified the effectiveness of small warbands, enabling them to overcome much larger forces. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_CIVILIAN_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HOCEEPKILENI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The hoceepkileni, “medicine man,” was a spiritual leader among the Shawnee people. They were intermediaries between the physical and metaphysical worlds and guided the community in their relationship with the divine. Healing was an important part of the hoceepkileni’s skills, and physical ailments were treated medicinally and spiritually. However, the hoceepkileni also addressed social tensions and communal disputes, mending divisions within the population. </Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				