<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_EDWARD_TEACH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fear is a weapon. It preceded the Mongol hordes, causing cities to surrender even at the rumor of their approach, and it was vital to Blackbeard’s campaign of piracy across the Caribbean. As his plain red "bloody flag" or his “death’s head flag,” black with a skull (not a devil skeleton piercing a heart as commonly claimed), ran up the mast, ships would give up their cargo rather than face what they feared. The tall, outlandishly-dressed pirate would famously wear lit fuses in his beard – the better to intimidate his foes. But this is Blackbeard, the pirate of imagination, rather than Edward Teach, the man. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_EDWARD_TEACH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Teach – occasionally written “Thatch” – appears in the historical record in New Providence, the base of the short-lived Republic of Pirates in the Caribbean. Before this is only speculation: that he was, for instance, a privateer during Queen Anne’s War (fought between France and Spain over control of North America). Blackbeard served in the short-lived Republic of Pirates under the command of Benjamin Hornigold and quickly acquired conquests and fame – notably taking over the crew of “Gentleman” Stede Bonnet, his former collaborator, when that captain’s authority was questioned.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_EDWARD_TEACH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But the Republic was to falter under pressures both internal and external. As it collapsed, Teach set out on his own, capturing a French vessel and renaming it the Queen Anne’s Revenge, and from its decks he menaced European trade across the New World. In perhaps his most famous exploit, he blockaded Charles Town, in what is now the state of South Carolina, and held its citizens for ransom.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_EDWARD_TEACH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Despite his reputation, Teach could be gracious in conquest, and rarely engaged in the kind of cutlass-swinging deck combat which he became famous for. His captives were well-treated, and he at times showed a great deal of mercy – the threat of violence, and not necessarily violence itself, was his most deadly weapon. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_EDWARD_TEACH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Blackbeard attempted to retire and started a more peaceful life in North Carolina, but his respite lasted only a few months. Though he had secured a royal pardon, he took the Queen Anne’s Revenge out to patrol the Atlantic waters again. On the morning of November 22, 1718, he was attacked and killed by Robert Maynard, a lieutenant in the British Royal Navy. Blackbeard’s head was, allegedly, hung from the bowsprit of Maynard’s flagship, and, North Carolina folklore attests, his ghosts still stalks the Outer Banks.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				