<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_OTTOMANS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In 874 CE, Ingólfr Arnarson gathered his household and set sail from Norway to an uninhabited island in the middle of the North Atlantic Ocean. The land had been discovered some years earlier, first named Snæland (Snow Land), then Garðarshólmi (Garðr’s Island, by a man named Garðr), and finally Ísland (Ice Land) after its immense western glacier. As Ingólfr’s longship approached the coast, he brought out the pillars that accompanied his hall’s high seat and threw them into the sea. Guided by the currents, fate, and perhaps the gods, they drifted ashore near what is today Reykjavík, where Ingólfr built his farm. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Today, medieval Iceland’s claim to fame is of course the Vikings. We will talk about them shortly, but Iceland was much more than a society of raiders. It was a small and sparsely populated island – there were no towns or cities, only rural farms and, later, monasteries. Most of the population were farmers and fishermen, and they lived a difficult existence in a land with few trees, massive glaciers, and active volcanoes. Their houses were built of turf and stone, and they relied on alliances to survive the harsh environment. Yet despite these challenges, the Icelanders remained a fiercely independent and highly scholastic society. They developed a law system and unique proto-parliament to solve social issues as a community; they produced some of the North’s greatest warriors and explorers; they composed some of the finest medieval poems and sagas; and they preserved and iterated on traditional Norse society even as the continental kingdoms transformed into more European-style powers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Iceland’s system of government is key to understanding how the island operated from its settlement. Eschewing a centralized government, the Icelanders allocated power to 39 goðar (sing. goði), chieftains who served as secular and religious leaders in their area. The goðar had many duties: they were arbiters of justice, resolving lawsuits or representing their followers in court; they led local religious ceremonies and maintained temples and later churches; they organized and presided over their local assemblies; and they provided for constituents in need, such as sustaining farmers if a harvest failed. In return for his services, the goði’s followers supported him at the assemblies, lending him legal power. Notably, Icelanders were not locked into their local goði – if they didn’t like the goði in their area, they could choose to swear themselves to another one, or none at all. In this way, the goði’s power was determined not by land, but by population, and the Icelanders were free to follow (or not follow) any leader they chose.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>By the time of Iceland’s settlement, the Viking Age was in full swing, and many men spent their formative years as raiders. In Iceland’s first decades, independent raids were launched from the island, but they were difficult to finance. All raiding parties needed a ship, but because Iceland was (and still is) sparse on trees, obtaining a vessel required importing timber from Norway or purchasing a ship second-hand. Prospective Vikings would band together to buy a ship, each purchasing a share until they communally owned the whole vessel. Later on, as the kingdom of Norway developed into a powerhouse, it became more lucrative for Icelanders to sail to Norway and join the king’s retinue for several years, where they would raid as part of the royal fleet (or wage war on Denmark). For these raids, they did not keep what they personally seized, but they were still paid handsomely by the king. Per the sagas, Icelanders were considered excellent Vikings and were highly valued by the Norwegian kings; but they could also be difficult to manage, because they were unapologetically independent and had little regard for royal trappings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Despite the geographical isolation of their island, Icelanders traveled widely through the known world and beyond, as raiders, mercenaries, merchants, and explorers. To the east, they sailed the coasts and rivers of Europe, from the Baltics to the Mediterranean. To the west, they established a colony in Greenland that lasted several hundred years (before mysteriously disappearing) and from there, became the first Europeans to arrive in North America. They built several temporary settlements along the eastern seaboard to source goods that were otherwise expensive to import from Europe, particularly wood. However, the land was already heavily populated by Native American peoples, with whom the Norse had both peaceful and hostile dealings. No permanent settlements were ever founded. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>At home, Iceland was always a learned society. In addition to the law code that was orally transmitted and recited at the Althing, the island was famous for producing some of the greatest skalds (poets). Old Norse poetry is highly complex, with strict metrical requirements, its own poetic language, and deep references to mythology and legend. The Icelandic skalds were so skilled that they were frequently hired by continental kings as court poets. The Icelanders were also famed composers of sagas. These works were initially passed down orally, but after Iceland converted to Christianity in the year 1000, literacy spread rapidly, and by the end of the 12th century, the period of saga writing was in full swing. The following centuries produced the vast majority of surviving texts that inform us about life during the Viking and Middle Ages across the North Atlantic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Because most scribes were monks or nuns, the earliest texts were religious narratives, translations or adaptations of Latin texts that had arrived from mainland Europe. But other genres began to take hold. The Prose Edda is perhaps the most famous text to come out of medieval Iceland, a poetry manual that contains the only comprehensive summary of Norse mythology that has survived outside of poetry; without it, we would know very little about pre-Christian beliefs. The kings’ sagas are another notable genre that relate the biographies of largely Norwegian monarchs. The most famous of these collections – Heimskringla, Morkinskinna, Flateyjarbók – weave the major tales of the kings with smaller stories about Icelanders abroad. Today, the most widely read genre is the family sagas. These narratives tell of the major families and players in Viking Age Iceland, preserving the history of the island through dramatic tales of blood feuds, romance, outlaws, and complex, memorable characters. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ICELAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>By the 13th century, Iceland’s system of 39 goðar had finally broken down – although the chieftains remained in place, they were sourced from only three families, whose conflict with one another fueled bloodshed across the island (and prompted the largest battle to ever occur on Icelandic soil, in which about 60 people died). At the same time, Norwegian king Hákon Hákonarson made overtures to several prominent Icelanders with the goal of incorporating Iceland as a colony of Norway. In 1262, he succeeded, and Iceland remained under the control of Norway, then Denmark, until 1918. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Constructibles-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_THING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In medieval Iceland, all political and legal dealings were managed communally at assemblies (þing, pronounced “thing”), which occurred at the assembly site (þingstaðr, “thing-stathur”). Many such gatherings occurred throughout the year – local assemblies, quarterly assemblies (Iceland was politically divided into four quarters), and the Althing (Alþingi), the big island-wide assembly that took place in southern Iceland once a year. Local assemblies were presided over by the local chieftain, or goði, who heard and attempted to resolve complaints and problems among his followers, from land ownership disputes and divorce to theft and killings. They were opportunities for rural communities to come together to air concerns, share news, and perform religious rights. To allow for productive dialogue, no bloodshed was permitted on the assembly grounds, and weapons had to be either left behind in booths or, in the case of swords, fastened to the scabbard with special bands (friðbönd, “peace straps”) so they could not be drawn. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_THING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Althing was Iceland’s major annual event, attended by all goðar and as many followers as they could muster (the more followers they had, the more capable they were of winning lawsuits), and took place over several weeks. Issues that had arisen over the course of the year (those too big to handle in the local assemblies) were brought forth before appointed judges so they could be resolved with as little violence as possible. A key figure at the Althing was the lawspeaker, an educated man who was elected for a three-year term. His role was to memorize the oral law code and recite one-third of it every year through his tenure for all to hear. Because so many people gathered at the Althing from all over the country, it was also a place for other business – markets, marriage arrangements, the sharing of news. Its legacy remains strong today: the parliament of Iceland is still called the Althing, and its medieval site, located in a stunning valley where the North American and Eurasian tectonic plates are pulling apart, is one of Iceland’s top tourist attractions. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_REYKHOLT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Reykjaholt (modern name Reykholt) was the farm of chieftain and scholar Snorri Sturluson (1179-1241), one of medieval Iceland’s most prominent figures. He was an active lawyer and politician both at home and abroad, serving as lawspeaker at the Althing before traveling to Norway under invitation of King Hákon Hákonarson, who was bent on incorporating Iceland into his realm. Snorri initially supported Hákon’s movement and promoted it in Iceland, but over time he lost interest in the cause, returning to the lawspeaker role and rising to become the most powerful chieftain in Iceland. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_REYKHOLT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It is during this period (1220-1223) that Reykjaholt became a major scholastic center, and the site was expanded significantly to accommodate the influx of intellectuals. Two significant works are attributed to Snorri: the Prose Edda, a poetry manual containing the most complete surviving summary of Norse mythology, and Heimskringla, a collection of kings’ sagas about the Norwegian monarchs and a critical source on the history of Norway. (The anonymous family saga Egil’s Saga has been suspected to be his work as well). Whether Snorri wrote these texts himself or sponsored scribes to pen them is unknown, but they draw on his skill as a poet and his deep interest in history and scholarship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_REYKHOLT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Snorri’s troubles only grew over time, and conflict with his own relatives chipped away at his authority in the following years. He returned to Norway, but got caught up in a civil war and fled the country. In 1241 he was assassinated in his cellar at Reykjaholt by another goði, Gissur Þorvaldsson, under Hákon’s orders. His famous last words were “Eigi skal höggva!” (Do not strike!)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_REYKHOLT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Today Reykjaholt is home to Snorrastofa, a research and cultural center devoted to Snorri’s work and legacy and general studies on the Icelandic Commonwealth. Little has survived of the medieval settlement, but a geothermal pool, Snorralaug (Snorri’s Bath), remains a notable feature in the landscape. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civics-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_LANDNAMABOK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Landnámabók, the “Book of Settlements,” is an early Icelandic historical text outlining the first decades of the island’s settlement. It relates the discovery of Iceland and lists initial settlers, where they settled, and a genealogy of their lineage interspersed with short anecdotes. In all, several thousand names are preserved, many of which can be cross-referenced and verified elsewhere in the saga corpus. As a result, the text remains a critical source for familial connections during the settlement period and a window into how later Icelanders perceived their own history and ancestors. The text was likely written during the 12th century during the initial period of literacy, though the earliest surviving manuscript dates from the 14th century. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_LANDNAMABOK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The formation of the kingdom of Norway is referenced by Landnámabók as a pressure point spurring settlers to move to Iceland, an event that was characterized as the settlement’s leading cause in later texts. According to the Icelandic saga tradition, as Haraldr hárfagri (Fair-Hair) consolidated his power to become the country’s first king, his enemies faced a losing fight or exile, and many chose Iceland as a new home beyond the reach of monarchs. However, history disagrees with this singular narrative – while Haraldr’s unification may have driven some to Iceland, the island also offered ample land for farming that appealed to those feeling increasingly crowded in Scandinavia, and also offered a haven for the Dublin Norse when they were ousted from Ireland soon after Iceland was settled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_HUGINS_DREKKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Hugins drekka” (Huginn’s banquet) is a kenning, a figure of speech used extensively in Old Norse and Old English poetry in which a multi-word phrase replaces a single word. Kennings range from straightforward (“whale-road” for “ocean”) to complex (“the favorable wind of the moon-bear” for “thought”). They may be purely descriptive or rely on mythological knowledge to interpret. “Huginn’s banquet” falls in the latter category – Huginn is a raven companion of the god Óðinn, and ravens are considered “beasts of battle” (along with eagles and wolves) because they are carrion-eaters. Thus a raven’s banquet is a corpse. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_HUGINS_DREKKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Preserved throughout the literary corpus, poetry was a highly valued craft across the Norse world and exists in two branches, eddic and skaldic. Eddic poetry had fewer rules and was primarily used for mythological and legendary works; it is found almost exclusively in the collection now known as the Poetic Edda. Skaldic poetry was more demanding, requiring not only the mastery of complex metrical, rhyming, and lexical rules, but also thorough knowledge of the mythological and legendary corpus so that proper references could be made. Creativity was key – repetition was discouraged, and approximately 10,000 kennings, mostly unique, survive in the extant poetic corpus. Dróttkvætt (“court meter”) was the most popular and revered skaldic meter, particularly for praise poetry devoted to capturing the impressive deeds of kings and warriors. Iceland was well-known as a consistent source of talented skalds (poets), and they were often recruited by foreign kings as court poets.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_HUGINS_DREKKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Poetry also played an important role in legacy preservation throughout the Viking and Middle Ages. For a society that, during the pre-Christian era, believed in mortal gods and a world that would some day come to a conclusive fiery end, mortality was an accepted part of the human experience. Immortality was earned through the reputation forged during life, as explained in the eddic poem Hávamál: “Cattle die, kinsmen die, the self also dies. I know one thing that never dies: the reputation of each good man.” Poetry was a means to capture the accomplishments of the Norse, preserved for oral transmission so that a person’s memory could live on for generations to come. After the conversion to Christianity, the mythological and legendary references began to fade, and in the 13th century, the Icelandic scholar Snorri Sturluson produced a poetry manual designed to preserve the waning art for future generations. Now called the Prose Edda, it begins with a lengthy summary of the myths that were being forgotten, inadvertently becoming the most complete source for Norse mythology that has survived to the modern day.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_VAERINGJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Norse warriors did not exclusively operate as Viking raiders – they were also highly valued as mercenaries across Europe and beyond. The most famous of these were the Væringjar, members of the Varangian Guard who served the Byzantine Emperors during the 10th and 11th centuries. The unit was founded in 988 CE by Emperor Basil II out of 2,000 Norse and Slavic warriors sent by Prince Vladimir I of Kiev. They were highly regarded as great warriors, often placed in the vanguard during major conflicts and entrusted as the emperor’s bodyguards. The most famous Varangian was Haraldr Sigurðarson, nicknamed harðráði, who later became king of Norway. The only Norseman named in Byzantine sources, he was deployed against the Bulgars in the Balkans and the Arabs in Sicily before returning north to claim his throne. By the mid-11th century, the Norse contingent of the Guard began to shrink, increasingly replaced by Frankish and English warriors until the unit dissolved during the fall of Constantinople in 1204.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_VAERINGJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Despite their immense fame, the history of the Varangians is challenging to unpack, as most of our sources for their activities come centuries later, well after their heyday, from writers who had never met a Varangian or been to Byzantium. Nevertheless, their lasting legacy fascinated both writers and audiences in Iceland during the later Middle Ages. The Mediterranean exploits of Haraldr and his two Icelandic companions, Halldórr Snorrason and Úlfr Óspaksson, proved immensely popular in the kings’ sagas composed in Iceland beginning in the 13th century. The future king’s outsized figure seems to have inspired other saga heroes elsewhere in the corpus, mostly Icelanders, who are often used by writers to explore the aftermath of service in Byzantium – what does it mean to return to rural Iceland after a glorious youth in one of the world’s greatest cities? Sometimes heroic, sometimes tragic, they offer a compelling glimpse into Norse perspectives on combat trauma and the challenges of coming home after military service abroad. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_THJODVELDID_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Icelandic Commonwealth (Þjóðveldið) is the modern term used for the period of Icelandic history between the Althing’s establishment in 930 to the island’s submission to Norway in 1262. These centuries of independence were made possible by Iceland’s unique political and legal systems. While the organization of the goðar avoided the consolidation of power to a single person, Icelandic law provided the structure by which society avoided anarchy. Our major source for these legal codes comes from the quaintly named Grágás (“Grey Goose”) collection of 13th century laws, which contains chapters on everything from land ownership and assembly procedure to homicide. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ICELAND_THJODVELDID_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The importance of the legal system is heavily explored in the family sagas, whose narratives center around what can happen if the law fails to rein in conflict – problems fester, leading to feuds and killings or, in extreme cases, the burning of longhouses with families inside. Yet all sagas witness the characters returning to the law in the end, implementing the code to resolve the conflict and demonstrating the faith in which the Icelandic people had in the system.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The most famous aspect of Icelandic, and more broadly Norse, society is of course the Viking phenomenon. The Vikings (Old Norse víkingar) were the young warriors who sailed abroad each spring to raid the coasts and rivers of, predominantly, Europe. Their attacks were swift and brutal, and were made possible by the technology of their longships. These vessels were low and built around a flexible keel – thus the ship was shallow enough to navigate up rivers and malleable enough to brave the choppy waters of the North Atlantic. Before the longships, there were no warships in Europe that could access rivers, and so these waterways were not well-guarded, instead functioning as natural barriers. The Vikings took advantage of the low security, arriving at dawn to pull their ships up on the shores, rapidly raiding and pillaging before departing a few hours later, faster than the local lord could muster forces in response.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Viking raids served two key functions within Norse society. The primary currency required for social mobility was honor, which could be reliably earned through martial success. Young men raiding during the summers between their mid-teens and mid-twenties could rack up many victories during that time, particularly against defenseless monks and surprised villagers. This was a quick and easy way of earning honor, though it could be obtained in other ways, such as serving as a mercenary or, for those who didn’t leave home, becoming a lawyer and winning the verbal battles of lawsuits. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Raids also enriched the Vikings, not only through money but, more importantly, through rare objects of great value. The North was not home to many valuable resources, but the social fabric of Norse society relied on gift-giving. Viking raids were critical sources of rare and unusual objects , and by the time he retired, a young Viking had ideally built a stockpile of valuable gifts from which he could pull for the rest of his life when he needed to establish or strengthen an alliance. For those who didn’t go raiding, other types of gifts included hosting a feast for someone, composing a poem about them, or crafting some kind of item with one’s own hand.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_2_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The most famous aspect of Icelandic, and more broadly Norse, society is of course the Viking phenomenon. The Vikings (Old Norse víkingar) were the young warriors who sailed abroad each spring to raid the coasts and rivers of, predominantly, Europe. Their attacks were swift and brutal, and were made possible by the technology of their longships. These vessels were low and built around a flexible keel – thus the ship was shallow enough to navigate up rivers and malleable enough to brave the choppy waters of the North Atlantic. Before the longships, there were no warships in Europe that could access rivers, and so these waterways were not well-guarded, instead functioning as natural barriers. The Vikings took advantage of the low security, arriving at dawn to pull their ships up on the shores, rapidly raiding and pillaging before departing a few hours later, faster than the local lord could muster forces in response.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_2_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Viking raids served two key functions within Norse society. The primary currency required for social mobility was honor, which could be reliably earned through martial success. Young men raiding during the summers between their mid-teens and mid-twenties could rack up many victories during that time, particularly against defenseless monks and surprised villagers. This was a quick and easy way of earning honor, though it could be obtained in other ways, such as serving as a mercenary or, for those who didn’t leave home, becoming a lawyer and winning the verbal battles of lawsuits. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_2_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Raids also enriched the Vikings, not only through money but, more importantly, through rare objects of great value. The North was not home to many valuable resources, but the social fabric of Norse society relied on gift-giving. Viking raids were critical sources of rare and unusual objects , and by the time he retired, a young Viking had ideally built a stockpile of valuable gifts from which he could pull for the rest of his life when he needed to establish or strengthen an alliance. For those who didn’t go raiding, other types of gifts included hosting a feast for someone, composing a poem about them, or crafting some kind of item with one’s own hand.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_3_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The most famous aspect of Icelandic, and more broadly Norse, society is of course the Viking phenomenon. The Vikings (Old Norse víkingar) were the young warriors who sailed abroad each spring to raid the coasts and rivers of, predominantly, Europe. Their attacks were swift and brutal, and were made possible by the technology of their longships. These vessels were low and built around a flexible keel – thus the ship was shallow enough to navigate up rivers and malleable enough to brave the choppy waters of the North Atlantic. Before the longships, there were no warships in Europe that could access rivers, and so these waterways were not well-guarded, instead functioning as natural barriers. The Vikings took advantage of the low security, arriving at dawn to pull their ships up on the shores, rapidly raiding and pillaging before departing a few hours later, faster than the local lord could muster forces in response.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_3_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Viking raids served two key functions within Norse society. The primary currency required for social mobility was honor, which could be reliably earned through martial success. Young men raiding during the summers between their mid-teens and mid-twenties could rack up many victories during that time, particularly against defenseless monks and surprised villagers. This was a quick and easy way of earning honor, though it could be obtained in other ways, such as serving as a mercenary or, for those who didn’t leave home, becoming a lawyer and winning the verbal battles of lawsuits. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIKINGR_3_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Raids also enriched the Vikings, not only through money but, more importantly, through rare objects of great value. The North was not home to many valuable resources, but the social fabric of Norse society relied on gift-giving. Viking raids were critical sources of rare and unusual objects , and by the time he retired, a young Viking had ideally built a stockpile of valuable gifts from which he could pull for the rest of his life when he needed to establish or strengthen an alliance. For those who didn’t go raiding, other types of gifts included hosting a feast for someone, composing a poem about them, or crafting some kind of item with one’s own hand.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SAGA_HERO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The sagas are the major native written works of Iceland composed in the centuries following the island’s conversion to Christianity. These texts have survived in many genres – kings’ sagas, legendary sagas, saints’ sagas, bishops’ sagas, chivalric sagas, contemporary sagas. But the most famous, and the most widely read today, are the family sagas, or Íslendingasögur (sagas of the Icelanders). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SAGA_HERO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The family sagas are tales of feuds between major families in Viking Age Iceland, relating events that were passed down orally for two to three centuries before their preservation in the manuscripts. They explore the boundaries of order and violence in Iceland, and often follow a common narrative – an inciting incident sparks conflict that pings back and forth between two factions until it can no longer be contained by the law and explodes in a bloody climax; surviving characters then work to reign in the hostilities, and the saga ends when equilibrium and peace are reached once more. Rich in violence, adventure, romance, and the supernatural, each saga is distinct in its characters, themes, and actions, spotlighting the notable men and women of the Viking Age. The crown jewel of the family sagas is the immense Njáls saga; other major works include Egils saga, Laxdæla saga, Gísla saga, and the Vinland sagas, which relate the Norse voyages to North America. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SAGA_HERO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The vast majority of medieval Nordic manuscripts that survive today are Icelandic; far fewer exist from Norway, Denmark, and Sweden. This success rate hinges on the work of Árni Magnússon, a scholar who traveled around Iceland collecting manuscripts in the 18th century. As a result of the overwhelming Icelandic voice in extant historical sources, our understanding of the medieval North largely comes via the Icelandic lens.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				