<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
    <EnglishText>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11134A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Fury of the Norse</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11134A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In the morning fog, víkingar leap out of dragonheaded ships, ready for bloodshed. Shouts and screams rend the dawn air, flames grab angrily at the sky, the tang of blood catches on the wind. And then, as quickly as they arrived, the Icelanders are gone, ships laden with plunder, leaving only smoke, death, and silence.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11134B_NAME">
            <Text>This is the path to Valhalla.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11134B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11134C_NAME">
            <Text>Seized treasures make good gifts back home.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11134C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11135A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Famous Last Words</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11135A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In the chaos of war, Icelandic víkingar seek immortality through reputation and an honorable death in battle. Leading the charge, a chieftain swings his axe ferociously, hitting mark after mark until finally a spear pierces his chest. "Broad spears are in fashion these days," he says, and falls down dead.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11135B_NAME">
            <Text>A runestone will preserve his name.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11135B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Wonders.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11135C_NAME">
            <Text>A poem will spread his deeds.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11135C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>+2[icon:YIELD_CULTURE] Culture for every active Trade Route.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11136A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>A Varangian Veteran</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11136A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>An Icelandic farmer sits on a hill, a gilded sword in his lap, surrendering himself to the memories of youth. A splendid city in a far-off land. His mercenary brothers laughing over ale. The blood and screams of countless battles. He is home now, yet still he yearns for that other home, the one across the waves.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11136B_NAME">
            <Text>Warriors should be supported upon their return.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11136B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11136C_NAME">
            <Text>Legends stand on their own two feet.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11136C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on all Commanders.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11137A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Jakúlus</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11137A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>A monk furiously scribbles on fresh vellum, composing a new saga about a legendary king searching for Paradise. Many dangers and foes await, but the monk is running out of inspiration. He casts an eye over a nearby Roman bestiary and peers closely at a grisly list of serpents sourced from an ancient poet. Yes, yes, this will do...</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11137B_NAME">
            <Text>Real monsters are more compelling than fantastic ones.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11137B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11137C_NAME">
            <Text>What if this serpent had wings, and spewed venom...?</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11137C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11138A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>At the Alþingi</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11138A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Standing upon the Law Rock, the young lawspeaker fidgets as he watches the large crowd gather before him. He has spent many months memorizing the law code, carefully trained by his predecessor. His recitation must be precise and accurate, for with law, Iceland rises, and without it, Iceland falls. He takes a deep breath and begins his performance.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11138B_NAME">
            <Text>Recitation makes these laws communal.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11138B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11138C_NAME">
            <Text>The laws should be written down for private consultation.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11138C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11139A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>A Haunting at Hrappsstaðr</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11139A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Laborers on an Icelandic farm complain that they are being terrorized by a draugr. The farm's former owner had requested upon his death to be buried standing up beneath the kitchen doorway, and now he rises every night to wrestle his servants.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11139B_NAME">
            <Text>The farmer must be reburied the proper way.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11139B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11139C_NAME">
            <Text>A great warrior could take on this menace.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11139C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} Saga Heroes.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Mead of Poetry</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In longhouses, at assemblies, in royal courts abroad, Icelandic poetry abounds, with its unique language of kennings. Once-simple substitutions – “wave-horse” for ship, “Sif’s hair” for gold – increase their complexity as skalds push their craft to new heights. When one produces “the dark betrayer of the wood-bear of old walls,” the audience concludes this must refer to…</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140B_NAME">
            <Text>Time.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>Story continues.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140C_NAME">
            <Text>The devil.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>Story continues.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140D_NAME">
            <Text>A cat.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11140D_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>Story continues.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11141A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Mead of Poetry</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11141A_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}, but {2_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11141A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>The skald shakes his head as he listens to his audience marveling at his kenning. “I’m not talking about time,” he chides. “Have you no respect for my craft?”</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11142A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Mead of Poetry</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11142A_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}, but {2_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11143A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Mead of Poetry</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11142A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>The audience praises the skald on his kenning for the devil. “But it doesn't refer to the devil,” he says, confused, but accepts the accolades regardless.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11143A_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11143A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>The skald finishes his lengthy kenning just as its subject, a large cat, leaps up on the table in front of him, stretches, and snags a piece of roasted meat with one long, sharp claw.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Snorri's Legacy</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Amid billows of steam rising from Reykjaholt's geothermal pool, the scholar leans back to contemplate the sky. The old myths and legends are fading in the face of new beliefs, and with them the language of poetry. But the kings across the sea have such interesting genealogy…He sits up with a splash, already formulating his next manuscript as he calls out to his scribes.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144B_NAME">
            <Text>A poetry manual, to preserve this marvelous craft.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144C_NAME">
            <Text>A history of kings, full of adventure and politics.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144D_NAME">
            <Text>An epic saga of the hero Egill Skallagrímsson.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11144D_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11147A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Worst Kind of Host</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11147A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Inside the longhouse, the hearth burns bright, laughter rises with the smoke, and the ale runs freely. A drinking horn presses into Egill’s large hand, and he catches the lady's nod – a gift. But something is wrong. There’s more than ale in this vessel. Egill drags his knife over the horn, scoring it with runes, and the horn shatters.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11147B_NAME">
            <Text>Poison must be repaid in blood.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11147B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Naval Units.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11147C_NAME">
            <Text>Escape first, vengeance later.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11147C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Víkingar.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11148A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Höfuðlausn</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11148A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Egill sits at the window, contemplating his fate. The lord's son is dead by his hand, and now Egill’s own head is on the line, unless he can craft a mighty gift – a poem to the lord's achievements and prowess in battle, verses to be remembered for centuries. If only this bird would stop distracting him.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11148B_NAME">
            <Text>Creativity cannot be stemmed by shapeshifters.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11148B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11148C_NAME">
            <Text>Perhaps a friend can ward the creature off.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11148C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11149A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Grásiða’s Bite</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11149A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In the black of night, Gísli stands in the door of the sleeping longhouse. One hand grips the spear so recently pulled from his brother-in-law’s corpse. Gathering rushes from the floor, he silently casts them at the flickering torches, one by one, until the hall falls into darkness. Gísli treads softly to the bed by the hearth and in a single motion drives the spear down, to vengeance.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11149B_NAME">
            <Text>Blood for blood.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11149B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Infantry Units.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11149C_NAME">
            <Text>Murder leads only to outlawry.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11149C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11150A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>In Pursuit</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11150A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Men pursuing the outlaw Gísli track him to a small homestead. As they hunt their quarry, the farmer’s wife scolds them from her bed, with language so foul they will be unlikely to ever forget it. Distracted by her abuse, they search less carefully than planned, leaving empty-handed and thoroughly chastised. The woman rises from her bed and lifts the covers, and Gísli rolls out with a smile.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11150B_NAME">
            <Text>Trickery is vital to an outlaw's survival.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11150B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Commanders.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11150C_NAME">
            <Text>Great warriors do not resort to deceit.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11150C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Infantry Units.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11151A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Eyes of Glámr</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11151A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In the dark hall, Grettir fights for his life. Beams crack and benches shatter as the two figures grapple furiously. The stench of undeath is overwhelming as Grettir shoves his powerful foe, sending them both tumbling out the door. As the moon emerges from the clouds, he gazes into gleaming eyes and, for a moment, trembles. Victory must be his tonight – but at what cost?</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11151B_NAME">
            <Text>Grettir's strength is unmatched.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11151B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} Víkingar.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11151C_NAME">
            <Text>The price of fighting draugar is deadly in time.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11151C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Víkingar.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11152A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Outlaw</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11152A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Rain falls on a cold island as Grettir the outlaw tends to his wounded leg. Ill fortune has dogged him since his victory over the draugr many years ago, and this injury, a witch’s work, may be his end. His strength wanes, and as night falls, his fear of the coming darkness grows. Only one year until his outlawry ends...if he survives.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11152B_NAME">
            <Text>There is still time for a final stand.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11152B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Ranged Units.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11152C_NAME">
            <Text>The age of heroes is ending.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11152C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11153A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Swimming Contest</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11153A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Beneath the calm surface of the river, two men wrestle, each striving to hold the other underwater. Finally they both give, emerging together to declare the competition a draw. Kjartan regards his opponent – a stranger with royal bearing, who offers his own fine cloak out of respect.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11153B_NAME">
            <Text>This gift will impress those at home.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11153B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} in Cities.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11153C_NAME">
            <Text>It bodes ill to be in a king’s debt.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11153C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}, but {2_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11154A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>A Perilous Journey</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11154A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Kjartan’s mind is troubled. Valuable items have gone missing from his hall, and his suspicions fall on his foster-brother – or rather, his wife, Kjartan’s old flame. Tensions are boiling over, and his men dream of approaching death. But as he rides over the heath, he knows he has nothing to fear from his foster-brother, so long as he is not goaded to action.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11154B_NAME">
            <Text>Brotherly love will win in the end.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11154B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} in all Settlements.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11154C_NAME">
            <Text>An ambush will be easy enough to defeat.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11154C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11155A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Dreamer</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11155A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Guðrún wakes suddenly in the dim light of dawn, surrounded by sleepers in the longhouse. Once again, her dreams have disturbed her. A headdress fallen in a stream; a silver ring lost in a lake; a gold ring broken and bleeding; a gold helmet sinking into the sea.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11155B_NAME">
            <Text>These are portents of future marriages.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11155B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11155C_NAME">
            <Text>They are warnings, nothing more.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11155C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11156A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Scorekeeper</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11156A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Guðrún stands in her leek garden. Laid out carefully on the ground around her are the clothes in which her husband was slain. Her young sons approach, and she motions to the stained garments. “These clothes condemn your inaction,” she tells them. “You care more for horse-fights than avenging your father.”</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11156B_NAME">
            <Text>The boys should know their task without reminding.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11156B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Cavalry Units.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11156C_NAME">
            <Text>It is a woman's duty to keep the score.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11156C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11157A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>A Sacred Oath</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11157A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Hrafnkell looks up from his meal as a loud whinny echoes around the farm. He recognizes the call of his horse Freyfaxi, dedicated to his god through a sacred oath, never to be ridden on pain of death. But here is the animal, coat drenched in sweat and mud. Someone has ridden him. The god will be angry. Hrafnkell fetches his axe.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11157B_NAME">
            <Text>Oaths are contracts that hold society together.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11157B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11157C_NAME">
            <Text>Perhaps the god will be merciful.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11157C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11158A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Freyfaxahamar</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11158A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Once, Hrafnkell was a powerful man, master of his fjord. Now he must start anew, cheated in the law court out of his home, his possessions, his reputation. One day he will find vengeance, but through his own power, not that of his god. Upholding his sacred oath has brought him nothing but pain, and when news arrives of his sacred horse's death, he swears off gods for good.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11158B_NAME">
            <Text>Worshipping gods is an act of vanity.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11158B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11158C_NAME">
            <Text>Gods are fickle, but devotion pays off.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11158C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11159A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Shepherds</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11159A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Njáll wakes in the dead of night to the scraping of metal. He peers out of the bed-closet to see his sons arming themselves, and inquires where they are going at this hour. “We are hunting sheep,” says his eldest with a wolfish smile. “You’ve told me that before,” Njáll replies, “but then, you were hunting men.”</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11159B_NAME">
            <Text>Peace must be prioritized above all.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11159B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11159C_NAME">
            <Text>Some matters can only be settled with violence.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11159C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11160A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Doomed Man</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11160A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Njáll lies still in his bed, his wife beside him, their grandson between. Beneath the heavy oxhide, he sees only darkness. But the smell of smoke is strong. He hears his sons shouting to one another above the roar of flames, thrusting swords and spears at the attackers outside, falling silent one by one, deaths he can never avenge. Pulling his loved ones close, he shuts his eyes.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11160B_NAME">
            <Text>There is no honor in burning a longhouse.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11160B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}, but {2_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11160C_NAME">
            <Text>When the law fails, chaos reigns.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11160C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}, but {2_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11161A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Sowing Lies</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11161A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Despite the fame he has earned as Iceland’s greatest warrior, Gunnarr longs for a life of peace. He brushes off the insults of his pot-stirring neighbors, refusing to rise to the bait. But when those insults turn to lies, threatening his reputation, he takes up his halberd, which sings to the coming bloodshed.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11161B_NAME">
            <Text>Insults can destroy a man's legacy.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11161B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Infantry Units.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11161C_NAME">
            <Text>Gunnarr's actions must be resolved in court.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11161C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11162A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Pale Fields</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11162A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Gunnarr's household waves him off as he departs for his longship. His sentence of lesser outlawry means three years abroad, three years before he can come home again. Yet as his horse stumbles, Gunnarr catches a final glimpse of his farm. "Lovely is this hillside," he muses. "Never has it looked so beautiful as it does now." He turns around, heading for home, and death.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11162B_NAME">
            <Text>Close.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11162B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} in all Settlements.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11163A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Seeress</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11163A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Hard times befall Norse farmers, and many strive to know its cause. A seeress is summoned, an aging woman bearing a brass-topped staff and swathed in a black cloak and white catskin gloves. Guðríðr knows the old ward-chants, but she has sworn herself to a new god, and hesitates to join the rites.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11163B_NAME">
            <Text>The people need familiar comfort.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11163B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} in all Settlements.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11163C_NAME">
            <Text>The old ways must be laid to rest.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11163C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} in all Settlements.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11164A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>A Fetch</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11164A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In a land far from Iceland, Guðríðr sits next to her infant son as her husband and his followers trade food with the locals. Suddenly a strange woman slips into the house, short and with immense eyes. “My name is Guðríðr, what is yours?” says Guðríðr. “My name is Guðríðr,” replies the woman. Suddenly a crash comes from outside, and the woman vanishes.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11164B_NAME">
            <Text>A strange friend in a strange land.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11164B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} in Distant Lands Settlements.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11164C_NAME">
            <Text>A herald of ill omen.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11164C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} all Units in Distant Lands Settlements.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11165A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Destination: Vinland</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11165A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Freydís stands on the dock, directing the stocking of the longships. Sailors scurry before her loud commands, bearing food and supplies for the long journey to distant shores.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11165B_NAME">
            <Text>This is an opportunity for adventure.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11165B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>Story continues.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11165C_NAME">
            <Text>This is a raiding expedition.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11165C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>Story continues.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11166A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Eiríks Saga Rauða</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11166A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In a distant land, Freydís staggers after her fleeing companions, heavily pregnant and cursing their cowardice. As the attackers close in, she bends to a fallen Norseman, seizing his sword and spinning around. In a swift motion she bares her chest and slaps it with the naked blade. Her alarmed foes immediately turn tail and run.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11166B_NAME">
            <Text>Close.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11166B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Víkingar, but {2_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11167A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Grœnlendinga Saga</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11167A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Early morning dew soaks the bare feet of the Norse explorers, bound and shoved out of their longhouse. One by one they are slain at Freydís' command, once her travel companions to a far-off land...now, at her whim, her victims. Finally only the women remain. Freydís raises her axe.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11167B_NAME">
            <Text>Close.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11167B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}, but {2_reward} in Distant Lands Settlements.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11168A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>A Rumor from Afar</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11168A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Esteemed ruler: I have heard a rumor from a passing pilgrim that Paradise has been found – in India! If such a tale is true, there is much to be learned from this holy place…but I also worry that Paradise is not meant for human eyes. Yours in faith, Eirekr</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11168B_NAME">
            <Text>Send Eirekr to find Paradise.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11168B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11168C_NAME">
            <Text>Honor the mystery of utopia.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11168C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11169A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Great Serpent</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11169A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Esteemed ruler: The lands have changed greatly, and there are many wonders to behold. Greatest among them is a dragon! He sits upon my path, growling and roaring at the wind. My journey calls to me…yet I fear to approach him. Yours in faith, Eirekr the Traveler</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11169B_NAME">
            <Text>Approach the dragon.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11169B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11169C_NAME">
            <Text>Return home.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11169C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11170A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>An Unexpected Spirit</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11170A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Esteemed ruler: As I approached the dragon, the strangest thing occurred – his maw opened wide, and I stepped through into a land of milk and honey. Within, I was welcomed by my guardian angel, a quaint being who gifted me with spiritual instruction to last many lifetimes. I eagerly return home to share these teachings. Yours in faith, Eirekr the Far-Traveler</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11170B_NAME">
            <Text>Close.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11170B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11171A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Road to Wisdom</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11171A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Esteemed ruler: Though I have turned away from the dragon, and my path, I return home with knowledge gathered from my voyage. May these insights enrich the people and ensure their continued quest for spiritual wisdom. Yours in faith, Eirekr the Far-Traveler</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11171B_NAME">
            <Text>Close.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11171B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_12014A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Dr Rizal at the Althing</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_12014A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Dr Rizal takes a seat at the summer assembly, where laws are adopted and disputes settled. Today, a chieftain has called for his rival to end their longstanding blood feud. But the opposing chieftain insists that the initial wrong has not yet been rectified.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_12014B_NAME">
            <Text>Wrongs must be righted.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_12014B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward} on Cogs.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_12014C_NAME">
            <Text>Blood is too costly a solution.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_12014C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11145A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>The Prose Edda</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11145A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>In a collection of old Icelandic manuscripts, a scholar discovers a manual for a long-lost poetic tradition. Perusing its leaves, she realizes it includes a summary of medieval Norse mythology. Originally meant for skalds as a source of poetic references, now it offers a valued window into a vanished religion.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11145B_NAME">
            <Text>Modern readers will treasure these myths.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11145B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11145C_NAME">
            <Text>It is time for skaldic poetry to make a comeback.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11145C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11146A_STORYTITLE">
            <Text>Heimskringla</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11146A_COMPLETION">
            <Text>Academics pore over a new edition of a medieval Icelandic collection of kings’ sagas. The text recounts stories of distant rulers, but the Icelandic lens is ever-present, and their skilled skalds and insolent yet daring heroes draw readers’ attention amid the royal trappings.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11146B_NAME">
            <Text>These sagas preserve much about other lands' histories.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11146B_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11146C_NAME">
            <Text>These tales capture how Icelanders saw themselves.</Text>
        </Row>
        <Row Tag="LOC_11146C_DESCRIPTION">
            <Text>{1_reward}.</Text>
        </Row>
    </EnglishText>
</Database>
