<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mongols had a long history of invading the lands bordering their native steppes. Their nomadic ways led them to wander vast distances, and their mastery of the art of war inspired terror in all those unfortunate enough to live in their path. But one khan united the tribes like never before, vanquishing a territory so vast that his empire remains one of the largest in history, and wreaking so much devastation that his name is still synonymous with conquest today. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Genghis Khan needs no real introduction, but despite his fame, there are very few sources that accurately cover his life. The most important, and thorough, is the posthumous Secret History of the Mongols, the oldest written text in Mongolian, which covers Genghis Khan’s life from mythical origins to his death. Beyond that, the Mongols produced a very small body of literature, while a significant number of texts about the Mongols were written by their victims, whose displeasure at their violent incursions casts a biased lens on their accounts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>What we do know about Genghis Khan: He was born Temüjin in 1155…or 1162…or 1167. He was the son of a chieftain, Yesügei. Later legends attest that Temüjin’s birth heralded his future greatness, because he emerged holding a blood clot in his hand. However, his childhood was not easy. When he was nine, his father was poisoned by the Tartars, after which his clan quickly dispersed, leaving behind Temüjin, his siblings, and his widowed mother Höelün.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Several apocryphal stories tell of early demonstrations of young Temüjin’s natural authority and charisma, but his story really picks up when he formed an alliance with a khan of another tribe, Toghril, who gave him an army of 20,000 warriors with which to reclaim his tribe. Temüjin began to eliminate his rivals one clan at a time, wiping out the nobility and incorporating the remaining people into his own tribe. Eventually he grew so powerful that he felt confident confronting the Tartars who had killed his father. Upon achieving victory, he killed anyone who was taller than the axle of a cart, and took the rest with him.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>These initial successes on the steppes developed Temüjin’s method of conquest on two fronts. First, he never left an enemy behind – complete annihilation of the leadership was the only way to guarantee that they wouldn’t come back to seek revenge. Second, the incorporation of the defeated tribes’ populations not only boosted his own ranks, but also broke down allegiances and cultural barriers by uniting the people under a single banner. Specifically, his own.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>But despite this meteoric rise to power, trouble was never far away. A rift appeared between Temüjin and his longtime ally and childhood friend Jamuka, a rivalry that is in some ways exaggerated by the Secret History and other sources. But the competition between them was ultimately fierce and divided the Mongols, who allied themselves with whichever leader they viewed as stronger. Even Temüjin’s first ally, Toghril, ultimately chose to back Jamuka. This choice would prove his downfall – Temüjin crushed Toghril and, as with all his other opponents, executed the elite and absorbed the populace. Others tried and failed to stop his momentum, but none prevailed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Several bloody years later, Jamuka was captured and executed, and in 1206, with no one left to challenge his authority, Temüjin was declared ruler of the steppes and took the title of Genghis Khan. The name has proven difficult to translate – a common interpretation posits its meaning as something like “Universal Ruler.” Genghis Khan’s first move was to reorganize his massive following. This involved replacing existing tribal leadership with a network of his own family members and trusted close associates to consolidate his authority across the population.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>He also gave particular focus to the organization of the army, which was divided according to the decimal system (units of 10, 100, 1,000, and 10,000 soldiers) led by his sons and most trusted allies. His earlier forces consisted entirely of fast-moving cavalry, effective against other nomadic steppe tribes. But Genghis Khan had bigger visions for the future. He had come to understand the value of settlements and the benefits therein – the wealth and power that could be cultivated from sedentary populations and their merchants, artisans, and agricultural harvests. To conquer settlements, the Mongol army had to evolve. And it did, very quickly developing siege weapons and mastering tactics effective against even the most well-defended cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Now that the consolidation of power within the Mongol Empire was complete, it was time to look outward. Genghis Khan’s first target was China, against whom his new military formula was extremely successful, and he overran the northern Jin Empire over the course of four years. Provoked by the massacre of a caravan under his protection, Genghis Khan soon turned his attention west to the Khwarazmian Empire, south of the Aral Sea. This campaign lasted between 1219 and 1221, and gave the Mongols their vicious reputation. Thousands were massacred, while prisoners were forced to serve in the vanguard of the Mongol army in future battles against their own fellow Khwarazms. In addition to plundering the cities they defeated, the Mongol army also destroyed infrastructure, both urban and agricultural, devastating Khwarazm and bringing down a once-mighty empire in just two years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>After the fall of Khwarazm, Genghis Khan returned to Mongolia and prepared to invade China once more, when the previously conquered Xia began to rebel. As before, his army swept through and quickly crushed all opposing forces. Not long after, in 1227, Genghis Khan succumbed to an illness. The nature of his death is a matter of debate, with theories ranging from consequences of an old injury from falling off his horse to a case of bubonic plague. The location of Genghis Khan’s burial site is unknown, and is one of the great mysteries of history. </Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				