<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Trade in the 17th and early 18th century moved immense amounts of wealth through uncontrolled, unpredictable regions. Galleons, however fearsome, were the mercy of wind and water… and whoever was bold enough to attempt to seize them. Were this not already an enticement to piracy, the powers of the day fostered independent raiders – privateers - as a means of cutting off their rivals’ revenue. But these privateers could just as quickly turn pirate if the opportunity presented itself. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1694, the Charles II waited in port in the Spanish city of Corunna, and its crew grumbled. The Spanish crown had promised a letter of marque enabling the Charles II to attack and plunder Spain’s rivals, but the letter had yet to arrive. When the crew’s wages, too, failed to come, the crew mutinied and, under former first mate Henry Every, seized the ship and sailed it to attack and plunder with or without a letter. They, in other words, “went on account,” went pirate. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Fancy, as the Charles II was rechristened, sailed to the Indian Ocean and took an impressive prize: the Ganj-i-Sawai and Fateh Muhammad, Mughal vessels carrying a fortune in gold and jewels. Every took this wealth and sailed to Nassau (in the present-day Bahamas), where he bribed the English governor to turn a blind eye towards the pirates. Not that the governor had much of a choice - he was the administrator of a distant colony of a minor (at that point) European power, and here under Every was a battle-hardened force armed to the teeth, offering him a fortune to simply do nothing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But with this new deal, pirates flooded into Nassau and, as the civilian population dwindled, Nassau (called, more often, Providence) became a pirate town. Benjamin Hornigold, an English privateer, formed the “Flying Gang”, a band of pirates that operated out of the city and flew the death’s head flag, and whose members boasted names such as Edward “Blackbeard” Teach, “Calico” Jack Rackham, Anne Bonny, Henry Jennings, Mary Read, as well as the republic’s self-appointed governor, Thomas Barrow.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The ”republic” (its name comes from a 2007 book by the historian Colin Woodard; its members referred to their city as Providence and their ships as the Flying Gang) operated on a certain code, one shared by many in the sea at that time. This was a system of consensual autocracy: the captain was the sole dictator of their ship, but, upon enlisting, potential crewmembers agreed to follow and expect certain terms: sharing of all plunder, a system of insurance for those wounded in battle, a vote in important matters, equal access to food and drink. But there were limitations as well: lights onboard were to be put out by eight PM, gambling and the bringing of women onboard ship were forbidden (though Bonny and Read’s presence suggests that this was not universal), and the forbidding of music on Sundays were common.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The pirates of the Republic were drawn mostly from English ships, and Hornigold’s refusal to attack English vessels was a common cause for complaint by many pirates under him. However, in addition to Englishmen (and a few women), there were a sizeable number of pirates from the United States, from Caribbean settlements or Europe, or even from the East Indies. The makeup of pirate crews was more diverse than navies at the time; estimates suggest that roughly 25-30 percent of pirates were of African ancestry and, although pirates considered enslaved people found in the holds of ships to be cargo that could be stolen and sold, free Black crewmembers seem to have been treated relatively equally. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Providence proved an embarrassment for England, and a threat to all legal commerce in the region. King George I sought its destruction via two means: a pardon for all who turned themselves in, and a relentless counterattack towards all who would not. Upon hearing this, roughly half of the pirates surrendered, including Hornigold – who immediately was placed in charge of hunting his former proteges.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The shattering of the Republic led to the “Golden Age” of piracy in the Caribbean, as the now-decentralized pirates dispersed to make their fortune in every corner of the sea.</Text>
		</Row>
		
		<!--Constructibles-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HAVANA_HARBOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Havana was one of the most significant settlements in the colonial Caribbean, and one of the hearts of Spanish power in the region. An excellent harbor just at the beginning point of the Gulf Stream – that warm current of water that served as a highway leading back to Europe (not to mention the reason for Europe’s warm climate relative to other places at its latitude), the harbor at Havana was geographically situated to extend power across the major and minor islands of the region, and beyond. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HAVANA_HARBOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As such, it was the place where treasure fleets would assemble before making the dangerous trip back to Spain. The Crown thought that a fortified fleet would prove better protected from the pirates that even by the 16th century had begun to plague the area. This calculation proved true… but also made the fleet a tempting prize for any who might take it. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HAVANA_HARBOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Fortifications began in the harbor in 1553, and were expanded as the English, French and Dutch presence in the region grew. The fortress fell to an English siege in 1762, but remained formidable throughout the age of sail, and beyond. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HAVANA_HARBOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Havana became the capital of an independent Cuba in 1902, though the utility of sea fortresses has waned in an era of cruise missiles and stealth bombers. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_NAVAL_ARSENAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A naval arsenal is a structure for the repair and construction of naval vessels, and is a major outpost of naval power for seafaring nations. But the Republic of Pirates was no such nation. Historically, the Republic was a short-lived takeover of a minor colonial outpost. Its navy – if such a term can come to be used for such an unorganized mass of independent actors – was made up of stolen ships crewed by people of dozens of nations. As such, it did not command a naval arsenal – ship construction (rather than theft) was not a feature of New Providence, and repairs were done in shallow water in the harbor. But were the Republic to grow and expand, it might have made its own arsenal, raising a vital challenge against the powers of the seafaring nations. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_NAVAL_STATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If the arsenal is the building for ships’ construction, the station (or, simply, naval base) is a building for ships’ restock and resupply. These could be major installations or smaller outposts to assist a ship on its voyage. Even with a perfectly sound ship, even with powder kept secure and dry, crews needed their own maintenance – seawater cannot be drunk, and rations needed to be stocked. Further, before 1747, the scourge of scurvy seemed to visit all who stayed on the sea for too long and failed to come into port from time to time (the solution to scurvy, of course, was a lack of vitamin C – a shipboard diet of cured meat and bread contained no fresh fruit or vegetables), thus making well-stocked naval stations vital for the maintenance of naval power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_HAVEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The governors of colonial cities faced challenges. They were reliant upon protection from powers based an ocean away, often in the middle of territory partially controlled by rival nations and the indigenous inhabitants who resented their presence – all the while sitting upon vast potential wealth. Is it any wonder that many struck deals with pirates for protection, for supplies, or just for wealth? </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_HAVEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the Caribbean, Tortuga, New Providence, and Port Royal were famous havens. In Africa, St. Mary’s Island supplied pirates working the Indian Ocean trade, and in Indonesia, Sulawesi and the Sulu islands were likewise pirate havens. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civics-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_ARTICLES_OF_AGREEMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“To go on account” meant, in the pirate lingo of the early 18th century, to sign up to be a pirate. And what one signed would be the Articles of Agreement. Also often called a “pirate code,” this was a list of rules that bound crew and captain in a sort of limited autocracy while the ship was at sea, a bubble of alternate governance unbound to nation or land. Signing the Articles also marked one as being a pirate in the eyes of the imperial powers of the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_ARTICLES_OF_AGREEMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>These varied often from ship to ship, but often contained a certain amount of rights. Pirates who signed the Articles could vote for important decisions and be assured of a share of plunder, but were also bound by rules while on board: no uncovered pipes below-decks, no music on Sundays, no women on board, no quarrels. At times, the democratic provisions in the Articles were far freer than that of imperial navies at the time, and this idea of independence and guaranteed rights were a draw for many who had faced abuse at the hands of a British or French naval captain. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_PORTS_OF_CALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The sea can be a hostile place. Ships damaged by battle or storms or running low on supplies needed places where they could securely rest, restock and repair. For pirates, the risks were increased, as such a place needed to be hidden from naval patrols and distant from the bureaucratic reach of imperial powers. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_PORTS_OF_CALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But such places existed. Pirate waters lay especially where geography became difficult – around warrens of narrow channels and treacherous islands, near major shipping lanes. The Sulu Archipleagio, for instance, in present-day Indonesia; Madagascar, near where ships would round the Cape of Good Hope and head north towards Asia; and, of course, the Caribbean. In some places, such as Port Royal or New Providence, pirates could pay colonial authorities to turn a blind eye to their activities; in others, local powers resistant to major European trade networks might encourage pirate activity. Each would provide a valuable port of call for raiders seeking rest and resupply. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_PIRATE_REPUBLIC_ENEMY_OF_ALL_NATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Colonialism needed sea lanes. The wealth mined, grown, or plundered in colonies was concentrated, loaded onto ships and sent across thousands of miles of trackless sea towards the mother country (or, in the case of the Manila trade, sent to trade with China). Unlike rival powers, who might seek to dominate the colonial system, and unlike independence movements that sought to build systems of their own, piracy attacked its very existence. Thus, pirates have since ancient times been categorized by states as, in Latin, “hostis humani generis,” enemies of all, opening pirates up to attack and retribution by any power. Pirates, of course, saw themselves differently – occasionally as lovers of freedom, or occasionally (as Henry Avery put it) as men “of fortune, (who) must seek their fortune.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_CIVILIAN-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BUCCANEER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A buccaneer is a general term for a pirate, but the word itself has an etymology that extends beyond. In the 17th century, as livestock from colonial settlements escaped and grew feral, Hispaniola gained a population of wild pigs – and some settlers, too, escaped and grew feral. These outlaws were named “buccaneers,” after the Arawak word (buccan) for a meat-grilling stand. By the time that more Europeans had arrived in the area, the word had come to mean anyone living off of brigandry and piracy – especially as colonial authorities tried to eradicate these lawless individuals and their feral prey and many sought employment and gain by plunder. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SLOOP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>On the horizon, a sloop is almost immediately recognizable – a triangular mass of sails almost obscuring the thin, knifelike hull beneath. Defined mostly by its rigging – a single mast with a mainsail, and a sail or sails mounted in the fore, a sloop is built for speed. Its shallow draft meant that it could sail across treacherous waters where more heavily-built ships might founder, and the extensive sails meant that it was extremely fast. It may have lacked the heavy cargo holds or firepower of a larger ship, but the sloop was perfect for quick raids – and quick escapes. </Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				