<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAKSHMIBAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Jhansi was a small state in north-central India, historically independent and bolstered by alliances with powerful empires nearby, particularly the Mughals. In 1740, Jhansi became part of the Maratha Empire, which soon transitioned into indirect rule by the East India Company. Under European supervision, when a Jhansi raja died, his successor had to be approved by British administrators. After this regulation was instated, the first few transfers of power between rulers, who were all blood related (father to son, brother to brother), went uncontested.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAKSHMIBAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But in 1853, Raja Gangadhar Rao lay dying with no heir and no siblings who could rightfully take his throne. As was custom in these situations, he adopted a boy, his cousin’s son Damodar Rao, on his deathbed and named him his successor. A British officer bore witness to this ceremony, and Gangadhar Rao wrote a letter explaining the legitimacy of the adoption by Jhansi tradition. Seeing an opportunity for expansion, the British chose not to recognize Damodar Rao as a legitimate heir upon Gangadhar Rao’s death. Instead, they declared the throne empty and annexed the state.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAKSHMIBAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But they didn’t count on Gangadhar Rao’s wife.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAKSHMIBAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Lakshmibai was the name given to her after marriage – she was born Manikarnika Tambe in 1835 and was raised in the household of Maratha ruler Baji Rao II, whom her soldier father served. Her upbringing was unusual. She learned to read and write at an early age, but she was primarily raised alongside the boys in the royal court. As a result, she also trained with them in sports and martial arts, including wrestling, fencing, and shooting. She was particularly skilled in horsemanship, and managed her own horses throughout her life. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAKSHMIBAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Her marriage to Raja Gangadhar Rao lasted just over a decade, and upon his death and the British takeover, she was forced out of the palace with her adopted son. She lay low for several years, aware that the British held all the cards and that to oppose them at this time would be futile. Yet she maintained a presence among her populace as the mother of their rightful ruler, and her charismatic persona earned her respect from all quarters.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAKSHMIBAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>In 1857, the Indian Rebellion began in Meerut, north of Delhi. Subsequent victories against the British proved the power behind the uprising, and Lakshmibai seized the opportunity to join the cause and take back her kingdom. She raised her own troops and joined the revolt when rebel soldiers arrived in Jhansi, capturing the British fort and massacring its European garrison and their families. Her contested role in this violence – it is unclear whether she took part or if incoming soldiers committed the atrocities – earned her negative press from the British, but she continued to fund the rebels. Her young son Damodar Rao was formally declared raja of Jhansi, and Lakshmibai was named regent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAKSHMIBAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>After only a short hiatus, the British returned to reclaim Jhansi in early 1858, initiating a siege that lasted several months until Lakshmibai’s forces could no longer hold out. A popular story has her escaping the fort by jumping over the wall on horseback with her son on her back, and a sign marks the spot at Jhansi Fort today. She continued her resistance in the aftermath, rallying troops and fighting in battles herself, often dressed as a man. But her forces suffered further defeat, and Lakshmibai was killed in combat on June 17 at the age of only 22. It took a further five months for the British to regain full control of Jhansi.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				