<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Vietnam, caught between Southeast Asian and East Asian worlds, has a history that is run through with both conflict and interconnection. Its early history is marked by indigenous kingdoms and Han domination, but in 939 CE Ngô Quyền, rebelling against the Southern Han, declared a new era. While Ngô Quyền’s own family would not rule it, and while it would be decades before the name came into use, the foundations of Đại Việt had been laid. For almost a thousand years afterwards, from its capital near present-day Hanoi on the Red River, Đại Việt went through periods of aggressive expansion, but also subjugation and loss. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1010 CE, Lý Thái Tổ, seeking to establish the glory of the new kingdom, renamed the capital Thăng Long, meaning “rising dragon.” On these rising wings, Đại Việt expanded bureaucratic rule at home but also pushed outward – north into Chinese cities, south into those held by the Cham, and westward to Lao and Khmer lands. At its core, the Đại Việt court was a complex mix, formed by political intrigue between eunuchs and noble families: a regime that prioritized bureaucratic and meritocratic power, and both incorporated ethnic others and asserted imperial control. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The dragon’s rise, though, was challenged two hundred years later by another power, on the opposite side of the continent – Mongolia. Möngke Khan, plotting the conquest of the Song Dynasty in China, demanded Đại Việt’s tribute. When the Vietnamese refused, he sacked Thăng Long and put its populace to death. Though the Vietnamese later pushed the invaders out, the weakened Đại Việt accepted overlordship and thus began a period where Đại Việt became a tributary state of its northern neighbor. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In this interlude, Vietnamese society began to change. Key within Chinese assimilation strategies was the “civilizing” of the Vietnamese – meaning turning the local population away from traditions both superficial (e.g., tattooing) and fundamental (e.g., from Buddhist to Confucian). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Chinese control lasted roughly two hundred years, and in the rebellion of Lê Lợi in 1418 CE that Đại Việt finally broke free of Chinese control. Wresting control from the Ming via a campaign of guerilla warfare, the new regime brought a fusion between earlier customs and Chinese norms, between tradition and new technologies – such as firearms. It would need them. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>In the years that followed, Đại Việt became one of the most educated societies in Asia, as the bureaucracy expanded and state strengthened. Professions were often regulated and overseen by the state, and Đại Việt workers excelled in constructing elaborate systems of irrigation – useful, given Vietnam’s climate and reliance upon wet rice agriculture. However, unlike their rivals in Champa and China, Vietnam’s reliance on state-run industry and agriculture meant that it was largely skipped on Silk Road routes, and most luxury goods (such as gold and silver, as well as ivory and rhinoceros horn) were traded locally. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_DAI_VIET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>All empires fall. And despite running for the better part of a millennium, Đại Việt fell to internal fighting in the first years of 1800. What followed was the Empire of Vietnam or, more popularly, the Nguyễn Dynasty, though the Nguyễn were to last just a few decades before yet another invasion, one planned far overseas, in Paris. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!--IMPROVEMENT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_WATER_PUPPET_THEATER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Vietnamese history is not all dynasties and intrigue – there are traditions both noble and folk, and water puppetry is one of the most distinctive of the latter. Taking advantage of the level stage provided by a flooded rice field, performers of múa rối nước – water puppetry – move lacquered puppets with long sticks from behind a screen. These were often rural, comic enactments of folk heroes (and fools), and provided a lens through which commoners could comment upon the doings of their lords.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civics-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_DAI_VIET_CAM_QUAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Đại Việt army was one that balanced a professional army with a more standard levy. In the former case, soldiers in peacetime would be a drain upon the treasury (and, worse, might grow bored and ambitious), whereas in the latter soldiers might be ill-equipped and ill-motivated to fight when farms at home needed tending. Instead, the cấm quân were given land to work free of tax, with the caveat that they would continually train for war and, come wartime, they would be ready.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_DAI_VIET_CHU_NOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Đại Việt had no shortage of choices for writing systems to draw upon for writing Vietnamese, surrounded as they were by Pali, Khmer, Sanskrit, and others. But after years of assimilationist policies under occasional Chinese rule, Vietnamese scribes created chữ nôm, a writing system inspired by, but not identical to, Chinese. This script lived alongside Classical Chinese, and was used for poetry and prose, where capturing the spoken qualities of Vietnamese was vital. It was in use from the 13th century CE until the French colonial occupation in the 20th century. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_DAI_VIET_THANH_HOANG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Religion in Đại Việt was a combination of a combination, bringing together Buddhism, Taoism, ancestor worship, and the animist worship of places and historical figures – including Trưng Trắc. These protective gods are collectively the thành hoàng, a name that specifically refers to the city and the walls that, like the spirits, protect it. Ceremonies to honor these spirits and protect the towns and cities are still held in Vietnam today. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_DAI_VIET_TU_DAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Of the Chinese traditions that Đại Việt took up and made its own was the system of ranked meritocracy, the tứ dân, that divided the population up into various categories of people, depending upon their aptitude. This would be especially relevant in a Confucian system, where correct governance involves having all flourish within their best-suited roles, though it sat uncomfortably with the system of clans and noble families, also a feature of Vietnamese life in that era. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- WONDER_THANH_HUE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_THANH_HUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Begun in 1803, just after the fall of Đại Việt, the imperial citadel of Huế became the crown jewel of the Nguyễn Dynasty and remains a stunning symbol of Vietnamese court glory. It held living quarters and offices for not only the imperial court, but also the bureaucrats (mandarins) who surrounded the court: a beacon of luxury, art, and state power. In this way, the palace, like with much of Vietnamese administration, was built along the model of the Chinese imperial state, but with its own characteristics. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_THANH_HUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In addition, like much of Vietnamese history, it has been riddled by war. Twice during European and American occupations, the citadel was the site of a pitched battle: once, in 1947, when the Việt Minh defended the palace against the French, and again, in 1968, when the North Vietnamese Army and Việt Cộng defended it against the Americans. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_CIVILIAN-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VIET_KIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Settlements in Southeast Asia were typically alleged to have been founded by a prince in search of a new kingdom. This aligned with the mandala politics of Indic lands, where each new city was to be a model of the heavens on the earth, but in Vietnam as well new settlements were attributed to the action of great people. Here, quận vương refers to such a noble, and the settlements that the quận vương makes are, too, meant to reflect the aspiration to create a center for beauty, refinement, and culture. Whether or not such mythic origins for cities and towns reflects the actual process of settlement is up for debate, but significant here is not how people came to live in a place and cultivate it, but, rather, the action that led to its legitimacy and recognition by the central state. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VOI_CHIEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>War elephants – voi chiến in Vietnamese – were a staple of armies across Southeast Asia. Able to move with surprising grace even when hauling heavy loads, they were vital in logistics, and in battle, they were terrifying. From a commanding height, mounted atop tons of hide and flesh, elephant-mounted warriors armed with spears, pikes, or bows could reach above and behind enemy lines, and the beast itself could be goaded into crashing through and trampling even seasoned soldiers. Cavalry, it seems, were particularly susceptible to an elephant charge, as horses required a great deal of discipline and training to keep up an assault when facing a mass of elephants. As such, they were the tanks of their day. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VOI_CHIEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But an elephant is, after all, a living thing. In the wars against the Song Dynasty, the forces of Lý Thường Kiệt, emboldened by their success against the Cham to the south, deployed war elephants against the Chinese. However, Chinese forces had learned to attack the sensitive trunks of the animals, causing them to fly into a rage and trample their own forces.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VOI_CHIEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Elephants remained in use for their hauling capacity and relative stealth well into the Vietnam War.  </Text>
		</Row>

	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				