<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_QAJAR -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The 18th century was a time of violent chaos in Iran. After over two hundred years in power, the Safavid dynasty had decayed, each shah more ineffective than the last until they were finally overthrown by a rebellion. As the old world faded away, a new star rose in the form of the ambitious and ruthless Nader Shah. He reformed the army and invaded India, sacking Delhi and claiming Mughal’s riches for himself. He also expanded Iranian power into the Uzbek and Caucasus regions, and pockets of the Arabian coast. At the height of his reign, his empire was one of the most powerful in the world, and created an army whose size was not matched until the late 20th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The aftermath of Nader Shah’s death was a disaster. Nader Shah himself had blinded his most promising heir out of fear of being overthrown, and much of his family was executed after his demise. His former generals warred with one another for power while border provinces seceded to form their own kingdoms. Two families, the Zands and the Qajars, emerged as the most prominent successors of the remnants of Nader Shah’s empire. For a brief two-decade interlude, the Zand ruler Karim Khan held onto the seats of power at Shiraz, Tehran, and Isfahan. Upon his death, the civil war picked up where it had left off until a victor finally emerged in 1796. This time, the Qajars came out on top. They would remain there until 1925.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Qajar royal family emerged from the Qajar tribe of the Oghuz Turks. Originally from the Armenian region, they had been relocated during the Safavid period to the southeastern shores of the Caspian Sea. Several Qajars had emerged as prominent military commanders during and after Nader Shah’s reign, but after the death of Karim Khan, it was Agha Mohammad Khan who successfully established the clan as Iran’s new shahs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Agha Mohammad Khan spent his childhood as a hostage, and was castrated at age six. He was a clever and tenacious man, focused at first on unifying the Qajar tribe and establishing himself as the dynasty’s head. He then turned to Iran proper, capturing the major cities held by the Zands and relocating the capital to Tehran, where it has remained ever since. Parts of the Caucasus were also subdued and brought back into the fold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Through his efforts, Agha Mohammad not only prevented the complete collapse of Iran, but restored its original borders and ushered in a period of stability. But at what cost? Hand in hand with his ambitions, Agha Mohammad had an immense penchant for violence, and thousands died during his campaigns. He blinded 20,000 men upon capturing the city of Kerman; for years afterward, these men could be found begging across Iran, relating the catastrophe that had befallen their home.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Agha Mohammad was assassinated in 1797, but unlike Nader Shah and Karim Khan, he had planned ahead for his succession, appointing his nephew Fath Ali as heir. Fath Ali Shah worked with what he had – although he lost the Caucasus again to Russia, he managed to maintain a status quo of peace across Iran, even achieving a small economic boost. Given the profound chaos of the previous century, this was no small feat. Iran was still a confederation of allied kingdoms and tribes rather than a cohesive state, and the government’s power beyond the major cities was weak. As much as half the population was still nomadic or semi-nomadic, left to their own independent rule beyond paying taxes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Fath Ali worked to stabilize these internal alliances; but he also transformed the central monarchy, moving away from the tribal khanate model of the Turks towards a more classical concept of kingship. He restored the ancient title of “shahanshah” (King of Kings) and installed his sons as provincial governors to expand his personal power. The revived interest in Iran’s history combined with Fath Ali’s admiration for the arts fostered an artistic and literary renaissance across the country. He was particularly fond of portraiture, and many paintings of his distinctive figure, with his narrow waist and remarkable beard, survive today. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>But Fath Ali’s tenure also saw increased contact with Europe, which would define the Qajar period to come. His long reign (1797-1834) overlapped with the Napoleonic Wars, during which European nations sought additional allies to aid them in the cycle of conflict. They eagerly looked east, but the shifting alliances of the anti-Napoleon coalitions often caused Iran to be disregarded when it needed help the most.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>As the throne passed from Fath Ali Shah to his son Muhammad Shah, European interference grew more direct. The Russian victory in the Caucasus had resulted in a treaty that allowed Russian merchants free access to Iranian markets, and soon the country was flooded with cheap European goods, undermining the profits of local craftsmen and damaging the economy. The Great Game, the war of influence between Britain and Russia in Central Asia, was in full swing, and both nations began meddling in Iranian affairs. In doing so, they hindered Iran’s modernization – for instance, they long delayed the construction of railroads in the region because they feared that trains could transport armies to their borders. But the lack of railroads also blocked the development of transportation and communication infrastructure that were rapidly reforming other nations around the globe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>But change was on the horizon. Naser al-Din Shah came to power in 1848, destined to become the most prominent Qajar ruler over his 51-year reign. He toured Europe several times (the first modern Iranian monarch to do so), keeping scrupulous notes on the wonders and technology he saw there. Following his own interests, Western arts began to catch on in Iran, particularly painting styles and photography.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Naser al-Din instituted a number of reforms across Iran inspired by his experience in, and contact with, the West. He opened Iran’s first newspaper, overhauled the tax system, expanded the military, and established postal and telegraph systems. He also made deals with Western investors. His reforms changed the face of Qajar Iran, but were not popular with his people; moreover, these developments further encouraged the integration of Britain and Russia into Iranian society.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Public discontent did not stop with Naser al-Din’s assassination. Suffering financially, Iran began borrowing heavily from Russia, and sold off concessions to other European powers. The population grew increasingly concerned about the involvement of foreign nations in their affairs, losing trust in the Qajar dynasty. In 1906, Mozaffar ad-Din Shah signed a constitution that divided his power with that of a Majles (elected parliament) but died shortly thereafter. His son, Mohammad Ali Shah, attempted to disband the Majles, going so far as to bomb the parliament building with the support of Russia and Britain. But this act only motivated the constitutional movement further, and revolutionaries sprang up across Iran. They ousted Mohammad Ali Shah in favor of his young son Ahmad and reestablished the Majles in Tehran.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QAJAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>But although the Constitutional Revolution marked a major milestone in modern Iranian history, it was short-lived. In 1907, Britain and Russia divided Iran between them and disbanded the Second Majles. The last Qajar shah was now a mere figurehead. In the following years, Iran became an unwilling battleground during WWI between Russia and the Ottoman Empire, and in 1921, Ahmad Shah Qajar was overthrown in a coup by Reza Shah Pahlavi; he was officially removed from power in 1925. The Qajar era was over – the Pahlavi era was about to begin.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Constructibles-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_BAQ_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The bāq, or garden, is an evolution of the Achaemenid pairidaeza. It was designed as a paradise on earth, with geometrical arrangements, architectural elements, and carefully selected arrays of plants. Bāqs may be private or public, ranging from palace gardens to city parks. In all forms, they offer respite and contemplation, and, within cities, a breath of fresh air. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TAKYEH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The takyeh is a place of mourning, where Shia Muslims honor Husayn ibn Ali, grandson of the prophet Muhammad, during Muharram, the first month of the Islamic calendar. It is also a theater for ta’ziyeh, a traditional Iranian dramatic performance that uses music, song, poetry, and choreography to recount religious, historical, and folkloric narratives. Ta’ziyeh thrived under the Qajar, and many takyehs were erected in the elaborate architecture of the era; Tehran alone had as many as 50. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GHAHVE_KHANE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Coffee arrived in Iran in the 16th century, and with it, the coffee house, or ghahve khaneh. These venues proved popular among the upper classes during the Safavid era, but saw a new resurgence, and reformation, under the Qajars. The traditional ghahve khaneh integrated elements of European café culture to form a new kind of space ripe for the exchange of ideas. Here one could participate in conversation, board games, music, traditional storytelling, and even the development of a new artistic style. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civics-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QAJAR_THE_SUN_THRONE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fath Ali Shah commissioned the Sun Throne in 1801 as a symbol of Qajar power. Constructed in Isfahan and bedecked with gold and gemstones, it is named for the sun disk atop its back, which rotated through a clockwork mechanism. When it was repaired during the reign of Naser al-Din Shah, he had poetic verses added to the throne on the topic of its restoration. The throne is sometimes called the Peacock Throne, though not after the Mughal throne of the same name, which also resided in Iran after its seizure by Nader Shah in the 18th century. Rather, Fath Ali Shah is said to have renamed the Sun Throne in honor of his favorite wife. Today, it is on display in the Central Bank of Iran.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QAJAR_TWELVE_GATES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When Agha Mohammad Khan established himself as the first Qajar ruler of Iran, he moved the country’s capital to Tehran. At the time, urban centers did not hold much sway over the country’s largely rural populace. To nominally take control of Iran meant capturing its major cities; but ruling the country required constant negotiations with the self-administrating provinces and communities. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QAJAR_TWELVE_GATES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As the nineteenth century advanced, the cities began to grow in both size and power, shifting the relationship between urban and rural spaces. Tehran in particular was greatly transformed, first by its new role as capital, which initiated an immediate population boom, and later by modernization. Among the many building projects that continuously expanded the city was an initiative by Naser al-Din Shah to construct a new wall with twelve gates. They stood for over half a century, a statement of Qajar power, until they were torn down in the 1930s during yet another phase of Tehran’s expansion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QAJAR_NEZAM_E_JADID_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Neẓām-e ǰadīd (“the new order”) was a series of military reforms instigated by crown prince Abbas Mirza following the Russo-Persian War (1804-1813). The conflict stripped Iran of most of its Caucasus territories and revealed major weaknesses in the Iranian armed forces. Abbas Mirza set about modernizing the military by sending soldiers to study in England and inviting European advisors to Iran to train the army in Western tactics. Military manuals were translated, and production of artillery and gunpowder began in Tabriz. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QAJAR_NEZAM_E_JADID_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The reforms were a success in the field against both the Ottomans and the Russians, although other factors contributed to the full rout of Iran from the Caucasus during the next Russo-Persian War (1826-1828). </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- WONDER_ERAM_GARDEN -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ERAM_GARDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Located in the city of Shiraz, Eram Garden has been a garden for many centuries, but its appearance today is largely the result of Qajar-era development. It is a prime example of the paradisiacal Persian garden (“eram” means “heaven”), composed of carefully crafted geometrical sections and a variety of flowers, trees, lawns, and water features. The three-story pavilion, completed in 1893, features paintings of historic and mythic figures, and the tiles on its ground floor are decorated with verses from the medieval poet Hafiz. The garden opened to the public in 1980. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_CIVILIAN-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SOLTAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The early Qajar army was not a standing army, but one made of irregulars who assembled in the event of war. When conflict broke out, the khan initiated a farmān, a summons, to governors and other leaders who levied their own soldiers to gather at a designated place before embarking on campaign. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SOLTAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The khan was the commander-in-chief, and beneath him were those appointed to lead individual armies – they received the title “sardār.” As the highest military rank under the Qajar, it was granted to princes and prominent members of the court, including the second Qajar ruler, Fath Ali, who served as sardār while he was crown prince. After the military reforms of Abbas Mirza, the sardār title was renamed “sartip.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_GHILMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Emerging from the tradition of the Mamluks in the Abbasid Empire, gholāms were initially Turkish slave soldiers, first appearing in records during the Saffarid dynasty in the ninth century. Slavery was phased out under the Qajar centuries later, but gholāms remained a prominent, respected, and feared component of the 19th century Iranian army, particularly in their role as the royal bodyguard. They were divided into two units. The gholām-shāh were exclusively cavalrymen; they were the highest paid soldiers in the Qajar army, making more than six times more than the average soldier. The gholām-tofangchis ranked below the gholām-shāh, and fought on horseback and on foot wielding long rifles. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_GHILMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The gholāms remained Iran’s most elite soldiers until they were replaced by the Persian Cossack Brigade in 1879. </Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				