<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Bronze Age collapse in the 12th century BCE brought many civilizations around the Mediterranean and Near East to their knees. Climate change, technological imbalances, invasions, and other factors combined to eat away at centralized governments, resulting in the collapse of empires and the dispersal of people from urban centers into smaller rural settlements.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But not all civilizations faded into darkness. Phoenician city-states had been on the rise for at least two centuries, first mentioned in Egyptian accounts of conquest over their coastal settlements in the Levant. They had become centers of trade, facilitating contact between Europe, North Africa, and Asia, but had struggled against empires seeking to control their economic power in the region. After the Bronze Age collapse, these powers stumbled or fell, and their influence over the Phoenicians dissipated. Now truly independent, the Phoenicians began to flourish in earnest, and, filling the power vacuum left behind, they soon controlled trade throughout the Mediterranean. They began establishing colonies across the Mediterranean, along the European and North African coasts as far as Morocco and Spain, seeking good natural harbors, access to local markets, and control over nearby resources.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Around 814 BCE, a group of colonists from Tyre arrived at the Gulf of Tunis in modern-day Tunisia. The location was ideal for a new settlement. An easily defendable hill overlooked a harbor that both provided shelter from storms and stood in close proximity to the Strait of Sicily, a bottleneck for Mediterranean trade. The Tyrians quickly began to build their colony, which they named “qrt-ḥdšt” (“new city”). Today, we call it Carthage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>This fairly mundane story of the founding of Carthage is not the same legend later sources recount. The more exciting version tells of Dido (Elissa), queen of Tyre, who fled her city after her brother Pygmalion stole her inheritance and murdered her husband. Arriving in North Africa, she made an agreement with a local Berber chief – she could claim as much land as could be covered by a single ox hide. Dido cut her hide into strips and used them to encircle the entire hill of her future city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Carthage existed as a minor colony for several centuries, until Alexander the Great smashed through the Levant in the fourth century BCE. In 332, he sacked Tyre, destroying the center of Phoenician power and sending Tyrian refugees scattering. Many ended up in Carthage, and the population boom combined with the fall of Tyre enabled the city to quickly become the new center of power and riches in the Mediterranean.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The wealth of Carthage came mainly from trade, tribute, and taxes. Unlike other Phoenician city-states, which consolidated their power within their own walls, the Carthaginians pursued an agenda of territorial conquest to expand their borders. Relying on their powerful navy, and combining their own armies with those of the neighboring Numidian Kingdom, they subjugated other Phoenician colonies and conquered new territory on both sides of the Mediterranean. There are several theories about why Carthage pursued an expansionist agenda, from their need to establish dominance in the face of competing Greek and Roman trade to the rise of military leaders in the Carthaginian government. Whatever the reason, Carthage typically did not exercise direct control over its new holdings, but preferred a hegemonic approach, collecting tribute from its settlements and colonies and leveraging them as trading hubs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Rule of Carthage had evolved from a monarchy into a republic by the fourth century. At the top were two suffetes (judges) elected from the most powerful families. They ruled together with a senate of 200-300 members. A civilian assembly voted on laws and measures put forth by the suffetes and senate. Civil and military power were kept separate – generals were elected or appointed, and had no say in political affairs; the suffetes likewise lacked control over the armies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The city itself was dominated by the Byrsa, a citadel perched at the top of the hill overlooking the sea. On the slopes below were four residential quarters and a large port. Beyond the urban center was farmland – Carthage was well-versed in agriculture, and successfully cultivated a wide variety of crops that both fed the city and provided ample surplus for exports. Carthaginian farming knowledge was so valued that one of the only texts to survive the city’s destruction was an agricultural treatise by the writer Mago. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Carthage’s expansion did not come without repercussions. The first big clash came against Greece. Even before Carthage had grown from a small colony into a prominent city, the Greeks had been a major competitor to the Phoenicians, slowly chipping away at their monopoly on Mediterranean trade. The rise of Carthage transferred this friction to the New City, and soon the two empires were at each other’s throats. Starting in 480, Carthage fought a series of wars with Greece over control of Sicily. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>By the third century, Rome had replaced Greece as Carthage’s main rival. Once again, Sicily was the powder keg that ignited the First Punic War in 264. After over two decades, the Romans emerged victorious, and Carthage lost all holdings in Sicily while facing a new internal revolt from their mercenary forces. But in 218, war broke out again. The Second Punic War saw famed Carthaginian general Hannibal lead his army overland through Gaul and across the Alps to attack the Romans from the north. He defeated a massive Roman army at Cannae, but, lacking reinforcements, he was unable to finish the conquest. The Romans successfully kicked the Carthaginians out of Italy and Spain and emerged victorious once again, now becoming the dominant power in the western Mediterranean. Carthage was stripped of all overseas holdings and its navy was reduced to a mere ten warships – politically it had essentially become a subordinate state of Rome.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_CARTHAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>The city was also forbidden to wage war. 50 years later, Carthage broke this rule, mobilizing an army to retaliate against Numidian incursions into its territory. The Romans had no investment in the conflict between Carthage and Numidia, but the scars of the Second Punic War ran deep. Despite having the upper hand in their political relationship, Rome was perpetually suspicious of Carthage, which had begun to rebuild its economic power through its traditional methods of trade and agriculture. Cato the Elder famously ended every speech in the Senate with the line "Ceterum autem censeo Carthaginem esse delendam” (“Furthermore, I consider that Carthage must be destroyed”). Carthage’s mobilization against Numidia provided the casus belli Rome had been waiting for. War was declared, the city was besieged, and Carthage was razed to the ground.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Constructibles-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_PUNIC_PORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As a naval economic power, Carthage’s success and survival relied on its port. The remarkable structure consisted of the outer commercial dockyard and the inner cothon for warships. The entire project was excavated from marshland circa 200 BCE, requiring the movement of around 235,000 cubic meters of soil. They were built of sandstone ashlar blocks, and were largely concealed from the outside by immense walls; the narrow entrances to the outer and inner harbors could be closed off with huge iron chains. When the Romans conquered Carthage during the Third Punic War, the port was the first part of the city to be destroyed. Yet its footprint remains prominent on the Tunisian coast, one of the few vestiges of Carthaginian glory. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_COTHON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The cothon was the inner harbor of the port of Carthage, home to the city’s navy. Named after a Greek drinking vessel of similar shape, it was circular with an island in the middle and was entirely manmade. Both the inner and outer shores were lined with shipsheds, above which were warehouses full of supplies. Classical sources say the cothon could hold up to 220 ships, though archaeology has revealed that the number was likely closer to 170. Its distinctive appearance has become a visual hallmark of ancient Carthage; yet the cothon was built very late in its history, soon after the Second Punic War and less than 50 years before Carthage was destroyed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DOCKYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Carthage’s port had two harbors, one for the military and one for civilians, and it was the latter, the commercial dockyard, that served as the economic gateway that enriched Carthage. Within this manmade rectangular harbor, trade ships were unloaded and restocked, taxes were collected, and tribute was delivered from colonies near and far. Its importance outshone its size – despite extensive remodeling after the Second Punic War, the dockyard was limited in space to a mere seven hectares, which was mediated by a wooden quay built outside its walls extending into the sea.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civics-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_CARTHAGE_SHIPSHEDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Carthage relied on ships for its economic and military power, and the maintenance of these vessels was paramount to success. Voyages around the Mediterranean and beyond inflicted significant wear and tear on wooden ships, including damage from storms, waterlogged timber that slowed speed and could lead to rot, and voracious marine life with a taste for wood. Yet pulling such large and heavy ships onto land for dry storage and repair was difficult and time-consuming, and exposed them to the persistent peril of weather.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_CARTHAGE_SHIPSHEDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>To resolve these challenges, Carthage constructed shipsheds for its fleet. These were covered slipways built along the water’s edge, allowing ships to be quickly and easily moved onto a dry dock sheltered from the elements. Here, repairs could be made before a swift redeployment, reducing the time a ship was out of commission and increasing the frequency of its maintenance, keeping Carthage’s navy and merchant fleet in top form. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_CARTHAGE_RED_SLIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Although the full nature of Carthaginian religion, its gods and practices, lies concealed behind missing and untrustworthy sources, the goddess Tanit has survived through her pervasive presence in the city and its colonies. A goddess of wisdom, fertility, and motherhood, she was one of Carthage’s chief deities, together with her consort, Baal Hammon. Tanit was a late addition to the Punic pantheon – while Baal Hammon has roots in Phoenicia and beyond, Tanit emerged around the fifth century BCE, possibly via local Berber beliefs, and soon outstripped her consort in Carthage in importance and reverence. Worship of Tanit seems to have included human sacrifice in the tophet, a sacred sanctuary, though the degree to which such rituals were practiced by the Carthaginians is under debate. Her symbol, the same used in this game to represent Carthage, is commonly found in stone carvings and mosaics; later depictions show her with wings and the head of a lion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_CARTHAGE_SICILIAN_WARS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Carthaginians followed the Phoenicians in establishing themselves as the masters of Mediterranean trade routes. But they were rarely unchallenged. Their first major rival were the Greek city-states, another strong naval presence who contested Carthage’s dominance in the region. Their major point of contention was the island of Sicily, which effectively divides the Mediterranean in two halves and was the lynchpin to mastery of the sea in ancient times. The Carthaginians and the Greeks fought a series of wars between 480-306 BCE over control of the island, during which territories moved back and forth between the two powers. The Sicilian Wars faded as Rome eclipsed Greece, and the Greek holdings on Sicily became Roman. But the rise of a new competitor for Carthage also sparked a new series of conflicts – the Punic Wars, which began, once again, over Sicily. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- WONDER_BYRSA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_BYRSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Atop the hill at the center of Carthage, the Byrsa citadel watched over the city. The name’s origin is unknown – the legend of Dido has created a dubitable link to the Greek word “byrsa” (oxhide) in reference to the means by which she acquired the land that would become Carthage. However, it is more likely a variation of the Phoenician “barsat” (stronghold). The Byrsa was the heart of Carthage’s military, and shared the hill (also called Byrsa) with major political and religious institutions. After the fall of Carthage, the walled citadel was reused by the Romans, Vandals, Byzantines, and others. Today it is a major archaeological site.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_CIVILIAN-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_COLONIST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Carthage began as a Phoenician colony, a small coastal outpost founded to facilitate and control trade across the Mediterranean. As it grew into a city and an independent center of power, Carthage used the same technique to expand its own influence and power, relying on colonies rather than land to fuel its empire. While historically this expansion has been characterized as aggressive and imperialistic (in large part due to hostile Roman accounts of Carthage’s history), more recent investigations have shown that the initial coalescence of power focused on taking control of, and strengthening, existing Phoenician settlements along the western coastlines, while direct seizure of territory occurred later on. During this later phase, colonists were sent to establish settlements around the Mediterranean and beyond to function as trade hubs, depots, and safe harbors for the Carthaginian fleet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_NUMIDIAN_CAVALRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Carthage’s power stemmed from trade routes and small coastal colonies; as a result, the city itself and its economic empire did not have a large population. In order to fill out its army in times of war, Carthage hired mercenaries from the neighboring Numidians. These Berber warriors were lightly armed, wielding javelins and riding small, quick horses; their speed and agility enabled them to ruthlessly harry opponents. The Numidian cavalry were used extensively by Carthage during the Second Punic War, where they were deployed with great success by Hannibal during his invasion of Italy, and against Roman incursions in North Africa. </Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				