<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Exploration Wonders -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_BOROBUDUR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Indonesia’s primary island of Java may not be its largest, but it has been home to a variety of faiths: Islam, Hinduism, and Buddhism, in the case of the eighth century Borobudur. The largest Buddhist temple in the world, Borobudur fell into ruin after Hinduism and Buddhism declined in Java in the 14th century (though Hindu traditions continued in Bali). It rests in nine tiers, with over 500 Buddha images (in Mahayana traditions, multiple individuals have achieved Buddha-hood, so one refers to a Buddha, rather than the Buddha).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_BOROBUDUR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Borobudur also reflects the international influence in the area. The Sailendra Dynasty, responsible for building the temple, drew from Indian sources for its cultural and religious development, sent trade delegations to China, and engaged in a series of wars with the Khmer – leading to Khmer’s independence and the origins of the Khmer Empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_BRIHADEESWARAR_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Southern India is home to groups that are ethnically and linguistically distinct from the rest of the country – primarily the Tamil people. Though Tamils follow Hinduism, they developed unique traditions and achieved a period of international fame and might during the Chola Dynasty in the first millennium CE (and part of the second). Brihadeeswarar is a testament to Tamil's rich culture, wealth, and strength. The “Meru (sacred mountain of Hindu myth) of the South,” the temple sprawls across a large complex designed for perambulation by pilgrims. At its center is the vimana – the pyramid-shaped tower adorned with carvings and limited to Hindu priests. While many temples were elaborately painted, it is a matter of contemporary debate whether or not the vimana at Brihadeeswarar was (or should be) painted. The tower is currently a sandy orange stone – impressive, regardless of adornments.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_BRIHADEESWARAR_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The temple is dedicated to Shiva, popularly known as the god of destruction, but his portfolio is far more extensive. Whereas many regions produced physical icons that display Shiva in a variety of poses, those in the Tamil regions often display Shiva dancing, indicating the god’s active movement – at least until his foot comes down, and the world’s age ends.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_EL_ESCORIAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Royal Site of San Lorenzo de El Escorial, the residence of the King of Spain, was built over the course of two decades by King Philip II (r. 1556-1598). In addition to its function as an administrative building and royal residence, the site contains a monastery, cathedral, library, and university. The complex highlights the religious nature of Spanish imperial power: the crown and cross united in one glorious building.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_EL_ESCORIAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>When it was built, El Escorial was envisioned as a nexus of Spain’s past, present, and future. It was not only the administrative center of a new religious, mercantile, and expansionist empire, but it was the resting place for its kings and home to relics and important documents. From here, Spain charted a course toward future greatness – and it didn't care who got in the way. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ERDENE_ZUU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mongolia has a long and complex history with religion. Early on, the Mongol Empire's religion was a form of shamanism (where an individual’s spirit communicates directly with the divine), holding the god Tengri at the height of an axis of power. Buddhism, especially Tibetan Buddhism, has impacted the region since its introduction only a few years after the life of the Buddha (about 500 BCE). But Buddhism's popularity fluctuated with shamanism, flourishing when Mongols were established in settled cities and declining when the Mongols were scattered across the steppe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ERDENE_ZUU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Erdene Zuu is the oldest surviving Buddhist temple in Mongolia, built in 1585 under an ambitious plan to model the temple after a Tibetan japamala (a rosary) and constructed of stones from the ancient capital of Qaraqorum. At times, shamanism is still practiced there, highlighting the often syncretic and blended practices of the region.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_FORBIDDEN_CITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the reign of the Yuan Dynasty, the Mongols built a new city at the heart of their capital, called “Dadu” in Chinese or “Khanbaliq” in Mongolian. Yuan rule was relatively short-lived, but the subsequent Ming Dynasty, under the Yongle Emperor, relocated their capital to this ancient site and built a vast administrative complex where yurts once stood. The construction of the Forbidden City, begun in 1406, served as the imperial palace and winter residence through the end of the Qing Dynasty. Built in the shape of a massive rectangle and featuring four gates, the space contains impressive wooden structures: palaces, temples, and administrative buildings. As a testament to China’s diverse history, the interior temples have included Buddhist, Taoist, and Manchu shamanist shrines, though each bolstered the might of the Mandate of Heaven, within and without.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HALE_O_KEAWE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hawaiian religious sites are manifestations of mana – the supernatural and physical power existing in kings, sacred objects, and sacred spaces. Hale o Keawe, on the west coast of the big island of Hawai’i, was one such site. It consisted of a central hale poki (a consecrated house) as well as a series of ki’i (the divine images of gods). The bones of Hawaiian kings rested inside the house, where their mana could continue to aid the land long after their passing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HALE_O_KEAWE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>These locations of powerful mana were forbidden to outsiders as the spaces were deeply involved in the indigenous kapu (taboo) system – observing the correct kapu was vital for the maintenance of one’s mana. The temple was destroyed (and the bones removed) when Hawaiians converted to Christianity in the early 19th century, but the site was restored in the 20th century and is today maintained by the National Park Service.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HOUSE_OF_WISDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Uniting Greek, Persian, Indian, and Chinese knowledge under an Arabic banner enabled the Abbasid Caliphate to become a center of learning and science. That center was concretized in Baghdad’s House of Wisdom, built in the eighth century CE as a private library and opened as a public academy in the nineth. Yet its presence at the heart of the Abbasid world brought calamity as well as prosperity – the library was utterly destroyed by the Mongols in 1258, leaving only traces that survive in works by contemporary scholars. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HOUSE_OF_WISDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>These sources describe a place where scientists, physicians, and scholars read and elaborated on works from antiquity as well as contemporary writing from across the known world. The House of Wisdom welcomed book-hunters from Constantinople and beyond, seeking old texts for translation and interpretation, and astronomers studying the movements of the stars. All of this work was tossed into the Tigris River by Hülegü Khan, grandson of Genghis Khan and founder of the Ilkhanate of Persia. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MACHU_PIKCHU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>High above the Andes, surrounded by cascading terraces, rests a city of stone: Machu Pikchu, “the old mountain.” Built as a royal retreat in 1450 by the Sapa Inca Pachacuti, the structure held nearly a thousand workers and attendants from across the empire. Given the Sapa Inca’s role as the embodiment of the divine sun, the complex contains political accommodations as well as temples and ritual sites.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MACHU_PIKCHU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The year 1450 was not an auspicious time to build the foundations of a new empire in the Andes. Even before the Spanish arrived in the region, European-born epidemics had begun spreading through the area to devastating effect. Machu Pikchu was abandoned less than a century after it was constructed, creating a “lost city,” a testament to what could have been.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_NOTRE_DAME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Notre Dame, the Cathedral of Our Lady, sits on the Île de la Cité at the heart of Paris. It is a masterpiece of Gothic architecture, with all its attendant flourishes and gargoyles, but the structure is most notable for its lightness. Older Romanesque cathedrals often needed massive walls and pillars to support their heavy stone roofs, but Notre Dame is a space of light, including multicolored stained glass windows. Notre Dame achieves this feat via the use of flying buttresses, ribbed vaults, and pointed arches, all working together to bear and distribute weight in support of higher and thinner stone walls.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_NOTRE_DAME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The cathedral was built over the course of nearly a century, between 1163 and 1261, and was overseen by multiple generations of priests and architects. In 2019, a devastating fire collapsed the spire and destroyed much of the vault, but the walls and windows remain, and donations have flooded in for the cathedral’s refurbishment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_SHWEDAGON_ZEDI_DAW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shwedagon Zedi Daw (the Golden Dagon Pagoda), also simply known as Shwedagon Phaya, is a gold-covered stupa that rises 59 feet above the skyline of Yangon, Burma. It reportedly contain relics of former Buddhas: the staff of Kakusandha, the water filter of Konagamana, the robe of Kassapa, and strands of hair from Gautama (the Buddha we normally think of). According to tradition, the stupa was built during the lifetime of the Buddha, nearly 2,500 years ago, although there is no record of the stupa until the 14th century CE. It is the most important site in Burmese Buddhism and is significant in Theravada Buddhism (mainland Southeast Asia and Sri Lanka).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_SHWEDAGON_ZEDI_DAW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At the time of its construction, Burma was ruled by the Mon people, and a Mon king likely built Shwedagon Zedi Daw. Over time, the stupa was filled with relics of significance to the Mon and later the Burmans, becoming a place of pilgrimage for Buddhists the world over.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_TOMB_OF_ASKIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The greatest of the Songhai Emperors, Askia Mohammad I, lies under a monumental pyramid-like structure in present-day Mali. The tomb is a 17 meter tall mudbrick and adobe plaster building held in place by wooden beams that jut from its sides, giving it a porcupine appearance. The tomb is an early example of a style that would come to define Sahel architecture from the period. Significantly, all of the materials that went into Askia’s tomb were imported from Mecca. There is no economic reason for this, but it befits the monument as a religious and political place.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_TOMB_OF_ASKIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Askia Mohammad (r. 1493-1528), also known as Mamar Kassey, created the largest empire in West African history, conquering the Hausa states (of Amina’s fame) and dominating the Western Saharan trade routes. Songhai's expansion was also its downfall, as Arab states and their guns seized the less-equipped Songhai a few decades after Askia’s death.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_WHITE_TOWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the Normans arrived on English shores in 1066, they encountered a diverse mix of Anglo-Saxons, Norse, and Celts, most of whom were fortified in strongholds protected by wooden palisades and elite foot soldiers such as the huscarl. In contrast, the Normans brought technologies from mainland Europe: mounted knights and towers of stone. Such fortifications became an important tool in keeping control over a recently conquered populace. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_WHITE_TOWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Tower of London wasn’t originally made of stone. William the Conqueror first built the structure from wood, then used this temporary security to construct a fortification of stone (begun 12 years after the conquest). The oldest part of the complex, the White Tower, became all things at once: royal residence, military fortification, prison, and church. As England’s turmoil subsided, the structure became more luxurious, with stained glass and a whitewashed exterior. Royals eventually moved elsewhere, to more spacious palaces, but the Tower remains a symbol of British fortitude today.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Exploration Buildings -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ARMORER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Arms are expensive. For many ancient and medieval armies, knights went into battle with arms and armor that they had purchased themselves. This made feudal armies cheaper to maintain but with the added risk that a military defeat would mean the loss of stewards, governors, dukes, barons, etc. Armies in the premodern period moved back and forth between levels of professionalism – meaning military leaders could be fully employed by the state or work part-time as farmers (or barons). The development of mass-produced arms was vital for professional armies. An arms factory could produce interchangeable arms and armor to quickly equip a large force, and a professional army could maintain its training even when not marching to war. However, professional armies require money, and soldiers often have ambitions beyond the battlefield (as the Romans constantly discovered).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BANK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What exactly is banking? Wealthy merchants in antiquity would often give credit or loans to farmers who supplied them; Mesopotamian and Roman temples also served as banks, taking a percentage of the gold deposited as profit. However, modern banks emerged during the Middle Ages when practices linked to long-distance caravans began to influence everyday agricultural production. In Europe, these banks were often owned by Jews who, barred from mainstream sources of income (i.e. holding land), were able to circumvent the religious ban on lending money with interest – a practice forbidden to Christians. Indeed, Christian elites depended on banking systems, often giving rise to the very anti-Semitism that created the conditions that made banking possible. Elsewhere, early Chinese systems of banking came about, often focused on transfers and money-changing (from silver to paper), rather than interest and loans. Today, banking financial services are a cornerstone of the world’s wealth – and disparity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BAZAAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Bazaar is the Persian word for “market” (in Arabic they are called a souq). Markets are more than just a collection of farmer’s stalls on a particular day of the week. Bazaars were the lifeblood of the caravan trade, often located just outside of caravanserai (protected inns servicing Central Asian, North African, and Middle Eastern caravan routes). As these locations, especially along Saharan or Silk Road routes, became increasingly important, towns grew up around them. These covered markets were vital locations for the exchange of goods and ideas, and the locus of cosmopolitanism in the Muslim world of the Middle Ages. Famous bazaars include the Bazaar of Tabriz in Iran, the Grand Bazaar of Istanbul, the Marrakech Night Market, and the bazaar at Batkhela in present-day Pakistan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DUNGEON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Prisons that function like correctional institutions are a relatively modern phenomenon. Punishments before and during medieval times were fast and public – and often bloody. However, at times, society wanted to keep a person alive and confined – whether to extract information, to hold for ransom, or out of an aversion to the death penalty. Dungeons (from the French “donjon,” a fortified keep) were designed for those purposes. According to the Ashokavadana, an account of Ashoka’s reign, the emperor created an elaborate dungeon disguised as a beautiful villa, where those imprisoned faced secret tortures patterned after the Buddhist hells. Arguably worse was the medieval European oubliette, a hole with no egress where prisoners were dropped and “forgotten” to die of dehydration or starvation (oubliette stems from the French “to forget”). Some castles featured “Hexenkeller,” places where those accused of witchcraft could be imprisoned and questioned about infernal powers, though the poor women incarcerated there likely had little knowledge on the subject. In the modern period, these tortures have been replaced by the idea of prison as reform – though results vary.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GRISTMILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Grains comprise much of our caloric intake and have been vital to most – but not all – human societies. Still, grains are difficult to eat without extensive processing. This requires a long period of grinding kernels of wheat, corn, or rice into flour, which can then be baked or otherwise used. There lies an issue: how does one source the energy to complete this repetitive work? Hand-rolled mills (simply crushing grains with a cylindrical stone) are functional on a small scale, but as agricultural societies grew larger and more complex, new systems came into play. A gristmill is a massive stone, powered by some outside source, that grinds kernels as it turns. Running water was often used to turn paddle wheels connected to the stone; when fast-flowing water was unavailable or inconsistent, animal and human labor was employed. These mills might belong to a large farming estate or could be private, a place where farmers could bring their grain in exchange for a percentage of the flour. Gristmills became more important as the power used to process their cereals began to be used to move heavier and more complex machines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GUILDHALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Artisans have been influential in nearly every aspect of human history. They are skilled tradesmen specialized in producing and evaluating particular goods or services – from merchants to academics, silk weavers to silversmiths. This work often needs to be evaluated by experts, which requires an organization. Guilds were self-governed and often operated as a type of monopoly under charter from the monarch or, more often, the city. The latter anticipated later bourgeois revolutions in France and elsewhere, as artisans and cities alike rebelled against the divine right of kings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GUILDHALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The guild hall refers to the offices of a guild. While guild-like associations existed in ancient Rome and parts of Asia, especially concerning the merchant houses of Chola, they are best known in their late medieval and early modern Europe incarnations. Guild-like associations remain today, especially within academia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_HOSPITAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hospitals serve a vital function, especially for those without individual access to medical expertise or a safe, clean environment in which they can recuperate. Many early hospitals were a part of religious communities or carried out charitable functions. The first recorded public hospital was built in Paliputra during the fifth century BCE, and was a place where those unable to afford a doctor's home visit could seek treatment, free of charge. Later, Khmer had a similar system of hospitals across their empire devoted to the Buddhist deity of healing, and the Muslim caliphates of the Middle Ages created public hospitals for the sick and wounded as a part of a public and moral good. Europe came to the project later, but during the Middle Ages, Catholic institutions set up hospitals, especially in southern Europe. These religious institutions often later transformed into state efforts to improve public health and ensure a healthy, happy citizenry. Even Adam Smith, that famous advocate for the free market, excluded hospitals from his model; it’s difficult to imagine shopping around for the lowest price when one’s leg is broken!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_KILN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Pottery (and brick) is a fusion of clay into a hardened state. This is similar to the glassmaking process, where different kinds of silicate earth are melted then cooled into harder, combined shapes. Pottery allows for a wide range of new cooking techniques; boiling water in a wooden bowl is a challenge. While pottery has been made since Neolithic times, higher temperatures allowed for stronger bonds, allowing rough earthenware to become superseded by refined stoneware or even delicate porcelain made from kaolin clays. The latter was perfected in China during ancient times, and became a hot trading commodity in Europe in the 14th century, so much so that the term “china” became synonymous with that type of vessel.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MEDIEVAL_BRIDGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Medieval bridges developed out of their ancient counterparts, combining practicality and aesthetics to expand and enhance building methods. East Asia saw the rise of wooden cantilever bridges, some of which were covered and featured elegant designs and decorations. These bridges supported increased travel and trade. Similarly, the Inca developed a system for maintaining rope bridges, in which villages along the extensive road system replaced their cables nearly every year as a community in order to prevent disruptions in mountain travel and communication. In the Middle East, Europe, and North Africa, the spread of the pointed arch, or ogival, replaced the round Roman arch technique, providing longer-term stability to the heavy stone structures. Bridges could be fortified as defensive positions and the drawbridge could be raised to prevent enemies from entering a castle or settlement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MEDIEVAL_WALLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Throughout the medieval world, wall technology evolved alongside war. Wood and rammed earth were increasingly replaced by more permanent stone, allowing for stronger, higher structures to guard against the pressures of siege weapons and powerful projectiles. Walls designs became more complex – towers were incorporated in new and innovative ways, and stone allowed for details such as arrow loops, murder holes, machicolations, and putlog holes for wooden hoarding structures that gave defenders additional ways and angles to repel attacks. While ancient walls were used for both offense and defense, medieval walls were used almost exclusively as defensive structures as they were slower and more expensive to build. However, the payoff was worthwhile, as they were often impenetrable in the face of a direct assault…at least until the age of gunpowder.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MENAGERIE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Royal courts often contained elaborate displays of treasures from around the world: works of art, curiosities, and even entire gardens landscaped to look like foreign, or conquered, lands. Many courts also contained menageries, collections of animals sent as gifts or tributes from abroad. Charlemagne had a collection of exotic animals, including monkeys, camels, and an elephant; the Tower of London held lions and bears in cages. The real height of the menagerie was the period of absolute monarchy when the majesty of the court became a central means of building a dynasty. Notably, most menageries were not zoological parks; these were not available to the public but were designed for the ruler’s pleasure and to spread their fame. The idea that the public should be educated developed slowly during the early modern period, along with public education and hospitals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_OBSERVATORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The archetypal astronomical observatory is a large metal dome with a telescope peeking out, something like the Sphinx Observatory in Switzerland. But imagine observatories centuries before – quiet, still platforms from which the sky can be analyzed, perhaps using reference markers to date astronomical movements (i.e. Venus rose from this stone, etc.). Such sites were important for astronomy, astrology, mathematics, and navigation, and they often fused religious and scientific understandings. We find these structures in Beijing, Delhi, the Mayan city of Caracol, and elsewhere. As optical technology expanded, observatories seized upon the ability to use bigger and more accurate lenses. By the 17th century onward, many major European nations built detailed observatories to better understand the heavens.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_PAVILION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A pavilion (ting in Chinese, chahartaq in Persian, and shala in Sanskrit) generally refers to an open structure designed for festivals, public assemblies, or general relaxation. The concept is old as pavilions were used widely during the Zhou Dynasty and formed a central part of Zoroastrian fire temples in the pre-Islamic period. In the West, these structures were often decorative, placed within a royal complex or fairground, and intended as places where one could relax and take in the sights. Famous pavilions include the Siamese summer palace at Bang Pa-in, the pavilions at Topkapı Palace in Istanbul, and the Forbidden City.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SAWMILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In a saw pit, men cut logs into planks. This is a long, laborious process made infinitely easier by the application of early machinery, which began in Byzantium in the early first millennium CE. Running water could turn a wheel – via connecting rods or a gear train – to move a stone or wooden saw that could cut through logs without human labor. Other forms of mills existed, namely those powered by wind, animals, or even human labor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SAWMILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Mills are historically important as an early example of mechanical engineering put to practical commercial use. Miniature mill technology exists within automobiles, trains, helicopters, and more, converting rotary motion to lateral motion (and vice-versa).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SHIPYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Oceangoing vessels are large. This statement seems banal but consider the implications. Constructing a large vessel capable of navigating the seas requires a specialized workshop. While early Polynesian and Scandinavian vessels could be assembled on a beach and rolled into the water on logs – or even carried into the waves by workers – making the truly massive vessels of the Early Modern period required a specialized site. In a shipyard, the timbers of a vessel could be stabilized; in a drydock, water could be drained out of the assembly area and then filled back in when the vessel was ready to float.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SHIPYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While early shipyards existed in India and the Mediterranean, shipyards reached their apotheosis during the height of colonialism. Of these, the Venetian Arsenal is the quintessential shipyard – a massive assembly line that could construct ships in record time. As European trading companies established outposts from Havana to Manila, Batavia to Suriname, New York to Singapore, the quick production of reliable oceangoing ships made the reach of empire possible.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_STONECUTTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Masonry has been a component of city-building since cities were first constructed – even before, as sites such as Stonehenge can attest. Medieval tools involved precise chisels and mallets. Societies such as the Inca were masters of stonework, fitting block atop block, each one so perfectly carved that their walls did not need mortar to hold together. In fact, the Inca were so careful to read rocks that they often split stones along natural seams. While East Asian cities often relied upon wood for all but military fortifications, in the European Middle Ages, stone cathedrals became a point of pride and city piety, and were often lucrative pilgrimage destinations as well as monuments to a higher power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TAVERN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Travel requires rest. Inns were often stationed near markets or along trade routes and were necessary for commerce. In these places, merchants, diplomats, and pilgrims could sleep, tend to their pack animals, and exchange stories and ideas. The caravanserai of the Persianate world or the Inca tambo were exemplary waystations that contained fortifications against bandits, supplies, and small markets. These relay stations could provide messengers with a fresh horse (or fresh rider), enabling information to travel as fast as was possible in the time – the Mongolian Yam system was exceptional in this regard, as messengers had to outpace the swift Mongol armies. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TAVERN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Importantly, inns were places where people of very different backgrounds would mingle out of necessity – both the shepherd moving their flock to a distant market and the noble en route to a foreign palace needed shelter. In a highly stratified society, this provision of necessities like food, sleep, and protection brought unlikely figures into discourse.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TAVERN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As transportation became mechanized, inns became less important for the movement of goods and people, but every railway station and airport still sits near a cluster of hotels, motels, bars, and diners. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In archaeological circles, it has become something of a joke that if a settlement has an undefined large structure, that structure is labeled a “palace.” A second large structure gets the designation “temple,” even if the actual use of these buildings remains undetermined. A temple is a general term for a place of worship. English speakers are used to calling Christian temples "churches" and Muslim temples "mosques," but the default “temple” is used to describe structures as disparate as the Hindu mandir, the Jewish hekal, or the Buddhist wat or otera. All these structures are reserved spaces for religious practice – a place for contemplation, coming together, or other activities that stand apart in some way from the mundane world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_UNIVERSITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As soon as humanity started making detailed paintings of flora, fauna, and gods on cave walls, places of higher learning existed. But universities – institutionalized sites devoted to higher study – emerged in the first millennia CE. The title of “the first university” is contested – Nalanda in India was a residential place of learning for religious and philosophical students and was founded in the fifth century CE, but the first degree-granting university in the world was Al-Qarawiyyin in Fez, Morocco and, founded in the 9th century, is still in operation. The University of Bologna, the first university in Europe, started roughly two centuries later and also remains a bastion of higher learning. These institutes flourished in the Renaissance period in Europe, especially in the Mediterranean, and they are a backbone for the development of civic and scientific life today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_WHARF_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Wharves are fixed platforms used for docking ships. These structures allow easy access to cargo holds for unloading and storage. They are vital pipelines for the movement of goods from sea-borne trade lanes to consumers. Fishing wharves are a stock fixture in many coastal cities, as vessels large and small disgorge their catches to be picked up by merchants. In earlier times, potential sailors could scout for new assignments at a wharf (and ship captains for new crew members).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_AMPHITHEATER_EX_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word “amphitheater” references a semicircular or circular ring of seats surrounding a stage where performances, speeches, gladiatorial contests, poetry, and the like could be staged. The term is specific to Greek and Roman contexts, where it performed a key role in public entertainment. However, if "amphitheater" is used to reference any gathering point for performances, we find examples across several societies, from Balinese dance to Chinese village opera to the singing of Malinese griots. Stories are crafted to be shared, whether that be a politician’s speech, a mythological tale projected in shadow on a screen in a Malay market, or a story writ in bronze and blood upon gladiatorial ground.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ACADEMY_EX_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While universities are massive institutions of general study, academies are places for philosophical reflection. Confucian academies were quintessential examples – places where students of Confucianism could study and debate the classics. Expertise in classical texts was necessary to advance in the bureaucracy. In Greece, the classical academy was a school originally named for a grove of trees sacred to Athena, and scholars such as Plato and Socrates taught there. These schools emphasized debate and philosophy as well as a close relationship between teachers and students – a tradition exported to Persia under Alexander’s conquests. Academies merged naturally into larger universities in Africa (specifically Mali, Morocco, and Egypt) as interests and knowledge expanded, and as society realized it could no longer expect students to be masters of astronomy, philosophy, religion, and mathematics all at once!</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- Unique Buildings -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ANJUVANNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Five Hundred Lords and the manigramam were ethnic Indian traders; the anjuvannam was a guild of foreigners (most often Persians and Arabs, but could include Jews and Christians) operating within the Chola Empire. That such merchants not only existed, but existed in numbers requiring their own category, is a testament to the reach of the empire. Traders from every known people and religion operated in a complex web of trade. Such networks extended to Southeast Asia in the east (and from there to China) and the African coast and the Middle East to the west, linking the world in ways that would only intensify as history progressed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BAILEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A castle was more than its garrison. It functioned like a small town, with stables, storehouses, workshops, and chapels. These were built in the bailey, a fortified settlement wrapped around the base of the motte. Protected by palisades or walls, the bailey provided for the domestic and economic needs of the castle complex, and offered additional space for services that could not fit in the keep (or should not, such as kitchens, which were built away from major buildings as they were prone to fire). The keep could be accessed via stairs cut into the motte or a flying bridge that could be raised during an attack.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BAILEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Baileys, also called wards, remained a constant feature of castles beyond the motte-and-bailey era. Larger fortresses often had multiple baileys, with those on the outside dedicated to defensive measures and expendable structures, while the inner ward housed services crucial to survival during a prolonged siege.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CANDI_BENTAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One of the key features of a Hindu temple built in the Majapahit style is the candi bentar – the split gate. Resembling a mountain cracked in half, the candi bentar offers a glimpse of a world breaking open to reveal another one nested inside. It resembles a stupa (a dome-shaped structure) that has been divided in two, with smooth inner walls that act as the passageway for dancers of classical Javanese performances. The gates have no function other than aesthetic – no defensive purpose other than to generate awe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CANDI_BENTAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Hinduism in Indonesia was largely replaced by Islam in the 16th century, and remaining adherents fled to the island of Bali, where the population remains mostly Hindu. These forms of Hinduism have long departed from what is practiced in South Asia, although the basic structure remains: the relevant deities, features such as caste, philosophical underpinnings, etc. Balinese temples place a great emphasis on water, with a system of temples at spring sources, at the central point in the village, and downstream of the village – sites corresponding to creation, rule, and destruction, accordingly.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CASA_CONSISTORIAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>By the 16th century, Spain’s expansion across the globe began to manifest in its architecture and city planning. Regional seats of power consolidated and centralized their political offices in the casa consistorial, the city hall, which sprang up in central plazas. These structures contained the necessary trappings of government, such as court chambers, meeting rooms, libraries, and gala halls. The authority within was reflected without in the stately façade. These arresting building designs often combined popular Renaissance styles with local architectural trends. Ample statues and reliefs depicted coats of arms, motifs of law and justice, and prominent historical figures and scenes that traced the lineage of Spain’s importance as far back as the Roman era.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CASA_DE_CONTRATACION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Spain secured vast wealth and power through international endeavors, but these exploits were not effortless. They required immense preparation, organization, and maintenance, and in 1503 the crown opened the Casa de Contratación (“House of Trade”) in Seville to administer the demands of expansion. The Casa’s responsibilities were many – from handling the finances of Spain’s trading empire through taxation, revenue, and duty collection to organizing trade missions as well as provisioning and licensing the ships of the treasure fleet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CASA_DE_CONTRATACION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Throughout history, the Casa de Contratación also oversaw cartography for the exploration effort. Ship captains and officers returning from the New World reported discoveries and their locations under oath to officials. This information was passed on to the cartographers, who incorporated it into the Padrón Real, a secret and ever-growing map of the Spanish Empire. Charts were copied from this master and distributed to ships when they embarked on new voyages. In this way, the Casa de Contratación maintained control of information flowing from Spanish explorers and merchants while ensuring their ships were always up to date with the latest maps.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MADRASA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the early years of Islam, education occurred in the mosque. Lessons focused on spiritual teachings and practical skills, such as medicine and war. The rise of the Abbasids saw a boom in intellectual curiosity that inspired new directions for education. Institutions and study groups sprang up to investigate topics such as theology, history, philosophy, law, music, and literature. The needs of these new lessons quickly outstripped the mosque’s offerings, and by the 10th century, the madrasa had risen in prominence as a college for adults to further their education.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MADRASA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Madrasas varied in design and architecture but typically featured an ornate entry portal and a central courtyard surrounded by open chambers. Curriculums were arranged by a madrasa’s founder and covered both religious and secular topics. Madrasas soon spread across the Abbasid Empire in an effort to unite the learned population under one cultural identity through shared education.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MANIGRAMAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The lesser of the Chola trading traditions, manigramam was a term used to apply to itinerant Indian merchants in the empire, originating in the present-day state of Kerala. Much has been made of the Cholas’ overseas trade routes – lines stretching via vassals in Srivijaya (Sumatra), Kalinga, Bengal, Burma, present-day Thailand, Cambodia, and southern Vietnam (and possibly as far as Australia and Hawai’i, based on DNA evidence of plant goods). But Chola trading power also extended internally over areas of direct control, including Sri Lanka, Kerala, and all of the southern tip of India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MANIGRAMAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The diversity of traded goods influenced religion, culture, politics, and food across the region. The chili peppers that give so much South and Southeast Asian cuisines their heat remained undiscovered in Asia, growing as they were in Mesoamerica, but saffron, cumin, and other spices moved readily through manigramam holds – as did war elephants, jewels, and weapons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MERU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The center of the Hindu-Buddhist heavens is the summit of Mount Meru, the home of the gods. But Hindu temples in Bali are versions of the heavens in miniature, featuring soaring, tiered pinnacles also termed meru, after the mountain. As with its divine counterpart, each meru contains sacred objects that ensure the gods’ presence on the site (including the Nine Gems, discussed as a Siamese civic).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MERU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The meru structure indicates the relationship of Majapahit society to the idea of the divine. Javanese royalty traced its lineage back to the god Vishnu; having shrines ensured that some of this divine power remained at the ruler’s disposal. Indeed, the possession of secret stores of magical power was key to Indonesian kingship, and could be sourced from a divine ancestry, a supernatural guardian, or a magical kris (knife).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MOSQUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The mosque is the central place of Muslim worship. Initial incarnations were likely open-air spaces designated for prayer in the earliest days of Islam during the seventh century AD. Over time, mosques evolved into structures with distinctive architectural features to facilitate religious use. The mihrab is a niche in the wall, often highly decorated, and indicates the direction of Mecca so worshippers can orient themselves correctly in prayer. Minarets, tall thin towers adjacent to the mosque, are used by the muezzin to issue the call to prayer to the surrounding population five times a day. Beyond spiritual activities, mosques represent the heart of a Muslim community, providing a space not only for religious practice but also for education and social gathering.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MOTTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>High ground was an advantage for castles, but sometimes it had to be manufactured. Medieval Europeans molded the earth to create mottes, hills with artificially steep sides and a flat top. Mottes could be formed by either whittling down an existing hill or by building one from the soil, leaving a defensive ditch around the base of the structure that could be filled with water (or pointed logs) to create a moat. These slopes were extremely difficult for attackers to scale and were cheap to construct, requiring no specialized knowledge. As such, they were a quick and easy way of establishing a defensive advantage, even in a flat landscape.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MOTTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The keep, the central fortification of the castle complex, sat on top of the motte. Small keeps might hold a small garrison, while larger ones contained whole households, with cellars below stocked with supplies and chambers above for the noble family and their staff and guards.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--Civ Unique Improvements-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CARAVANSERAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Medieval Muslim trade routes crossed some of the most inhospitable terrain of their day. From the dry Eurasian steppe to the wastes of the Sahara, merchants needed places for rest and shelter during their journey. The word “caravanserai” is Persian in origin, and likely would not have been used by the Songhai, but the concept is the same: a rest station. Given the importance of trans-Saharan trade for the Songhai, these stops were vital in the maintenance and prosperity of trade routes. A typical caravanserai had walls for defense against raiders (or storms), stalls for animals, baths, mosques, and small markets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_LO_I_KALO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hawaiian rulers faced the same challenge as the Inca: how to turn mountainous terrain into a productive powerhouse? Like the Inca, they arrived upon a common solution: terraced farms. In the Hawaiian case, the staple crop, taro, required artificial wetlands to thrive, and lo’i kalo provided that space. The streams that feed lo’i kalo (literally “taro patch”) begin at artificial stone dams where cool water flows. This water is redirected to channels that feed the patches, and requires constant maintenance to ensure it flows fresh and cool. The establishment of these plots supplied one of the two major historical empires (along with the Inca) whose staple crops were not grains or cereals, but tubers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MING_GREAT_WALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>After the fall of the Han dynasty, the Great Wall was relatively neglected until the rise of the Ming. Like their forebears, the Ming again faced a threat from the North in the form of the Mongols. In 1421, the capital was moved to Beijing to address the conflict head-on, and Ming emperors began to fortify the territory around the city by renovating the old walls and building new ones better positioned to the current situation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MING_GREAT_WALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Unlike the Han, who used the Great Wall in their offensive strategy, the Ming employed the wall as a defensive structure, building it behind their existing borders as a final bastion against invasion. They invested more time and money into the building process, using stone and brick to build walls and strengthen older rammed earth sections. These techniques enabled walls to be built on steeper inclines, taking advantage of more advantageous terrain; the use of stone also permitting the inclusion of additional defensive flourishes like crenelations and arrow loops.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MING_GREAT_WALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Although the Great Wall delayed the onset of their Manchu conquerors, it ultimately could not save the Ming from their fate. Still, their structures remain the most famous, and most visited, sites on the Wall today, a lasting legacy of strength that has come to symbolize China’s illustrious history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ORTOO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In today’s world of near-instantaneous information, it is hard to imagine how crucial the flow of information was to a functioning empire when that information traveled only as fast as its messenger. For the Mongol Empire, which spread across the known world, a message had to be able to travel from China to Poland as fast as possible. The Mongols attempted to minimize this hurdle by creating a system of checkpoints – Örtöö – where a message could be transferred to a fresh rider and horse, who passed the message along again at another point closer to the destination. These checkpoints were spaced around 30 miles apart and moved messages nearly 200 miles in a day. In the years after the Mongol Empire collapsed, Russians adopted the system, eventually resulting in the postal service.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_TERRACE_FARM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Inca's ability to carve an empire on the slopes of a mountain range is nothing short of phenomenal. Where lowland empires had broad floodplains on which to plant crops, the Inca needed to create flat, stable platforms. They accomplished this by fitting together stone without mortar, making flat bases for soil and retaining walls, often with water channels to manage a stable irrigation system. With these structures – and rock's natural ability to store daytime heat and then emit it at night – the Inca began production on millions of acres of formerly inhospitable land, cultivating maize far outside of its natural growing zones and turning a mountain wilderness into a bread (or potato) basket for millions.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--City-State Improvements-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_KASBAH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The kasbah, from the Arabic “fortress,” was the citadel of medieval cities in North Africa. Defended by walls, towers, and a garrison, it typically hosted a settlement’s administration and ruling family. Beyond this, the kasbah varied widely in size and nature; in some regions, it was a small stronghold, while in others it was an entire fortified neighborhood and large enough to host a palace, a mosque, and other facilities. These larger kasbahs are often the oldest sections of modern cities, and the term has evolved as a synonym for medina, or historic quarter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MINOR_EMBASSY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first permanent embassy is typically traced to Renaissance Italy, specifically Milan, the center of European trade and style during the period. The history of embassies goes back much further than this, of course. The Byzantines maintained permanent ambassadors from different civilizations, and the Middle Ages saw diplomacy intertwined with religious domination throughout Europe. The Christian patriarchs, especially Rome and Constantinople, sent out missions to both convert external groups and advocate for their own superiority. These were typically temporary; Milan’s great innovation was the permanence of its embassies.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MINOR_EMBASSY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 15th century Italy, the Holy Roman Empire was nominally in control, but duchies were largely governed as independent city-states. Milan was ruled by the Duke of Milan, Francesco I Sforza, a capable ruler who had a keen sense of diplomatic affairs. He was the first European to conduct affairs with the aim of balancing powers, keeping any one state from becoming strong enough to dominate the others. Beyond the permanent embassies he established throughout northern Italy, he also conducted diplomacy with France, Spain, and England, while managing tense relations with the Ottoman Empire. His efforts helped ensure the continued independence of the Italian peninsula from other European powers.</Text>
		</Row>			
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MONASTERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Monasteries in the medieval and Early Modern periods were spaces of respite from the world at large. Monks and nuns laid aside their former lives to dedicate themselves to spiritual pursuits. This was a journey of the mind, not only through engagement with sacred doctrine but other academic topics. Monasteries were often the site of manuscript production, as their inhabitants were literate (unusual for the times) and inquisitive, well-suited to copying and composing religious texts – and eventually secular ones. The creation of manuscripts required peace, quiet, a lot of time, and money for materials. Monasteries provided these resources, enabling their residents to become theologians, historians, literary authors, and scientists.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_SAQIYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The saqiya is an irrigation device that has been used for centuries throughout northeastern Africa, the Middle East, India, and Southeast Asia. It consists of a large wooden wheel, its edge lined with buckets or pots. The wheel was placed vertically in the water and fastened to a large gear driven by a work animal, such as a donkey or ox. As the animal walked forward, the gear would twist, rotating the wheel in the water. The buckets would fill with water as the wheel turned, and then dispense the water into a channel that flowed to fields or sometimes to a bathhouse.</Text>
		</Row>	
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_SAQIYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Our earliest archaeological evidence of the saqiya comes from third century BCE Egypt, but similar waterwheels are referenced in ancient literary sources from the same period, making it unclear where they were first invented. In the Medieval period, the saqiya was a common feature found throughout the Islamic world. Islamic engineers perfected the device, creating complex versions that were more efficient and effective at gathering water. Today, thousands still exist throughout the Nile valley, though most are now motorized, freeing their work animals to more engaging lives.
			</Text>
		</Row>				
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_STONE_HEAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Stone heads have been a common theme among sculptors throughout history. Representations of the human face not only preserve the symbol of individuality but capture the face's ability to communicate without words. As a result, these sculptures are often explorations of identity, both human and divine. While stone heads were created in ancient times – including the huge mysterious Olmec heads – many variations emerged through the medieval period and beyond. The moai of Rapa Nui are the most famous of these statues. Their immense forms represent the living faces of Polynesian ancestors, and they face inland, keeping a watchful gaze over the land and its people. For centuries, Celtic artists in Europe carved smaller heads that varied widely in appearance and style. Their prevalence is ascribed to the head's sacred symbolism in religious beliefs and went hand-in-hand with the Celts’ keen enthusiasm for headhunting. West Africa saw the creation of the mahe-yafei, a type of soapstone carving by the Kisi people thought to have originally represented ancestors, like the moai. However, these carvings have taken on new meanings in modern times, and are now honored by the Mende as agricultural deities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_TRADING_FACTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The rise of the merchant class during the Middle Ages encouraged the development of formal communities for traders. Local guilds began to systematize regional commerce, establishing rules and regulations that improved their social and economic status...and their profits. Soon these guilds expanded into larger networks. Some were fueled by civilizations, like the Chola expansion via the markets of the Indian Ocean, while others operated beyond national borders, like the Hanseatic League in Northern Europe. By the 17th century, guilds and leagues had reorganized into private companies that often acted as extensions of their home states. They had their own fleets and soldiers to support their economic endeavors. European nations in particular leveraged these entities (such as the East India Company and the Hudson’s Bay Company) to establish a presence in regions, often with an eye toward colonization.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--Civ Unique Quarters-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_DONJON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The origin of the motte-and-bailey castle is unknown, but the style was popularized by the Norman ruler William the Conqueror, who introduced these structures to England following his 1066 invasion. Constructed of earth and timber, they were cheap and quick to build, but difficult to conquer. William raised hundreds of these castles across Britain, using them as nodes of power to consolidate his rule. They were so effective that he forbade their construction without royal permission.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_DONJON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Over time, timber, which rotted quickly and could easily catch fire, was replaced by stone for castle construction. These fortresses were far more complex, expensive, and time-consuming to raise, but they had many advantages over earlier designs. Their well-guarded donjons (central fortified towers) were more resistant to attack and allowed for new configurations that heightened their defensive capabilities. Castles became almost impossible to conquer directly, and could be captured only through siege or sabotage. Stone fortresses were imposing and prestigious buildings, broadcasting the wealth and authority of the aristocrats within. Although gunpowder eventually ended the age of castles, many survive today, immortalizing the beauty and power envisioned by their creators.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_ULEMA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Religion and education were closely intertwined under Abbasid rule, and the pursuit of knowledge was considered a key part of one’s spiritual journey. Early schooling focused on memorizing and studying religious texts. The development of the madrasa presented the opportunity for higher education and entry into the ranks of the ulema (the plural form of ʿālim), a community of scholars whose expertise on matters of legal import was invaluable to the empire. The mosque’s role as the center of spiritual and communal life formed a natural bond with the madrasa’s focus on religious-based scholarship, and the two buildings were typically constructed in a single complex that included a library and a boarding house for students, funded through charitable donations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_PLAZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The plaza was the center of Spanish government and society. These large open squares drew together the administrative buildings of a town or city, including the casa consistorial, the law court, and trade buildings of the Casa de Contratación, as well as the local church or cathedral. Because of its size and prominent location, the plaza was a key space for communal assemblies, operating as a site for social gatherings and celebrations as well as military parades. It was a consistent element of Spanish urban planning, so much so that it was exported to settlements around the world during Spain’s era of expansion and colonization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_PURA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hinduism was the first major global religion to reach Indonesia, arriving with the wave of Sanskrit and other South Asian influences in the first century AD. Hinduism spread via the poetry and epics of Sanskrit literature, and local rulers sought power by linking themselves via the religion to distant (and prestigious) centers in South Asia. Once settled in the palace, the religion slowly filtered down to the rest of the population. We see the construction of Hindu temples steadily from the first millennium onward, including the structures at Borobudur, Prambanan, and elsewhere. Building temples became a language of power for Majapahit elites, one they took with them as they fled their declining empire to the island of Bali.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_PURA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>From Bali, we take the term “pura.” Hindu temples in Java, where the Majapahit Empire was based, are still referred to as candi, but here we use the Balinese term to avoid confusion with the candi bentar building as well as mark the Majapahit legacy of the island.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_FIVE_HUNDRED_LORDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Positioned at the tip of the Indian subcontinent, the Chola Dynasty was at the heart of the seagoing Silk Road. It managed much of its naval exploits via a loose network of merchant houses and privateers, of which the Five Hundred Lords was of special note. Casting themselves as adventurer-merchants, the Five Hundred Lords specialized in risky adventures abroad (including Southeast Asia) as well as investment in infrastructure and maintenance at home (including ports and irrigation). Their goods included spices of all kinds, elephants, and horses, as well as gold and jewels. In addition, they cast themselves as those upholding a noble creed, the vira-banaju-dharma, the law of the hero-merchants.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>