<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Exploration Civics -->
		<!-- Main Branch Civics -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_FUTURE_CIVIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“The future is unwritten” proclaimed the punk rocker Joe Strummer, but this has not stopped generations of people seeking to create a new model for society. From Communist republics to millenarian movements, people have long sought to reshape society into forms never before seen, all in a quest to further perfect human belonging. The task remains incomplete, the revolution unfinished, the utopian world unrealized, but this does not prevent us from imagining what could be, just around the corner. Or, perhaps, on the next turn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_ECONOMICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The regulation of trade and commerce was a feature of court life as far back as the Babylonians, but economics offers a more holistic perspective on systems of commerce. How are resources produced, managed, and distributed? How can this system be manipulated to produce the best possible results (and for whom)? Debate over such questions traces back to antiquity, e.g. the Han dynasty’s “Discourses on Salt and Iron,” which records free-market challenges to the long-standing practice of royal monopolies over certain goods. Arab philosopher Ibn Khaldun, the “father of economics,” was the first to propose a supply and demand curve, and to note that money had no inherent value outside of exchange, a principle that would (likely unknowingly) also occur to later scholars, such as Karl Marx.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_ECONOMICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the later part of the Exploration era, issues of economics became vital to the survival of empires, as industrialized imperial centers required an influx of raw goods as well as a market for finished products, creating the mercantilist system that proved so vexing to colonies in India and the Americas. Counter to this were Adam Smith’s notions of free trade and the potential of a new economy…with new challenges.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_PIETY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>We are caught between our public and our private selves – as Claude Levi-Strauss writes, that aspect of ourselves that is perceived by another is both inaccessible to us and the basis for social life at the same time. This social self asks us to care for our kin, to fulfill our role vis-à-vis the state or other social organizations, and to be a part of a spiritual community. Piety, from the Latin “dutiful,” is at the core of this concept. For Confucians, filial piety – devotion to family and community – is one of the key virtues, whereas in more mystical religions piety may ask one to leave family and community in exchange for devotion to the divine (i.e. holy men, monks, and other mendicants). The development and richness of religious devotion in medieval times was diverse, from Hindu rishi who left civilized life to live in poverty in the mountains, to Christian saints who walled themselves in cellars voluntarily with only a small opening to provide air and nourishment. A common thread between these measures is an orientation toward something greater than our individual needs, and a willingness to sacrifice the self for this purpose.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_AUTHORITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“I am the state,” proclaimed Louis XIV. Thus the Sun King declared himself to be synonymous with the power of the French Empire – not a representative of the masses, nor an efficient manager of the heritage of the land, but authority embodied. For Louis, as for other absolute monarchies – Imperial Germany, Meiji Japan, Fifth Reign Siam, and Tsarist Russia, to name a few – authority became the ultimate feature of absolutist rule. This was a modern invention. As feudalism decayed, a centralized bureaucratic state based around the body of the sovereign and the apparatus of rule grew. This was a kind of despotism, but one where authority was enshrined in royal charisma – the Russian tsars and the French kings had to prove their authority by increasingly elaborate spectacles of power lest they be perceived as less than they claimed. It set the stage for the twilight of the Exploration era and the end of the golden age of monarchy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_INSPIRATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Creativity is not quantifiable. It cannot be engineered or programmed or mandated, but it can be fostered. The development of social roles for creatives, and the granting of time and resources for purely creative pursuits is a necessary luxury for social life. At times, such outlets are limited to the religious or political sphere, where art is required to reflect certain truths, but even then artists are often able to subvert mandates to express something of themselves. For instance, the dramatic bas-relief carvings depicting Ashurbanipal’s lion hunt reflect the (likely mandated) power of the ruler, but the faces of the lions are pitiable – historians are divided on whether or not this reflects a profound critique of Ashurbanipal’s bloodlust or a genuine bloodlust on the part of the carver. Later nobles and other patrons would often sponsor creatives, allowing an artist, writer, or inventor to focus on works of insight and beauty rather than producing goods to sell on the market. It remains to be seen whether this space persists in societies that rely upon the market to fund these pursuits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_SOCIETY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Society” has come to stand in for many things, but like the term “public,” “society” refers to a collective – a group with its own norms, rules, codes of conduct, and opinions. Societies require a forum where these norms are voiced, and they have a common understanding of how things should work. Widespread literacy and the growth of newspapers – along with an increasing standardization of mechanized time and life around factories – meant that even a widely dispersed population could have a common perspective. If multiple people read the same paper, they understood the day’s events in similar ways, even if their individual takes on these events differed. Even before this, standardized religious sermons, public announcements, the growth of universities, and the steady increase in urban life led to the development of a social consciousness, something we could term “society.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_BRANCH_THEOLOGY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is the nature of the soul? What is the relationship between the mundane and the sacred? Questions such as these have formed the basis of theological inquiry across many religions. Christianity finds rationalistic arguments for God and how to reach divine revelation in the writings of Thomas Aquinas, John Calvin, and others – arguments over whether works or faith should take priority, or how to reconcile an omniscient, omnipotent creator with the fact that some individuals are damned. In Muslim thought, a key schism revolves around the proper interpretation of divine law as revealed in the Quran. In Hinduism and Buddhism, theological questions (though the latter does not have a theos, or god) probe the nature of the soul (or atman). The two religions differ on this point. Hinduism posits the persistence of the soul in every living thing. Buddhism takes the opposite tack; there is no essence, all being is dependent. Regardless, each religion has a dedicated group of people whose role in society is to study the interplay between the divine and mundane and to understand our role in a greater cosmic sphere, which transcends our earthly existence (or, for Buddhists, non-existence).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_BRANCH_REFORMATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Protestant Reformation rethought the relationship between the believer and their church. As the Catholic Church positioned itself as the sole interpreter of the divine, it established a political structure that went above and beyond that of earthly kings – naturally, Catholics were bound to a higher authority. However, Martin Luther and other Protestants posited that individuals could cultivate a personal relationship with the divine. This approach ran on the back of an urbanizing society, which drew on and contributed to popular literacy; Protestants made sure the Bible was available in vernacular languages for everyday understanding.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_BRANCH_REFORMATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But religious reformation spans past those Christian and European examples. Within Southeast Asia, Theravada Buddhism offered something similar to Protestantism; whereas Mahayana in the region had focused on the divine right of the elite, allowing the populace to continue traditions they had practiced for millennia, Theravada strove to educate everyone (actually, only boys) in the basic principles of the religion and provide some degree of literacy. Meanwhile, Islam lacked an establishment akin to the Catholic Church, so there was no need for a reform along Luther’s lines as Muslims who sought piety were already expected to read and study scripture for themselves.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_SOVEREIGNTY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Who has the power to determine what is right and what is not? Who has a monopoly over the law and the justified use of violence (e.g. police, military)? These are questions about sovereignty. This topic became pressing for Protestant states as they broke away from the authority of the Catholic Church; in the absence of a Pope, who has the authority to criticize a state’s actions? In Asia, powerful states such as China, Siam, and Vietnam often negotiated the proper conduct of a weaker neighbor, both to ensure their own status as a regional hegemon and to keep the peace nearby.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_SOVEREIGNTY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Early modern writings are replete with calls for sovereignty (most famously Thomas Hobbes’ “Leviathan”) in the twilight of the Ming tributary system, as well as within the colonized world. Writings such as those by Phan Bội Châu, the struggles of Túpac Amaru II, and Siamese declarations of the itsaraphap (independence) of its monarchy all echo the desire for sovereignty, whereas principles of human rights, international criminal courts, and arms conventions seek to limit its worst excesses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_IMPERIALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Imperialism, as a modern political movement, is related to colonialism. However, while colonialism carries weight directly among populations, imperial structures impose political power. For instance, Sheldon Pollock has contrasted the imperial structure of Rome (which maintained foreign control via military might) with the Sanskrit world (power influenced via the arts and religion without political domination). Examples exist elsewhere – the Inca's “Empire of the Four Parts” established a lingua franca, co-opted local figures, and established control over smaller groups. Imperialism also existed among the Aztecs, Mongols, and nearly all civilizations in this game. However, imperialism's 19th-century interpretation extended centralized power across the world for the aggrandizement of the capital – seizing all things for fame, profit…and to distract from conflicts at home. Imperialism went hand-in-hand with absolute monarchy, the growth of the bureaucratic state, and the establishment of for-profit trading companies, shaping the world into its present form.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_BUREAUCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>State functions can seem abstract. Questions that range from “Who is fit to occupy what role?” to “Have all been paid for working on the city walls?” require some degree of bookkeeping, whether that is recorded in Sumerian clay tablets, Inca quipu, or a computer spreadsheet. Bureaucracy may seem cold and faceless, turning human experience and struggle into statistical models, but this is precisely the point – without such a system, large-scale organizations become unmanageable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_BUREAUCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Standardization was a famous facet of Confucian societies, where a system of examinations was put in place so personal preference would not dictate the state's needs. However, the golden age of bureaucracy is likely the centralized states of the modern period, where an increasingly mobile population met a scientific establishment that focused on the desire to know all about its populace. This led to the fusion of power and knowledge, the creation of sciences such as demographics, psychology, and more and more in-depth economics, all serving the purposes of control.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_SOCIAL_CLASS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Class consciousness is an awareness that one’s interests are influenced by one’s labor. Social theorists of the 19th century pointed to a few basic divisions of class: feudal subjects might be serfs who were bonded to a particular plot of land, a lord could be the owner of that land and those serfs, and an artisan was free with the right to engage in certain kinds of labor. With some important variations, similar divisions held for the Indian varna (caste), East Asian social class, Southeast Asian sakdina systems, and the like. Industrialization bred a new consciousness as the serf and farmer classes flocked to cities to work in factories. In the city, classes had clear divisions: aristocrats who had titles and land and did not labor; bourgeoisie who owned factories, machines, and other tools; the petit bourgeoisie (shopkeepers and the like) who were free and could own property on a smaller scale; and the proletariat, the masses with nothing to their name but their capacity to work. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_SOCIAL_CLASS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>For Karl Marx, and other social theorists, this was a vital split: the bourgeoisie had to legitimate their ability to generate profit without actually having to work, and the proletariat needed to remain deluded enough to accept these terms. This model was not based on organic systems of harmony and stasis (as we might find in feudal or Confucian models); rather, it was a system with inherent conflict. At the end of feudalism, the bourgeoisie would wake up to the notion that aristocratic titles were meaningless and unprofitable. Similarly, at the end of capitalism, the proletariat would wake up to the notion that factory owners contributed nothing to production but extracted value from their workers' labor. Marx drew from examples from the French and American revolutions (as examples of the bourgeois revolt against feudal systems) as well as the revolutions of 1848, where social class entered the picture in a dramatic fashion. However, he did not live to see the later revolutions carried out under his name (indeed, who knows what he would have thought of these).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_DIPLOMATIC_SERVICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Today’s career diplomats – shuffled from one post to another every few years while engaging in bureaucratic negotiations in business hotels and conference halls – are a far sight from the diplomats of earlier times. In the past, a foreign posting meant spending an entire lifetime – and often dying – abroad.  These diplomats could be at once an adventurer, a spy, a politician, an entrepreneur, a judge, as well as a representative of their home nation. The officials of the VOC – the Dutch East India Company – were expected to make a lifelong commitment to their position, which included having a family with local women where they were stationed (that is, in the early period of colonialism, before the Dutch state took over the administration). In a previous era, one might see travelers such as Marco Polo or Ibn Battuta as diplomats – wandering representatives of a far-off land sent to gather information and stories about places of interest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_MERCANTILISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The relationship between empire and trade is delicate and has been worthy of concern since the early days of civilization. In the modern era, when colonialism coincided with industrialization, states saw their colonial possessions as sources of raw materials to fuel industrial booms back home. For instance, to ensure Liverpool’s prosperity, England could not have Indian merchants selling raw materials to other countries’ manufacturing centers. Mercantilism was the solution – control over trade that ensured goods could only be exchanged with approved merchants.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_MERCANTILISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In opposition was the notion of free trade, where anyone could sell to anyone. This idea threatened colonial systems with destabilization, as the merchant class in the colonies could become independently wealthy, decreasing their reliance on the state. (In the case of India, free trade proved dangerous as needed goods and food were shifted toward markets where they could yield a larger profit, leaving many hungry.) As such, mercantilism was one of the core complaints of many wealthy colonists and a prime cause of revolutions across the New World.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_COLONIALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The eras after the 16th century have come to be defined, worldwide, by colonial systems of control. In short, colonialism is an imperial power's attempt to establish outposts around the world for the purpose of extracting local resources. This usually involved either the replacement of the original inhabitants (often grisly business) or their ideological and cultural assimilation. This assimilation was never equal – colonial subjects were not considered metropolitan subjects. This division between colonized and non-colonized created the framework upon which present-day concepts like race were constructed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAIN_COLONIALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Colonization features a few distinct phases – an early one, where powerful companies seized foreign land and assets to fuel trade and extraction, leaving “unproductive” areas largely untouched (aside from the imposition of Christianity). In late colonization, metropoles took direct control, managing and regulating the population. Settler colonies varied greatly, but the indigenous populations were often displaced, killed, or replaced by metropolitan inhabitants.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Civ-Specific Civics -->
		<!--Abbasid-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ABBASID_ROUND_CITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some would say city planning is a modern innovation. They are incorrect. Grid cities existed as far back as 2600 BCE in Harappa, in the Indus River Valley, and across Classical antiquity. Cities such as Persepolis were monuments to the learning, forward-thinking, and prestige of the builder. The Abbasids were no different.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ABBASID_ROUND_CITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thousands of years later, Baghdad, “god’s gift,” was a monumentally planned city. Around 765 CE, Caliph al-Mansūr constructed the round city, which contained the residence of the Abbasid court, the House of Wisdom, the principal Abbasid mosque, and the Abbasid palace. The city was a testament to the divine right of the caliphs to rule their empire, the Dar al-Islam (the Muslim world), as well as all enlightened peoples. Wave after wave of invasion and destruction, by no less than Genghis Khan, proved otherwise.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ABBASID_MAWLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the Arab caliphates expanded, they incorporated a wide body of non-Arabs into their collective, most notably Persian. Persian language and culture had a profound impact on many Muslim societies, especially from Mesopotamia eastward. This raises a fundamental question: to what extent are cultures, languages, and other markers of identity separable from religion? The oldest global religions – Judaism, Shinto, and Hinduism – do not focus on conversion. In contrast, the conversion of foreign groups is a key goal of the world’s newer religions of Buddhism, Christianity, and Islam.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ABBASID_MAWLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the Arab caliphates, the category of “mawla” became a way to incorporate non-Arabs into an Arab-dominated structure. In the Abbasid Caliphate, this especially meant Persians, including the leading general of the Abbasid Revolution, Abu Muslim Abd al-Rahman ibn Muslim al-Khurasani. This tolerance gave the Abbasids a key advantage over their rivals when it came to bringing large numbers of potential allies, subjects, and converts into the fold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_ABBASID_AL_JABR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The bane of middle schoolers everywhere, Al-Jabr is better known in English as algebra. The term is the shortened name of the “Compendious Book on Calculation by Completion and Balancing” by the Abbasid scholar Muhammad ibn Mūsā al-Khwārizmī. This text, detailing polynomial equations and elementary algebra, represents the advances in mathematical thought by the Abbasids and their contribution to the fields of math and astronomy. For further evidence of their import, we need look no further than the many English words for mathematical and astronomical concepts that are borrowed from Arabic, such as algebra, algorithm, azimuth, nadir; or the Arabic numerals that have replaced Roman ones in the Latin script, including those used in this game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Chola-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_CHOLA_NAGARAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Terms such as “nagar”, “negara”, “angkor”, and “nakhorn” proliferate around the Indian Ocean region, but they mean roughly the same thing: town. However, under the late Cholas, the variant “nagaram” adopted a new meaning. Chola society was organized around merchant guilds, and after the 12th century, merchant outposts used the term nagaram to refer to their local base of operations. These urban centers were influential in regulating commerce and the larger society as they pushed for the formation of jati, a caste system where communities collectively became associated with a particular profession or trade. In this context, nagaram became vital to the functioning of Tamil society (the ethnic group most closely associated with the Chola) more deeply than European guilds, encompassing all facets of society and mobilizing them for the benefit of trade groups.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_CHOLA_DIGVIJAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Violence emerges when words fail – when all attempts at the legitimation of control lose efficacy. Famously, after the Mauryan king Ashoka realized the horrors he had inflicted in conquest, he renounced violence in all of its forms. But Ashoka was an outlier; several South Asian kings not only conquered but devised strategies to legitimate their conquests.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_CHOLA_DIGVIJAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>For the Chola, power came alongside religion, poetry, and literature. Conquest and stories of conquest were linked. This was central in the concept of the Digvijaya, the conquest of the directions. Rulers would cast themselves as righteous monarchs – a chakravarti in Buddhist terms – to reframe a very calculated strike as one destined to “turn the wheel” of karma, keeping the world on its progression toward enlightenment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_CHOLA_KANAKAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Southern India – the home of the Tamil and their Chola dynasty – sits at the heart of the Indian Ocean. From here, powerful merchant houses managed trade between the Abbasid Empire, Aksum, and Tang China, and outward from the Indian subcontinent. This was a powerful position, and the flood of kanakam (Chinese gold) into Chola trading hubs enriched their coffers. On these trade routes, Chola language (especially script), religion, and culture traveled widely – a conquest that was much more successful than Chola military expeditions. A series of wars with the Khmer and others proved inconclusive, but by the end of the Chola period, Sanskrit poetry was being read across the Indian Ocean.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_CHOLA_MONSOON_WINDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The prevailing winds over the Indian Ocean experience yearly shifts. In the summer, when the land is hot and the sea is cool, winds blow from the southwest ocean, bringing moist air and rainfall to the subcontinent and Southeast Asia. In the winter, cooler air blows down from Mongolia, though this path is largely blocked by the Himalayas. It is not an overstatement to say that everything depends on the monsoon in this part of the world – rains bring life-giving water to crops, power hydroelectric dams, and renew the parched land for another season. Unsurprisingly, in many South and Southeast Asian countries, the New Year begins at the monsoon, not on a shift in the sun that is barely perceptible in equatorial climates.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_CHOLA_MONSOON_WINDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Chola exploited these winds for travel. A ship could voyage east at one time of the year buoyed by the winds, and west a half of a year later.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Hawaii-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_HAWAII_MANA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The question “what is mana” could be better posed as “what is not mana?” The concept is often appropriated by games to suggest magical energy, but it comes from Polynesian cultures and is not entirely translatable without understanding an entire worldview. Mana is the power that gives the world life and strength, that which makes sacred things sacred and strong things strong – its Hawaiian use is more of a verb than a noun. Mana is an action of kings and priests (kahuna) and places. It incorporates supernatural power as well as physical strength all at once, and is maintained by observing rites and ritual prohibitions (kapu, a form of taboo).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_HAWAII_OHANA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>More than “family,” ohana represents a concept of community, a mutual interdependence. The word appears to be new to the Hawaiian dictionary; it doesn't appear in very old texts and may have developed as an outsider's characterization of the “Hawaiian family” or as an assertion of unity in the face of Hawaiian disruptions of the 19th and 20th centuries. During this time, waves of labor immigration incorporated new Asian residents into the Hawaiian fold, while a white American minority with powerful corporate connections slowly increased its control over the island.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_HAWAII_HE_E_NALU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Being moved by the waves allows one to feel the grip of a far greater power. For Hawaiians, the sea was the source of food, resources, trade, warfare, and, ultimately, the Hawaiian people themselves. The sea’s power was something that demanded magico-religious awe and veneration. Surfing, or he’e nalu (“wave sliding”), placed one in harmony with this power; it was a religious sport of nobility in the islands. Kings, blessed by the kahuna, displayed their grace and power through direct interaction with the sea, showing their mana in tandem with nature’s power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_HAWAII_HE_E_NALU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Surfing remained a sport of kings and was a curiosity until it became popularized in the mid-20th century, especially with the figure of Duke Kahanamoku, a Hawaiian of noble birth who gained fame via an Olympic gold medal, and who used his platform to bring surfing and Hawaiian culture to a wider audience.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Inca-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_INCA_AYLLU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ayllu are clans in Inca society, but they are also more than that. An ayllu is a community with a common fictive ancestor that controls a particular area of land. On that level, they managed the land and dealt with larger demands, such as the imperial corvée known as the mit’a. The preservation of local communities is a key function of imperial control; it allows for local land management, keeps leadership relatively autonomous, and permits communal practices even among larger unequal systems. Ayllu made a mark on the landscape, preserving shrines of local deities and sacred spaces as well as markers of faith and fealty to the tirakuna (the earth beings).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_INCA_MITA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mit’a literally means “season,” and was the regular corvée labor system in the Inca Empire. It was a complicated system but was vital to the massive infrastructure, expansion, and military conquests of the Inca. Mit’a service could consume the vast majority of the year, up to 300 days. All the time that wasn't used for farming was expected to be used in service of the state. Labor units were arranged by ethnic group or profession: craftsmen were not required to serve in war or as farmers, and particular conquered people were often assigned to roles in which they had a perceived skill. In this way, the great Andean roads and bridges were built and maintained, armies were levied, and imperial granaries and treasuries were filled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_INCA_MITA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Inca, of course, were exempt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_INCA_QHAPAQ_NAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Empires thrive in flat, fertile floodplains, where rivers and grassland provide easy movement for goods, armies, messages, pilgrims, and so on. The Inca – a massive, well-organized empire based in the jagged peaks of the Andes – provide a shocking counterpoint. Their empire was only possible thanks to quality roads and bridges, which, in turn, could only be maintained through corvée labor supplied by stable farming.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_INCA_QHAPAQ_NAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Qhapaq Nan were these Incan roads. First laid down long before the Inca, these routes reached their greatest breadth during the Incan heyday. These roads were walled, shored up, featured drainage, and used entirely by people on foot (and pack animals such as llamas). The system stretched over two million kilometers, from present-day Colombia to Chile, and linked together relay stations, warehouses, inns, and pilgrimage sites.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Majapahit-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_WAYANG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the Sanskrit epics travelled along monsoon trade routes from South Asia to Southeast Asia, they inspired new innovations in art and expression. One of the most striking is the Indonesian wayang – shadow puppetry. In a wayang performance, leather puppets depicting the heroes of the Mahabharata or Ramayana are manipulated in front of a light source and behind a transparent screen to dramatize stories of gods and kings – or other indigenous epics such as the stories of Panji, a Javanese prince.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_WAYANG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Wayang performances were and (in Bali) are still performed for the benefit of the Hindu gods as well as spectators; while in Muslim Indonesia, wayang adopts a more literary and cultural form. As with the Greek epics in a Christianized Europe, stories of no-longer-worshipped gods and heroes still inspire, and performances are held for Muslim festivals as well as secular ones.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_ALIRAN_KEPERCAYAAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Indonesia is a melting pot of peoples, religions, cultures, and traditions – notably the Indonesian language, Bahasa Indonesia, is considered one of the easiest languages to learn simply because it is designed as a lingua franca, a trade language. Indigenous traditions of Javanese, Balinese, Bugis, Dayak, and a multitude of other peoples blended with waves of Hindu and Buddhist traditions from South Asia, and again later with Chinese religions and eventually Islam following the 12th century CE. This combination of religions – referred to as syncretism (the blending of two religious forms to make a third) or hybridity (the ongoing interchange between multiple religious traditions and their mutual alteration) – is referred to as aliran kepercayaan (“the branches of belief”).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_ALIRAN_KEPERCAYAAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Which beliefs take precedence have troubled scholars for years. Did Majapahit and earlier rulers adopt Indian forms, or did they incorporate Indian imagery into a fundamentally Southeast Asian organization? More recent scholarship downplays this question – all religious beliefs are constantly being adapted and changing to fit new situations, new societies, and new imaginaries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_NUSUNTARA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Nusantara, or “outer islands,” is the Javanese term for the Indonesian archipelago. Majapahit (and present-day Indonesia) are thalassocracies – states that exert control through dominance of the sea and, often, trade routes. With the Majapahit navy patrolling the waters, independent powers are cut off from all sources of luxury, commerce, religious pilgrimage, learning, and communication.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_NUSUNTARA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Majapahit extended from eastern Java, much of Sumatra, present-day Malaysia (and parts of southern Thailand), Sulawesi, coastal Borneo, and much of Indonesia’s smaller islands. Still, power in the nusantara always stemmed from the sea, carried to the islands on the planks of Majapahit ships.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_GAMELAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The music of the Indonesian gamelan is chaotic and haunting. It operates on polyphonic synchronism – a layered musical texture where multiple instruments (such as lutes, gongs, and flutes) play different melodies that come together and break apart. Gamelan reached its standardized form under Majapahit, and its performance in Bali retains part of the religious character that it once held. It can be performed with dance, depicting the legends of the region and telling stories often imported in distant years from South Asia, including epics such as the Ramayana and Mahabharata.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MAJAPAHIT_GAMELAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Gamelan is still practiced in Indonesia and is listed as a UNESCO Cultural Heritage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Ming-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MING_DA_MING_LU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Great Ming Code, written into its final form in 1397 CE, was implemented by the Hongwu Emperor. More than a system of governance, it was a moral and cultural document, a codification of how to remain in line with the natural and social order. It provided a clear break from the past Mongol-led Yuan Dynasty and birthed a resurgence of a Han Chinese social order. In its attempt to place social and moral life under a legal order, it established the bones of a modern order.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MING_DA_MING_LU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Great Ming Code is the basis for multiple attempts to establish an enduring and cosmically-oriented legal code in Korea, Vietnam, and Japan – not to mention the subsequent Qing Dynasty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MING_LIJIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Organizing an empire as vast as Ming China was a formidable task. Other empires managed to rule by keeping local units autonomous, but Ming sought to mobilize the power of local communities for defense, taxation, and labor. This was the lijia, a system of categorization and taxation that sought to mobilize peasants for state purposes. Each household was registered in a central book (the huangce) and categorized by the number of males in the household and the size of their fields. The lijia also established a village head for each community who could take over duties such as tax collection, civic festivals, funding schools, and sending tribute to the center.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MING_LIJIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Such organizational systems are part of a more general centralization and control, bringing disparate people under the same banner and way of life. In different ways, this became a common feature of societies as the medieval period gave way to modernity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MING_NINE_GARRISONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The end of Mongolian power in China came with the Ming victory over the Yuan Dynasty in 1368. The Mongols fled northward back into Mongolia but remained a constant threat to the Ming. In response, the Hongwu Emperor built a series of garrisons along the border. The Yongle Emperor continued this emphasis on fortification, moving his capital to Beijing in part to better administer this defense. The Mings’ aggressive posture received a nearly fatal blow in 1449 when Mongol forces destroyed half the Chinese army and captured the Emperor. Subsequent rulers focused on building additional walls and garrisons, containing the Mongol threat rather than pushing back against it. The later Hongzhi Emperor installed the Jiubian, the Nine Garrisons, as a bulwark against the Mongols, and expanded the wall from the sea, just north of Beijing, in the east to Jiayu Pass in the west, creating a hard, fortified border.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MING_NINE_GARRISONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The wall worked…for a time. In 1629, the Manchu leader Hong Taiji breached the defense, precipitating a crisis that would eventually lead to the fall of Ming, and the rise of the new, Manchu-led Qing Dynasty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Mongolia-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MONGOLIA_ULUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mongol Empire, or Yeke Mongyol Ulus, is inextricably connected with the rise of Temüjin, a noble of a nomad clan who fought, schemed, and negotiated his way to become the ruler of an association of Mongol tribes. He then led them to establish, via horse archers and cannons, the largest land empire in history. Genghis Khan, as he was later known, governed an incredibly diverse empire that held Chinese and Russians, Arabs and Persians, Turks and Burmese, all under the same banner.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MONGOLIA_ULUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>After the empire broke up, ulus came to mean “horde,” a term that is a bit of a misnomer as it is taken from the Turkic word “orda,” which means “camp.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MONGOLIA_FOUR_HOUNDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Secret History of the Mongols describes Genghis Khan’s four elite generals as “dogs of war”: “Chisels for snouts and awls for tongues, iron for hearts and whips for swords, drinking the dew and racing the wind – they go.” </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MONGOLIA_FOUR_HOUNDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each of the great Khan’s generals – Jebe, Kublai, Jelme, and Subutai – was a master strategist and tactician. Subutai in particular rose above the rest. He lacked the skill with horses of his Mongol compatriots (he was from a Turkic tribe), but made up for that with a focus on tactics. He deployed siege engines to devastating effect and exploited the Mongols’ most effective weapon: fear. Spies sent in advance would spread stories about the Mongols’ ferocity in battle. When coupled with a blistering artillery barrage and a heavy cavalry rush out from a smokescreen, most battles were won before they even began. Subutai himself was responsible for the conquest of Eastern Europe, Russia, and Persian-speaking lands, and his tactics were studied and deployed by Russian generals well into the 20th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MONGOLIA_YASSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Yassa was the legal code of the Mongolian Empire. No complete record of it remains, but excerpts are quoted by Ibn Battuta and others. As with other legal codes of its time, the Yassa extended beyond civic regulations to include religious and sacred prohibitions, such as the prohibition on washing clothes unnecessarily or during thunder (though that might also be a practical concern), and was thus carefully guarded by Mongolian nobility. The Yassa forbade the shedding of noble blood (in the literal sense – punishments often involved trampling by horses, while offending commoners, under no such restrictions, were just decapitated). The code also guaranteed religious freedom – a forward-thinking rule that was necessary for such a wide-ranging and diverse empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_MONGOLIA_YASSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Yassa also regulated soldiers' behavior. Generals were forbidden from making peace with enemies who had not surrendered, and from allowing their troops to pillage until the order had been given.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Norman-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_NORMAN_CONSUETUDINES_ET_JUSTICIE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The power of the Norman dukes was passed down through practiced custom rather than written law, an oral preservation of authority that was fragile in the face of political change. When Robert Curthose, William the Conqueror’s eldest son, prepared to embark on the First Crusade in 1096, he sought a regent to oversee Normandy in his absence. His younger brother William Rufus, King of England, paid 10,000 silver marks for the responsibility, but he was less familiar with the customary rights of Norman rulers. To ensure a smooth transition, Robert and William commissioned an inquest to establish these rights in writing. The barons and bishops of Normandy convened at Caen to record their knowledge in a text now known as “Consuetudines et Justicie” (“Customs and Justice”), providing an unusual snapshot of the responsibilities and limitations of power established by the Conqueror himself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_NORMAN_COMMON_LAW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before the arrival of the Normans, the peoples of Britain relied on local courts and customs to solve social problems. These practices were not written down but became widely accepted within communities over centuries of use. The Normans recognized the deep roots of such traditions among the populace and promoted them within their legal system. Judges responsible for hearing local cases decided their rulings based on local customs. These decisions were treated as binding, creating precedent for future rulings. In drawing solutions from regional practices and codifying them on a kingdom level, the Normans created a “common law” that was instituted across all English courts. In modern times, the system was spread by the British Empire to its many colonies, and it remains a leading form of law around the globe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_NORMAN_DOMESDAY_BOOK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the wake of the Norman Conquest in 1066, a new regime gained authority over England, and the connection between the crown and the land it controlled was shaken. By 1085, William the Conqueror sought to reforge these ties through a comprehensive survey of his realm to determine who owned what. In part, he wanted to assess how much each holding owed the crown in taxes and knights for his army; but he also gained insight into the total value of his kingdom. The results of this survey were recorded in heavily abbreviated Latin in a manuscript later named the Domesday Book. It remains the most complete public record of this period, capturing the distribution of power and wealth across Anglo-Norman England.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Songhai-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SONGHAI_SHIPS_OF_THE_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The trade routes across the Sahara stitched together the savannahs of the Sahel and Sudan and the Muslim caliphates of North Africa and the Near East. These journeys could take months and were beset by risks posed by a hostile environment and numerous nomadic tribes. Gold, copper, horses, and enslaved people were all exchanged. With this trade came new ideas in art, architecture, and religion; even as Ibn Battuta bemoaned the syncretic and culturally different West African practice of Islam, rulers such as Mansa Musa of Mali were known for their piety.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SONGHAI_HI_KOI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Songhai military calls to mind images of cavalry sweeping across the savannah. This is not entirely inaccurate, but the Songhai also retained a powerful navy based in the Niger River, on whose waters the empire depended. The hi-koi, the “master of the waters,” commanded this navy and maintained control over the river that was vital to maintaining power in the Songhai heartland. He also oversaw more peaceful traffic on the river, including the safe passage of merchant and civilian crafts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SONGHAI_KANTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Named after the kingdom of Kebbi (an ethnic Sorko kingdom whose ruler was called Kanta), large riverine kanta ships were important vehicles for transporting messages and troops along the Niger River, which ran through several important points within the Songhai Empire. The name of these vessels is emblematic of the systems of domination that the Songhai held over neighboring people, epitomized by the figure of the Songhai monarch who demanded his subjects approach prostrated, and who (according to accounts) was often surrounded by seven hundred eunuchs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Spain-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SPAIN_COUNCIL_OF_THE_INDIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The supreme governing unit of the Americas and East Indies, the Council of the Indies was created in 1524 to manage the rapidly expanding Spanish Empire. Before this, adelantados (contracts awarded to adventurers) had been extremely lucrative for individuals, but the system represented a threat to centralized Spanish authority. The Council replaced this old order. It was largely independent but reported directly to the monarch and oversaw New World taxation, expeditions, and wars.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SPAIN_COUNCIL_OF_THE_INDIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Oddly enough, the Council remained in Spain, despite its need for regular contact with the Indies. It included the Casa de Contratación, the body that oversaw trade in the New World. At the end of the 18th century, as Europe again faced massive disruption, the Council closed down.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SPAIN_ARMADA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The European empires of the 16th-18th centuries were built on sails. Ships designed for intercontinental travel were large and valuable – as was their cargo. But such ships could easily be converted to warships, especially with cannons now portable enough to fit on board, and powerful enough to cause significant damage to enemy ships.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SPAIN_ARMADA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Spanish Armada was commissioned by Philip II of Spain for an invasion of England in 1588. While some ships were armed merchantmen, the Armada's quintessential ship was the galleon (a name that essentially means “armed merchantman”). These ships could be between 500 and 2,000 tons, with double stacks of cannon. Despite these arms, the Armada was defeated by a combination of bad weather, English ships with more maneuverability, and a cunning use of fireboats (ships loaded with flammable material sent amidst the Spanish fleet).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SPAIN_NEW_WORLD_RICHES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Spanish expansion had three interrelated goals: gold, glory, and God. Regarding the first, a global world allowed Southeast Asian crops (e.g. sugarcane) to flourish in a new environment (e.g. Hispaniola) when farmed using enslaved African labor, resulting in European profit. The mines that enriched the Inca and Aztec empires could also be exploited for Spanish gain – or taken to trading stations in Manila and exchanged for Chinese goods, which proved even more profitable. This stitching together of all the known continents birthed the first truly global economy (though the Silk Road had been uniting Africa, Europe, and Asia for millennia before).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_EX_SPAIN_NEW_WORLD_RICHES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The brutality of this extraction should not be underplayed. While Isabella castigated Columbus for enslaving indigenous Americans, Spanish colonies relied heavily on the exploitation of local groups. Individual governors, landowners, and adventurers stood to gain incredible riches, but these did not immediately translate to gold and glory back in Europe. Indeed, much of the wealth from the New World fell to waste in failed and ill-run wars on the European mainland.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>