<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>

		<!-- Governments-->
		<!-- GOVERNMENT_FEUDAL_MONARCHY -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_FEUDAL_MONARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is the connection between family and land? For monarchies, a particular family establishes itself as the primary owner and ruler of a region, responsible for its welfare. The details of a monarchy differ over time – it may include kings or queens; the firstborn child might inherit rule, or the elder brother, or there may be a selection process among noble families. At times, the process for transferring power may be less clear – arguments regarding succession laws were a major reason for war. Even beyond the monarch, there were layers upon layers of authority: the baron of a small valley may pay allegiance to his count, who pays allegiance to his earl, who pays allegiance to the duke, who in turn reports to the king (and who might report to the emperor). Everyone has a place.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_FEUDAL_MONARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>This system has several variants. While lordship was tied to land in Europe, other systems held sway elsewhere. Where polygamy was the rule, royal households could produce scores of potential heirs, and one did not immediately inherit their parent’s rank, but the rank just below this. Royal children took positions elsewhere in the court or were given governorship over provinces. One child was selected by the current monarch as heir apparent. A position like this could be quite dangerous, as a brother, or uncle, or, in some cases, mother was always waiting to take over.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- GOVERNMENT_PLUTOCRACY -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_PLUTOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Blood may be thicker than water, but gold is thicker than all. In a plutocracy, the authority of royal bloodlines takes a backseat to the rule of those with property, money, and influence. For some historians, the liberation of merchants and artisans over the divine claims of kings and emperors is a natural progression. In trade-focused economies, the middle classes may feel limited by feudalism and seek to create their own form of property-based governance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_PLUTOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Some examples: in Renaissance Italy, the maritime republics grew as merchant houses developed independent militaries to protect their interests. With security and prosperity in the hands of merchant houses, what need is there for a king? The Chola dynasty of southern India did something similar, where merchants contracted naval mercenaries for protection (and conquest), extending their influence around the Indian Ocean rim. Plutocracies exist anywhere that money can buy political influence, thus one can argue that the Gilded Age United States, Meiji Japan, and Yeltsin-era Russia had strong elements of plutocracy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- GOVERNMENT_THEOCRACY -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_THEOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If political philosophy is a search for an ideal form of rule, what could be more ideal than the rule of the divine? In a theocracy, the divine’s intermediaries – i.e. priests – take direct control of the arms of the state. Theocratic systems often feature complicated and hierarchical networks of power within the church (or sangha, or ulema) where particular individuals or groups can rise based on their scholarship or other influence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_THEOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Sumeria and Egypt had elements of a theocracy, as the ruler was seen as a manifestation of a god on earth. In recent years, theocracies have taken radically different appearances, including early 20th century Tibet, the Holy See, and the Taliban. The latter shows the complexities of the term theocracy – while many agree that a system where the head priest makes the law is a theocracy, what about a situation where a king has ritual functions (as in Southeast Asian mandala states)? Or where a secular ruler alternates with a religious ruler (as in many indigenous American states)?</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- GOVERNMENT_REVOLUTIONARY_AUTHORITARIANISM -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_REVOLUTIONARY_AUTHORITARIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Authoritarian regimes born of revolution marked the 20th century, with such examples as the rise of the Soviet Union following the Russian Revolution and the dictatorship of Fidel Castro after the Cuban Revolution. These movements are typically born out of ideological and violent unrest arising from the lower classes of society, but result in a government where power is held by a single dictator or party. Revolutionary authoritarianism dramatically changes nearly all aspects of a state, demolishing institutions, rewriting the social contract, and often violently suppressing competing ideas. Their mastery of propaganda and other coercive techniques tends to keep the population’s unrest quelled, limiting the challenges to their power. Military consolidation in the hands of those who claim power further curbs dissent and leads to lasting authoritarian states that are widely resistant to counter forces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- GOVERNMENT_CONSTITUTIONAL_MONARCHY -->
		 <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_CONSTITUTIONAL_MONARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One of the earliest constitutional monarchies was recorded in the works of Herodotus, an Ancient Greek historian. He tells a story of the Cyreneans who, upon losing most of their army and dynasty in a succession war, asked the oracle at Delphi how to structure their government. The oracle’s recommended arbiter was a man named Demonax who split the powers of governance between the monarch and the populace. The king was allowed to retain all priestly duties and responsibilities, but the rest of the concerns of the state were delegated to the people. The Cyreneans enjoyed peace under this regime until the next monarch grew discontent with his limited role, and the country found itself in crisis yet again.</Text>
		 </Row>
		 <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_CONSTITUTIONAL_MONARCHY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In modern times, constitutional monarchies are found throughout the world and have been a frequent iteration of government during times of revolution, easing the transition from absolute monarchy to republic. Their common thread is the power and status of the monarch. While these rulers typically hold the titular role of head of state, their powers are often severely limited. In practice, it is the parliament or other representative body that governs while the monarch retains the symbolic role of embodying either the state or the people over which they nominally rule.</Text>
		 </Row>
		 <!-- GOVERNMENT_REVOLUTIONARY_REPUBLIC -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_REVOLUTIONARY_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the late 18th century, revolutionary movements like the American and French Revolutions rejected a single sovereign entity in favor of a free and self-governed people. They were heavily influenced by Enlightenment ideas such as those of Jean-Jacques Rousseau, who emphasized the will of the people and considered the Roman Republic to be the pinnacle of government.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_REVOLUTIONARY_REPUBLIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Following these early examples, revolutionary shifts toward republicanism occurred across the globe. Throughout Latin America, revolutionary leaders such as Simón Bolívar aimed to throw off the shackles of colonial rule and empower the people to govern themselves. In cases like the Haitian Revolution, a complete transformation of society from slavery to equality was a key motivation for revolutionary action. Türkiye abolished the rule of the Ottomans, ending nearly two millennia of imperial control over Anatolia and setting the stage for many of the independent nations we recognize today throughout the Middle East.</Text>
		</Row>		
	</EnglishText>
</Database>