<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_ABBASID">
			<Text>The second of the great Arab caliphates, the Abbasid Dynasty is the heart of wisdom. As the knowledge of the world and the heavens flows inwards to Abbasid libraries, Abbasid scholars are guided by the tenets of their faith, and their devotion to expanding the frontiers of science and commerce. Seek, read, discover - the world is yours.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_CHOLA">
			<Text>The greatest of the Tamil dynasties, the Chola lords rule the seas. Their touch extends outward, across networks of merchant houses, to the poets and philosophers of the Sanskrit world, and to artists and scholars. Each seek to capture the dreams of the fleeting world, for a time. Extend your grasp - though the seas are ever-changing, make your mark.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_HAWAII">
			<Text>The world’s greatest sailors, the Hawaiians venture forth when all others fail. With the blessing of their kahuna, they brave the blue expanse in search of new lands to sow with taro, new treasures to collect, and new legacies to forge. The conch is blowing, the wind is right - it is time for the oar to bite water.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_INCA">
			<Text>In the stony heights, the Inca create an empire where few others dare to tread. Guided by the condor’s flight and the puma’s track, they chart connections from peak to peak, building fortresses in the mountains. From these heights, decide whether to send down prosperity and wisdom - or a hail of sling stones.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_MAJAPAHIT">
			<Text>The Majapahit sail between a thousand islands, bringing with them their tales of heroes and gods. As the sun sets, weary sailors gather to hear the gamelan, and see their tales performed in shadow on the silken screen. Beauty is divine, claim the Majapahit poets, and divinity is power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_MING">
			<Text>Meaning “the bright,” “beautiful,” or “shining,” the Ming Dynasty radiates at the heart of the world. A vast society, with scholars and bureaucrats, farmers and kings, the Ming concentrates its focus inward, bringing all that is worth having to the center, intensifying its beauty and radiating it outward like the sun. Take up the mantle of the Ming, and shine.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_MONGOLIA">
			<Text>A name whispered in the nightmares of the settled lands, the Mongols stand poised to shatter the world – and remake it in a new image. With the thunder of bombards and roll of hooves, the hordes come. Lead them, and sow destruction among your enemies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_NORMAN">
			<Text>Restless conquerors, the Normans seek out new lands, and, with their mighty stone castles, they hold what they take. Norman society is made of courtly knights and chivalry, chevalers and keeps. It offers protection – under the sword. Stand and receive the fealty of your knights - the Norman yoke is upon the land.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_SONGHAI">
			<Text>Masters of the rivers and desert alike, the Songhai venture forth into the land. Stirred by the songs of the griot, and driven by their passion for profit and God alike, they seek out the riches of the world. Ride now with them, whether driven on by ambition or virtue, and lay claim to what you can.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_SPAIN">
			<Text>The white foam gathers as the galleons set forth, and Spain emerges on the world. As conquistadors set their gaze upon the horizon, a glint arises in their eyes - they sail to claim the world – for glory, for God… or for gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_ABBASID">
			<Text>Bahamut rumbles and sways the jacinth slab of Kuyutha. The Abbasids' weight will realign the balance of the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_CHOLA">
			<Text>The monsoon gathers, filling sails and banners, pushing the fierce Chola toward their destiny.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_HAWAII">
			<Text>The oceans whisper of a new power rising with the tide. The masters of waves will take a name forever remembered - Hawaii.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_INCA">
			<Text>The mountain valleys will sound with hammer and spade as the Inca enrich the land.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_MAJAPAHIT">
			<Text>The earth cries out for stewards. The Majapahit shall answer, and by wisdom, power, and grace, the fields will sing their name.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_MING">
			<Text>Guided by the stars, the Ming will seize the mandate of heaven, and lead the people into a prosperous future.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_MONGOLIA">
			<Text>The steppes brace for a coming storm - one of horses, valor, and endless ambition. The Mongols ride forth. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_NORMAN">
			<Text>The winds rise, and the Normans cross the channel of history to seize the world for themselves and hold nothing back.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_SONGHAI">
			<Text>From the heart of the Sahel, the Songhai will emerge upon the river's waves to take the world by storm. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_SPAIN">
			<Text>Undaunted by the ocean's expanse, Spain will follow the song of gold to unknown lands and make them its own.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_ABBASID">
			<Text>With the City of Peace Tradition, Buildings around the City Center receive additional Science adjacencies. Put Specialists on those tiles to really make number go up.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_CHOLA">
			<Text>The Chola excel at making Trade Agreements and Trade Routes, especially when you have Coastal Settlements. But they also have a really impressive navy for defense... or for offense.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_HAWAII">
			<Text>The Moananuiākea Unique Ability and Ho’okupu Tradition provide amazing Culture yields for expanding into Coast. With the Mana Civic, you also benefit from natural disasters like volcanic eruptions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_INCA">
			<Text>The Terrace Farm can go on any Rough Terrain that doesn't have a River or other Feature. However, with the Ayllu Civic, it benefits most from being adjacent to Mountains.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_MAJAPAHIT">
			<Text>The Majapahit benefit considerably from Specialists, which increase the adjacency of Buildings from the current Age by 50%. Use the Wayang Civic's boost to Overbuilding to construct those Buildings more quickly.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_MING">
			<Text>The penalty from the Ming's Unique Ability, Great Canon of Yongle, does not apply to Traditions slotted into your Government. Look for Civilization icon tags on Social Policies to identify your Traditions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_MONGOLIA">
			<Text>The Örtöö Unique Improvement restores the movement of Units that enter the tile. With faster movement from the Four Hounds Civic and the Noyan Unique Commander, you could cross a continent in a single turn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_NORMAN">
			<Text>The Motte and Bailey both count as Fortifications, automatically making them defensible Districts. It also means they can be purchased in Fort Towns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_SONGHAI">
			<Text>The Kanta Civic lets the Songhai generate small Treasure Convoys in Homelands Cities on Navigable Rivers. Unlock it early to get a head start on the Economic Legacy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_SPAIN">
			<Text>Spain can thrive in Distant Lands with the New World Riches Civic and Plaza Unique Quarter... or conquer them with the Conquista Tradition.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
