<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Modern Technologies-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_ACADEMICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Confucian academies, Buddhist monastic schools, Christian seminaries, and Muslim madrassas have all been around for many centuries. The school at Nalanda, in India, was a hub for Buddhist scholars in the first millennia CE, and the University of al-Qarawiyyin in Morocco remains the oldest university still in operation. The transition from a religious institution to a secular one took some time – such a move is only conceivable once one creates a divide between divine and mundane insights and can consider something like chemistry in a fundamentally different realm from things like theology or philosophy. Here, “academics” refers to something similar to Cornell University’s motto: “an institution where any person can find instruction in any study.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_STEAM_ENGINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The principles behind the steam engine have been understood for a long time. In 30 BCE, the engineer Vitruvius described a mechanism wherein a hollow bronze ball with two small outflow pipes could be filled with water, and once heated, would rotate rapidly. The mechanism was not very efficient but was used at times as a kind of "special effect" to open temple doors. Over a millennium later, Leonardo da Vinci proposed a steam-power-operated cannon. During the 17th and 18th centuries, steam engines became more of a reality, especially as improved metalworking allowed for the creation of parts that fit together seamlessly. In 1807, Robert Fulton made the first commercially successful steamboat, leading to steam power's rise in interest and investments, which eventually took the technology to the rails.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_MILITARY_SCIENCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is changed when the terms “theory” and “philosophy” are replaced with “science?” Science breaks an object into parts and encourages the study of those particular parts. While works such as Sun Tzu’s famous manuscript offer a wealth of good advice to generals, they explore strategy as art, not science. For the latter, Carl von Clausewitz sought to research the intangible aura of a military general's instincts. For Clausewitz (according to his “On War”, published posthumously in 1832), this research included topography, military art, history, organization, artillery, fortifications, legislation, administration, and maneuvers – discrete categories meant to be broken down and understood. These principles changed as war changed, meaning cavalry was no longer essential in a world of tanks, and fortifications offered scant protection in a world full of bombers. Overall, technology became king.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_MILITARY_SCIENCE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Whether this breakdown of art into science is ultimately a good thing remains in question, but when the science of strategy is universalized, it means all are playing the same game. However, a reliance on standard practices can lead to unpleasant surprises as line infantry-reliant generals discovered when facing hidden, rifle-toting snipers, or as American troops learned while traversing the chaotic terrain of the Mekong Delta.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_URBANIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The choice to live in a city versus the countryside is not new. Behind each societal myth is the idea to sacrifice the freedom of the hinterlands for the order and collective dream of urban life – from Hobbes’ social contract to Rousseau’s state of nature to the dreams presented by mandala states such as Angkor. However, for much of the world, the process of mass urbanization coincided with industrialization. As manufacturing moved from homes towards centralized, often privately-owned, mill-driven towns such as Manchester or New York, cities began to require new ways of life. Farmers were displaced by elite encroachment onto farms or the expansion of industrialized logics in rural areas, and many moved en masse to the cities, giving rise to tenement structures. Disciplines were no longer organized not by a list of tasks or the rising and setting of the sun but by the industrial clock.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_URBANIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With these new ways of working came new modes of leisure. Industry, moving out of the home, became male-dominated. Spaces such as the shopping arcade or the department store became sites where mass-produced goods could be consumed and displayed. In a stroke, artisanal culture declined and mass consumerism ascended.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_MASS_PRODUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The era of mass production was a corollary to urbanization. New machines – first water and steam, then electric mills and factories – enabled the production of new goods in greater quantities. As machines became more complicated, only a few could afford to own them; most simply operated the tools. The target consumers for mass-produced commodities were the very same workers who produced them. Turning a good into a commodity, and turning artisanal labor into factory labor, requires a different economic perspective – goods and labor became interchangeable and virtually synonymous with price. Needs, like the goods that satisfied them, could also be produced.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_MASS_PRODUCTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With the production of these goods came the rise of urban consumer culture, where fashion trends and perceived needs were not determined by individuals, but by the interests of manufacturing. People no longer acquire the latest coat, vehicle, tool (or mobile phone) to meet a need; rather they follow the dictates of profitable marketplaces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_ELECTRICITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>People were aware of electricity centuries before it was formally discovered. The ancient Egyptians recorded accounts of fish that delivered electric shocks, and the Greeks understood how to generate static electricity through the rubbing of amber. The 17th and 18th centuries saw major breakthroughs by scientists like Otto von Guericke, Stephen Gray, and Benjamin Franklin, who famously flew a kite with an attached key in a thunderstorm to prove that lightning was an electrical phenomenon. The advent of electricity as a major source of power changed the world, allowing for the invention of many commodities we now consider requirements of daily life: communication, lighting, and all manner of electronic technology.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_INDUSTRIALIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Industrialization hit the economies of Europe (and Japan) during the 19th century like a bomb. With the rise of mill manufacturing, goods could be produced in unprecedented quantities – indeed, the structure of colonialism laid some of the groundwork for this boom. For instance, Britain undercut local manufacturing in India to make the Liverpool market more lucrative (a strategy that had led to rebellion in the Thirteen Colonies some years before). While industrialization improved the finances of its backers, squalid working conditions in these industrial towns encouraged disease, poverty, and a reduction in worker life expectancy, as detailed by Friedrich Engels’ “Conditions of the Working Class in England” and Upton Sinclair’s “The Jungle.” </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_COMBUSTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Engines require a delicate balance of pressurized gasses and explosive forces. In an internal combustion engine, pressure is created by burning fuel – usually gasoline – to move a series of pistons, and the movement of these pistons can be harnessed towards a variety of larger systems. These engines, first developed in the late 18th and 19th centuries, were immediately applied to transportation. The smaller and lighter internal combustion engine (in comparison with the steam engine) could make a craft, such as a horseless carriage, versatile enough to move through most of the places an animal-drawn cart could go. By 1886, a viable automobile had been built, and cars were ubiquitous in many places, causing a massive redesign of cities and modes of life.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_RADIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Radio waves exist on one end of the electromagnetic spectrum, a line that includes gamma radiation and visible light among other things. Radio waves, however, are low energy; their wavelengths are long but ubiquitous. By altering the frequency of these waves, humans have learned to transmit data remotely, through the air, at the speed of light (perfect for Earth-bound communications, but more cumbersome in the endless expanse of space).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_RADIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Radio was first harnessed around the turn of the 20th century. Notably, Guglielmo Marconi invented a machine capable of transmitting and receiving bursts of Morse code in 1894. This “wireless” became a standard means of communication – faster than courier or pigeon, though less charming. In less than a decade, other inventors had devised ways to surpass these Morse bursts and transmit speech. By 1919, radio had become a popular medium for entertainment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_FLIGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When air flows over the curved surface of a wing, an aerodynamic force, called lift, is produced that begins to push the wing upwards. This concept has been understood for centuries, but successful winged flight was only achieved just over 100 years ago. Hot air balloons have been in operation since 1783, and dirigibles graced (or marred) the skies above Europe as early as the late 19th century. But in 1903, after extensively studying the history of flight, the Wright Brothers created the first true airplane – not a glider, but a machine that flew under its own power. The plane flew only 120 feet, soaring over the sand dunes at Kitty Hawk, North Carolina, and its landing was hardly graceful. But later innovations at the Wright home in Ohio produced more and more sophisticated aircraft. In less than two decades, this dream of flight took machine guns and bombs into the skies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_MOBILIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A war has been declared. A rallying cry is signaled. But how are a mass of peasants, students, and otherwise ordinary people converted into an army? The logistics of military mobilization have plagued wartime leaders since humans first picked up weapons. Peasants need to be converted into recruits and recruits shaped into soldiers. Soldiers then need weapons, food, and transportation to the battlefield. The term mobilization initially referred to the Prussian army, itself a paragon of wartime efficiency, and Friedrich II’s claim to fame was primarily his attention to supply lines, more so than artillery lines. By the dawn of World War I, most European powers had a system of conscription (the United Kingdom being an outlier). From Vietnam War-era American troops to today, powers have always had to issue this call. In the weeks leading up to the Great War, mobilization was almost seen as a holiday, but since that conflagration, such summons have come with increasingly uncertain sentiment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_ARMOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Armor” here does not refer to the personal plating that soldiers wore in antiquity or the medieval era, but to the armored vehicles of World War I and beyond. No man’s land – the spaces between enemy trenches during times of trench warfare – was the closest that hell has come to earth. Anything visible in this jagged, blasted terrain became a primary target. Crossing this terrain by infantry resulted in massive casualties, and bombers were in their infancy. A need developed for some means of conveyance, and existing automobiles were insufficient for this uneven terrain. This resulted in the development of armor, in other words: tanks. Treads could cross trenches in ways wheels could not, and steel plating offered some degree of protection for troops hiding within. From fortified slits in the armor, soldiers could fire as they approached enemy lines. The weight and power of these mobile bunkers even allowed soldiers to mount artillery and machine guns. This terrifying sight was a viable way of moving across the trenches.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_AERODYNAMICS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For a craft to move through the air, properties of drag and lift must be carefully managed. The shape of a wing generates lift, pulling its craft into the sky, but overall a plane must slip seamlessly through the air. Understanding these concepts was vital to air combat in World War II. The British Spitfire and its unique elliptical wing provided one model for flight, and the hyper-light Japanese Zero another. The Zero, in particular, was capable of generating lift at relatively low speeds, enabling rapid maneuvers and offering devastating dogfighting capability, especially early in the war. Later, faster craft abandoned the straight-wing design of these early fighters for swept wings that more efficiently spread drag across the craft.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_ROCKETRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>China has long been using rockets in warfare. In the 18th century, Indian troops in Mysore developed devastating rocket attacks to use against the English. But the idea of placing a person inside a rocket seemed like madness. Even so, inventor Robert Goddard, inspired by science fiction authors such as Jules Verne, proposed exactly that. With the goal of reaching the Moon, he refined a rocket design to include stages and a separate firing chamber, developing (flawed) plans for extreme-altitude rocket journeys. In the lead-up to World War II, rocketry became an obsession among many scientists and inventors, and the idea of rocket-powered cars and planes grew in popularity. During the war, the German V2 rocket, the first guided missile, rained down on London, demonstrating the devastating capacity of modern rocketry in warfare – a lesson scientists would later apply to the delivery of nuclear warheads. Yet scientists continued to explore peaceful applications for rocketry, and the technology became vital during the space race.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_NUCLEAR_FISSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If elements are the fundamental building blocks of matter, fission is the destruction of that foundation. Atomic nuclei divide when struck with enough energy, releasing more energetic particles. When compacted into a dense enough space, reactions can sustain themselves until the fuel is spent. As Harry S. Truman put it, this brings “the basic power of the universe” to Earth for a brief point in time. This nuclear reaction has peaceful applications, as in nuclear power. Unfortunately, it also has catastrophic wartime uses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_NUCLEAR_FISSION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Fission was first discovered by Otto Hahn and Lise Meitner in Berlin in 1938 when they noticed uranium slowly become barium (a drastic step down on the periodic table). By 1942, the then-wartime United States embarked on a massive project to develop a bomb based on a fission chain reaction. This bomb, first detonated at the Trinity site in New Mexico, was eventually dropped on Japan during the war – ushering forth an era of existential dread about the fate of the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- TECHNOLOGY_FUTURE_TECH -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_TECH_MO_FUTURE_TECH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ernst Bloch, in writing on hope, describes what he calls the “Not-Yet.” It is a thing which is felt, but not realized; imagined, but not seen. Strides in technology and political life rely upon this horizon of hope, and an ability to reach for and imagine the possibilities of what lies just beyond. This is the hope – and perhaps also fear – in imagining the unknown, but it is a hope that has allowed humanity to leave the confines of the Earth’s orbit, to unlock the secrets of our genetic code, and to seek to (perhaps so far unsuccessfully) create societies in which we can all flourish. Here is your future tech – now go study another.</Text>
		</Row> 
	</EnglishText>
</Database>