<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Modern Constructibles-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_BRANDENBURG_GATE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Berlin is at the heart of European history. The city has seen liberalism, militarism, democracy, communism, and fascism. Berliners have experienced devastation, occupation, empire, ruin, and the specter of domination that wears multiple masks. Each moment in history left its mark on the city. But through all these changes, the Brandenberg Gate has remained.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_BRANDENBURG_GATE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Built in 1791, the neoclassical gate marked the beginning of the road to Brandenberg, the Holy Roman Empire-era capital of the margraviate (state) of the same name. The gate marked a break in the wall surrounding the city but became more important as a symbol. It was partially dismantled by a victorious Napoleon, made into an imperial symbol during the Kaiser’s reign, employed as a fascist symbol during Nazi rule, and used to display Soviet flags during the partition of East and West Berlin. When the American president Ronald Reagan called upon Premier Gorbachev to “tear down this wall,” he prefaced it with “open this (Brandenburg) gate.” When the wall came down, the gate became a symbol of European freedom and hope. It remains a symbol for these, even today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_CHENGDE_MOUNTAIN_RESORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While the Forbidden City was the winter residence of the Qing Emperors, Chengde was the summer residence. The mountain resort fulfilled the same function – a large collection of administrative buildings built around royal dwellings. Chengde remains unique thanks to the special cultivation of its surrounding landscape. Each imperial temple was built in the style of one of China’s ethnic minorities, reinforcing a notion that China was not merely a state for the Han ethnicity (indeed, the Manchu Qing rulers would not have allowed this); rather it was a collection of peoples united under a single crown. Expert gardeners followed the landscape, ensuring their work did not overwrite the topography but enhanced it in ways informed by Chinese feng shui traditions, especially regarding the Danxia landscape (the red earth and steep cliffs) where Chengde is situated.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_DOI_SUTHEP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Doi Suthep, in Northern Thai, is the name of a peak just outside the city of Chiang Mai in northern Thailand. Atop this mountain is Wat Phra That Doi Suthep, a Theravada Buddhist temple and symbol of the North. Today, Doi Suthep lies in Thailand (formerly Siam), although the temple is not Siamese, having been built by the khon meuang people of the formerly independent state of Lanna who retain their own traditions and language, similar to Thai and Lao.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_DOI_SUTHEP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The temple’s story begins in 1368 with the discovery of a bone claimed to belong to the Buddha. The king of Lanna purchased the bone, enshrining one part of it in the city, and tying the other onto the back of a white elephant who was released into the jungle. The elephant climbed what is now Doi Suthep and suddenly died, indicating that was the site where the bone should be enshrined. In 1935, the popular monk Khruba Siwichai organized a massive movement to link Doi Suthep with Chiang Mai city, bringing tribal peoples and khon mueang together to build a winding road up the mountain. This organization, combined with brewing movements for Lanna independence, frightened the Siamese authorities enough to call Khruba Siwichai to Bangkok and have him surrender his monastic authority. The temple remains one of the most beautiful Buddhist sites in Southeast Asia, a cloud-drenched place of serenity high above the city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_DOGO_ONSEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What could be a better way to restore one’s health than at a hot spring? Nestled in the city of Matsuyama, Dōgo Onsen remains one of the oldest indoor hot springs in Japan. Constructed as a public bathhouse in 1894, the three-story onsen was used as a retreat by a variety of people, ranging from average citizens to royalty. The baths are separated by gender, while the Yūshinden is a separate bathhouse reserved for the imperial family located on the east side of the main building. Dōgo Onsen remains popular today, and the baths usually become crowded around early evening.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_DOGO_ONSEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Two legends surround Dōgo Onsen and the therapeutic powers of its waters. In one, an egret bathed his injured leg until it healed and he could fly away. In another, the Shinto god Sukunabikona was cured of an illness after bathing in the springs, and danced on a stone to prove his renewed strength. Dōgo Onsen still displays this stone today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_EIFFEL_TOWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Shortly after the Eiffel Tower’s construction, a collective of artists including Guy de Maupassant and Alexandre Dumas Jr. decried “the odious shadow of this odious column of bolted metal” which extended across the “city of light.” The Eiffel Tower is a symbol of the modern age, an image of Paris made of salons and cafés as well as industry and steelworks – it is a deep irony that it has come to symbolize the former in recent years. The resistance to the tower was so strong that it was slated to be demolished in 1909 and was only saved by the advent of radio technology (it is still used as an antenna).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_EIFFEL_TOWER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Eiffel Tower was built by Gustave Eiffel in 1889. Soaring over a thousand feet high, it was the tallest structure in the world (until 1930 with the construction of New York's Chrysler Building), and it was assembled from great iron beams that afford it the epithet “la dame de fer,” the lady of iron. French writer Roland Barthes noted that the tower is not a monument – rather, one sees the city as a monument from the tower's perch. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HERMITAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The largest art museum in the world, the Hermitage – which sits on the banks of the Neva River in St. Petersburg – was originally known as “Catherine’s collection,” a testament to the art tastes of a monarchy focused on the cultivation and collection of art and culture. In 1764, Catherine the Great, tsarina of Russia, purchased a collection of art from a Berlin art dealer and installed the pieces in a building near the Winter Palace. The collection was not intended for her but was originally assembled for the Prussian king Friedrich II, who refused it. Over time, the collection grew and grew as Catherine purchased more pieces from collectors’ estates. Eventually, the buildings employed a staff of nearly a thousand people to manage the collection and arrange the extravagant festivities that marked Romanov life.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HERMITAGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Under the tsars, the Hermitage was not the public museum it is today. This transformation happened after the Russian Revolution, a moment that ironically expanded the collection via the nationalization of many Russian nobles’ collections. It remains one of the most impressive art museums in the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MANHATTAN_PROJECT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>On July 16, 1945, a miniature sun appeared in the New Mexico desert. Forced together with common explosives, plutonium atoms showered each other with neutrons, splitting their nuclei and prompting a chain reaction that released incredible amounts of energy. In other words: a nuclear explosion. Oppenheimer famously captured the tone surrounding the test by quoting the Bhagavad Gita: “I am become death, destroyer of worlds.” However, the theoretical physicist also quoted John Donne when summarizing his feelings on the bomb: “So death doth touch the Resurrection.” Within a short period, these bombs were used against civilians in Hiroshima and Nagasaki, leading to the surrender of Imperial Japan in 1945.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MANHATTAN_PROJECT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Manhattan Project was a series of experiments on radioactive materials carried out by the United States, with support from the United Kingdom and Canada. It prompted similar projects elsewhere in the world, and the rapid escalation of nuclear weapons and the low-grade fear of worldwide annihilation defined much of the 20th century – before we realized our economy, not just warfare, was sowing the seeds of our destruction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MUZIBU_AZAALA_MPANGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The kings of Buganda were interred in a large domed house – the largest grass-thatched dome in the world. Along with kings, the site contained drums, spears, shields, and medals that bolstered the Bagandan kabakas’ (kings’) power. Descendants of the kabaka used the tombs to commune with their ancestors, although the site has now been inscribed as a World Heritage Site rendering this exclusive domain of kings accessible to tourists. The thatch roof also remains in need of maintenance (and defense against fire, as evidenced by a devastating blaze in 2010).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MUZIBU_AZAALA_MPANGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The tombs are an example of innovative Baganda architecture, built of wood and sheaves of grass. As a testament to its ongoing heritage, the site is decorated with photographs of past monarchs, indications that their influence has not waned.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_OXFORD_UNIVERSITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Academic institutions provide society with the space and time to reflect on the past and plan for the future. Societies that do not invest in education quickly repeat the errors of their predecessors. Although Oxford is not the oldest university in the world (the University of Bologna has been in continuous operation longer), it has been teaching students for over a thousand years, since its founding circa 1096. The university remains one of the most prestigious institutions for higher education today and has the largest academic press and library in the world (counting its digital assets). After its founding, Oxford grew thanks to conflicts between Europe and England, drawing in students who had been forbidden from studying abroad. In 1878, it started admitting women, and in recent years has hosted and educated over 70 Nobel laureates and 50 world leaders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PALACIO_DE_BELLAS_ARTES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Nations need museums. According to political scientist Benedict Anderson, modern nationhood was nearly inevitable, the result of a grand ethnic narrative (i.e. “the Swedish people”) or a culmination of ideological principles (i.e. “liberty” in the American context). Art plays a significant role in this process, both in how it records history and in how it gives form to the imagination of a nation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PALACIO_DE_BELLAS_ARTES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Palacio des Bellas Artes is Mexico’s cultural center. Built on the foundations of a church – which in turn was built on the foundations of an Aztec site – the current building was commissioned in 1904 to celebrate Mexican independence, but its Art Nouveau stylings were not completed until 1934. It is the nation’s most prestigious place for hosting theatrical performances and contains works celebrating Mexico’s marriage of indigenous and Spanish customs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_RED_FORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>India is built on layer upon layer of fallen empires. Delhi alone contains one of the Pillars of Ashoka, the ruins of the Delhi Sultanate, and various traces of the Mughal Empire. These remnants display how the Hindu and Buddhist (and British) faiths have existed side-by-side, even if they were not always at peace with each other. At the heart of the Mughal Empire were the Red Fort and its Peacock Throne, from which the emperors ruled over one of the wealthiest and most productive civilizations of its time. The British occupied the Fort during the Raj, and it remained a constant source of anxiety, as the massive complex and its wealth was an ideal fortification for any seeking to seize power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_RED_FORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Built by Shah Jahan, of Taj Mahal fame, the fortress was commissioned in 1639 after Jahan moved from Agra to Delhi. It is a city in itself, containing the Pearl Mosque and associated baths, a market, an audience hall, and a stepwell. The fort remains the most recognizable image of Delhi – perhaps second to the Taj Mahal in all of Mughal India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_STATUE_OF_LIBERTY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An iconic sight for many immigrants to the United States during the late 19th and early 20th centuries, the copper “Liberty Enlightening the World” was a gift from France to the United States in 1886. The statue's principal designers were the French sculptor Frédéric Auguste Bartholdi and the architect Gustave Eiffel – also known for the tower that bears his name. The monument was intended to represent both countries' commitments to liberty and is a testament to the warm Franco-American ties that have existed since the American Revolution.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_STATUE_OF_LIBERTY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Its original color was not a greenish hue – over the years, the statue's copper naturally oxidized, gaining its patina. Additionally, the commonly attributed quotation, “Give me your tired, your poor, your huddled masses yearning to breathe free,” was not originally a part of the statue. Those words, from a poem by Emma Lazarus, were installed on the pedestal in 1903 and came to redefine the statue in the eyes of waves of European migrants.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_TAJ_MAHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Often listed as one of the most beautiful buildings in the world, the Taj Mahal is actually a tomb. It was commissioned in 1631 by the Mughal Emperor Shah Jahan, the force behind Delhi’s Red Fort and other impressive building projects. The space contains gardens and a mosque, and houses the body of the emperor’s favorite wife, Mumtaz Mahal, as well as the shah himself (almost as an afterthought). Built in the distinctive Mughal style, it combines Persian and Hindu designs, reflecting those dual influences within Mughal society at large. Many recognize the structure thanks to its great onion dome composed of marble.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_TAJ_MAHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Today, the Taj Mahal is a symbol of India, perhaps surprising given the ambivalence that many Hindus feel about the Mughal period. Yet it remains a powerful icon of love, loss, and the hope that beauty can outlive us.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_WORLDS_FAIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Modern technological marvels stretch as far as the eye can see and a gigantic ferris wheel, the first of its kind, towers over a carnival of rides and games. Art and music flow through the White City as hundreds of thousands of visitors come to see and to wonder. As arguably the most famous of the World Fairs, the Columbian Exposition of 1893 in Chicago showcased to the world all the delights of human ingenuity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_WORLDS_FAIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Beginning in the mid-19th century, World Fairs served to present the culture and technology of not just their host countries but the world afar. Inventions like the telephone and flushable toilets were displayed for people to view for the first time. Inventors and artisans competed for prizes, while artists and scholars met to debate and create. France’s Eiffel Tower serves as a lasting reminder of the iconic stature of these events, the greatest of them exemplifying the heights of the Gilded Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_WORLDS_FAIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the 20th century, World Fairs diminished in importance, but remained an important reflection of their times. During the Great Depression, their exhibits provided a glimmer of hope for a recovered world, but after World War II, they turned toward more nationalist rivalries during the Cold War. Following the collapse of the Soviet Union and the turn toward a more global economy, World Fairs (or “Expos” as they are now called) have served to unite the world around common themes such as sustainability or peace. Though dominated by Europe and the United States throughout their first century, World Fairs are now often hosted in Asia as well, including the 2010 Shanghai Expo which boasts the record for attendees at any World Fair: over 73 million visitors came to visit China’s largest city to see the world on display.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Modern Buildings -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_AIRFIELD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Flight took numerous small hops before it fully leaped into our lives – and the battlefield. Scholars during antiquity in Europe and the Middle East experimented by strapping feathers to their arms and flapping (never seeming to notice that even birds need tails for control). Leonardo da Vinci designed gyrocopters and artificial wings that he hoped would enable people to take flight. With the advent of the airplane in the early 20th century, people were finally able to take to the skies. Still, these devices took up space. Wings create lift, but only by moving forward at high speed, which requires a long, flat runway. Thus, the Aerodrome: a vast open space with massive hangars and quaint buildings for humans (seemingly insignificant in comparison with their creations).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CANNERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Food does not spoil on its own. Instead, spoilage comes from the action of a host of bacteria, fungi, and other organisms that work on living matter once its defense mechanisms have failed (i.e. it is dead). In theory, food left with a complete absence of these organisms could stay fresh indefinitely – this is the principle behind canning. In the early 1800s, as Napoleon’s conquest swept across Europe, armies needed some way of keeping troops fed; earlier practices of pillaging the land were vulnerable to scorched-earth tactics (and alienated the population). Nicholas Appert developed a method of sealing food in an airtight container to keep microbes out, before cooking it to kill microbes already present. Given the right container, and the ability to produce the container cheaply, food could be conveniently preserved for mass transport and storage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CITY_PARK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What constitutes a city park? The gardens of Ashurbanipal were certainly in the middle of the city, but these were closed to commoners. One of the first identifiable Arab cities, Qaryat al-Faw, was termed the “city of gardens," but what exactly did that reference? Green spaces within temples and churchyards were places for contemplation and relaxation, but the idea of a city park for the population implies the public's needs are served by a centralized city plan. Further, it implies that relaxation in green space is one of these needs. Those needs arose out of industrialization, as the population moved into the city and into cramped tenements. The notion of a communal space for relaxation soon entered the consciousness of urban planners. Some parks were royal hunting grounds (e.g. Hyde Park) or military mustering grounds (e.g. Yoyogi Park), whereas others were inventions of urban planners themselves (e.g. Central Park). The most extreme of these design forms was Le Corbusier’s Garden City, a plan for cities that involved setting housing away from the city center and surrounding it with green spaces. The irony of the Garden City project was that its promised "relaxation" often led to increased alienation – turns out people don’t always appreciate living in isolated bubbles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DEFENSIVE_FORTIFICATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With the rise of gunpowder and modern military tactics, fortifications evolved beyond a reliance on walls. Their strength against small arms and siege weapons during the medieval era fell short in the face of cannon fire. Walls became lower and thicker and were typically built of dirt and stone. Fortified cities became obsolete. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DEFENSIVE_FORTIFICATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Instead, defensive strategies focused on smaller positions that were easier to protect and could operate as a base from which to mobilize units. These defenses relied heavily on forts, which used a combination of ditches and walls to outlast explosives and reduce blind spots. Bastion forts were particularly prominent; the European star design was notoriously difficult to overcome.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DEFENSIVE_FORTIFICATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Yet military strategy and technology marched on. By the end of World War I, as combat became increasingly mobile and ammunition grew more powerful, permanent fortifications became impractical. Defenses became more and more temporary, taking the form of concrete pillboxes, trenches, barbed wire, and other methods that were quick to deploy, cheap to produce, and easy to abandon when the fighting moved elsewhere.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DEPARTMENT_STORE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Everyday life changed as the world moved from the pre-industrial era to the industrial. Millions of people migrated from the countryside to the city, following a more rigidly demarcated life, where the home was separated from work (i.e. a farmer or artisan often lived at his place of work, whereas a factory worker does not live in the factory). Gender roles also calcified; while women had previously participated in various small-scale productions, industrial-age women were largely expected to remain in the domestic sphere. Time became regimented: a farmer’s chores were done when they were done, but factory work began and ended with a whistle. Add a growing amount of disposable income to this lifestyle and the modern-day notion of shopping for leisure takes shape. Brands, popular fashion, and advertising evolved during this period, but their presence was felt most heavily in the great department stores. From their origins in England, specialized districts and stores grew up around the world: the Bon Marché in Paris, Wanamaker’s in the USA, Mitsukoshi in Tokyo, etc. All of this led to a mass culture and popular consumption in which we are still enmeshed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_FACTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Factories denote a site of mass production, where a large amount of labor is performed by machines. These mainly refer to workplaces after the Industrial Revolution, where steam and electricity revolutionized production – though the factory has its roots in water-powered mills or even mills powered by humans or animals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_FACTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Factories boomed during the 1800s and onward, mass-producing manufactured goods and raw materials. A key component of the factory is that labor is replaceable (as opposed to the artisan). Like a machine part, a worker could be switched out when needed. Also like machine parts, factory workers were stored, often just offsite (i.e. in planned residential communities). The effects of this shift in labor were profound – new cities arose with new industrial sectors (and new polluted slums), while new theories developed to grapple with these alterations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_FACTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Factories placed large amounts of capital in a small number of hands. Machines were expensive, and workers did not own the machines they used. Theorists such as Friedrich Engels pointed out how this division created a large body of industrial workers with few assets other than their physical labor, drew people together in cities, and produced the conditions for the objectification of people's labor. Others, such as E.P. Thompson, pointed out how factory time became a standard measure: hours on and off work and homes entirely separate from the workplace arose from working on machine time. In this way, the factory system structured how we think of our world, our time, and our work.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GROCER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A grocer, or grocery store, is a shop that deals in bulk quantities of food. These were often centers of small towns, and the systems of credit extended by grocers were lifelines for farmers whose incomes trickled in throughout the year until the harvest boom. Grocers came about during a time when food preservation – drying or otherwise – was rapidly evolving, and they were a step up in complexity from a traditional market where one wanders from stall to stall purchasing needed provisions. For American audiences, a grocer might be more recognizable as a corner store, bodega, or ethnic market – the larger supermarkets and hypermarkets that stock nearly every household item are features of the 20th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_IRONWORKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Outside of easier availability, iron offered few benefits greater than bronze. However, iron smelted at a higher temperature turned into steel, which was far harder and stronger than any bronze – that was iron’s key advantage. The means to produce such high temperatures involved forcing air into the furnace, either by exploiting natural conditions or by using an advanced form of bellows. Early iron production, especially in India (wootz or Damascus steel), produced iron with a high enough steel content to be desired for luxury tools and weapons that were durable, corrosion-resistant, and able to hold an edge.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_IRONWORKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>However, this process didn't become standardized until the modern era. Iron and steelworks used blast furnaces powered by coke or charcoal to force air into the forge, producing pig iron (for casting), steel, and other forms of iron. Before the turn toward coke (which is less pure than charcoal), iron production decimated forests out of the sheer demand for fuel – the forests of England disappeared into blast furnaces during the Industrial Revolution. Modern ironworking remains an important industry in the USA, Russia, China, Japan, and India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LABORATORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A laboratory is a place of experimental learning. While the word is often interchangeable with “institute,” the latter implies more engagement with texts, whereas laboratories involve practical matters: beakers of bubbling chemicals, grinding gears, animal/human specimens, etc. Historical laboratories could include the studios of Leonardo da Vinci and the Divine Machine Division (shenjiying) of the Ming Dynasty, a place that experimented with new forms of firearms and weaponry. A laboratory could be a result of state-funded experimentation, a part of a university, or a private workshop run by an individual or company. These spaces typically hosted the work of a group of scientists and assistants, often with a particular goal. The DuPont labs, for instance, began in the early 1800s as a gunpowder supplier and moved on to materials science (including medicines) to further profits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LAUNCH_PAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For many, space exploration carries a dream of unity. Together against the vacuum of inhospitable space, many imagine the fading of humanity's national rivalries. With that in mind, it is a pity that rocketry developed as a weapon of war. Facing the increasingly devastating aerial bombing of German cities, the Third Reich created the V2 rocket, a supersonic artillery capable of raining destruction on London and other targets from launchpads located in safe zones. Such a rocket first crossed the line into space in 1944. Since then, the utopian appeal of exploration and its darker side have been in constant tension. The Soviet Union launched the first satellite (Sputnik, in 1957) and the first human (Yuri Gagarin, in 1961) to Russian pride and Western dread. The technology that could carry an explorer could also carry a nuclear warhead.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LAUNCH_PAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Since those early days, many countries have built space programs, both as a means to develop sophisticated weapons that may spell humanity’s decline and for the exploration that may prove its salvation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MILITARY_ACADEMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Elite soldiers often came from the upper classes of society. Roman patricians formed the core of the early legions (to be replaced by foreign mercenaries), Han officers were often appointed from bureaucratic posts, and medieval knights descended from the landed and educated gentry. But these were not professionally trained officers, educated in schools for positions of leadership. As military technology grew more sophisticated and complex (e.g. artillery), commanding troops required increasing technical know-how on top of personal charisma. Armies began to form specialized schools to train officers in the best use of new and complex equipment. The golden age of military academies came during the Napoleonic Wars, as the combination of artillery, cavalry, and formalized army regiments became critical components of war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MODERN_BRIDGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Bridges in the modern period moved beyond the age of wood and stone to embrace metal and concrete. Many techniques that had been reliable across the centuries were adapted for these new materials; for instance, arches are still common in many styles around the world. Cantilever bridges have also adapted to make use of truss systems, in which a series of beams and nodes are arranged into a firm structure of triangles. As the Industrial Revolution took off, additional methods were employed to maximize the use of wrought iron and eventually steel, which has a higher tensile strength and is capable of supporting larger structures. Today, cable-stayed and suspension bridges are some of the world’s longest and best-known overpasses, notable for their engineering feats and their attractive appearance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MUSEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Traditionally, a museum is understood as a collection of objects, generally for educational purposes and often for the public. However, the concept of a public museum relies on the concept of the "public," which was not a given in many historical times and places. Early museum-like collections were often associated with an individual or a religious institution – consider Buddhist or Christian reliquaries meant to showcase particular religious teachings or events. Alternatively, Catherine the Great’s art collection in Russia was the largest collection of its time. Reliquaries were for public education but only for a specific public, and private collections were secular but limited in scope and accessibility – but together they resemble the modern museum. As the notion that education served a public benefit grew up alongside an ideology of secularism (and, on a darker note, as European powers expanded their colonial reach), new museums opened: the Ashmolean Museum, the Louvre, and the British Museum among others. In later years, it became standard for countries to have a central, national museum: the Smithsonian, the museums of Ueno Park, and the like.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_OPERA_HOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Opera calls to mind a tradition that began in the Baroque era, in the 17th century, as Europe re-imagined the sung chorus of classical plays. The works of Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, Giacomo Puccini, and Richard Wagner are typical examples of this development, producing grand sung spectacles put on stage for an elite audience such as the Marriage of Figaro, La Bohème, or Der Ring des Nibelungen. But these are just a few of the operatic traditions around the world. Chinese jingju, the Beijing Opera tradition from the Qing Dynasty onward, and other various Chinese traditions would also fit the definition – as would the elite noh tradition of Japan (or its more populist kabuki theater). In mainland Southeast Asia, elaborate khon dances enacted Hindu myths. In the islands of Southeast Asia, wayang shadow-puppets depicted the same stories in all-night performances. Malian griot singing and a wide variety of Indian dance traditions also serve the same general function as “opera” in the West: to dazzle and engage audiences with story and song.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_PORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Coastal cities require ports. Historically, transporting goods by water was often easier and faster than by land, but necessitated a sheltered place within deep water where large ocean-going ships could safely dock. These ports were installations where heavy ships could be fastened to a pier and unloaded by a team of stevedores. In addition, ports could contain areas for repair and refueling (for coal and oil-fueled ships). In this way, ports are in sync with land-based infrastructures such as rail and other distribution networks – ideally, a successful port is not a stop but a continuation of the flow of goods and people.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_RADIO_STATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Radio allows for nearly instant communication across long distances and requires relatively little infrastructure – while lines had to be erected, earlier forms of communication, by comparison, involved sending physical messages/people across long distances. Heinrich Rudolf Hertz discovered the existence of radio waves – electromagnetic waves of extremely long wavelengths – in 1888, but several years of experimentation were needed before this technology came under broad use (largely thanks to Italian inventor Guglielmo Marconi). Early radio signals were used in radiotelegraphy, employing quick bursts to transmit the same information traditionally carried over a telegraph. Imagine the coming revolution, as society would soon receive news in an instant, send messages to secret agents and explorers, and instantly issue orders to troops.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_RADIO_STATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1906, Reginald Fessenden produced continuous broadcasts capable of transmitting speech. A scant three years later the first radio station was formed, and the format became popular through the course of the 20s and 30s. As Henri Lefebvre points out, radio allows mass media, capitalism, etc. to occupy our time and thoughts even when we are “doing nothing.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_RAIL_STATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As much as trains need the rails on which they run, they also require stations at which they stop. In its most basic form, a rail station consists of a simple platform allowing passengers and cargo to be on- and off-loaded. But as railroads became more common as a means of travel, additional services clustered around the tracks: ticket counters, waiting rooms, freight storage, staff offices, shops, and more.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_RAIL_STATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Rail stations rapidly grew in size and grandeur as the 19th century progressed. Exaggerated porticos and arches became consistent elements of the façade, while large clocks were integrated, often in the form of clock towers, to help passengers catch their trains in an era before watches and smartphones. Arched roofs of iron and glass protected tracks and platforms from the weather, and vaulted concourses echoed with travelers hurrying to their next destinations. The most elaborate stations of this period remain some of the world’s most iconic buildings, including Grand Central Station (New York City), Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus (Mumbai), St. Pancras (London), and Gare du Nord (Paris).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SCHOOLHOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What assumptions underlie public education? The idea that all children should be educated rests on the concept of citizenry – that all people should reach their potential and contribute to society as full members of the public. Feudal lords had little need to educate their serfs. When education existed in previous ages, it was often within religious schools – Theravada Buddhist temples especially had a mission to promote universal literacy (amongst boys) and advance general knowledge. Confucian academies promoted education for those who entered the administrative class. However, universal public education along secular lines came about in the 15th century, together with the idea of the public. For idealists, the notion of a public school promotes universal opportunity and produces a better-informed population. For cynics, it promotes conformity and nationalistic loyalty to the state.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_STOCK_EXCHANGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Stock exchanges were founded upon the principles of investment and money lending. These establishments became important during the early era of colonialism, as voyages posed a significant risk to ship owners. Sending a ship overseas could be incredibly lucrative, but the vessel could simply vanish, taking that investment to the bottom of the ocean. A group of lenders offered to defray some of these costs in exchange for a cut of the ship’s profits – and the modern stock was born. The first stock exchange was founded in London in 1773, and the New York Stock Exchange followed a few years later. In theory, these exchanges democratized wealth, allowing those without capital to invest in an entire business to venture a piece of the profits. In practice, exchanges often led to the growth of larger and larger business ventures, widening wealth gaps.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TENEMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word “tenement” simply means “residence,” but it has come to denote tall, multi-family buildings. The quintessential structures are the high-density New York housing blocks of the late 19th century. Tenements in cities such as New York, Edinburgh, and Glasgow came hand-in-hand with industrialization, as workers flocking to cities sought cheap housing near factories or other places of employment. These buildings usually gained a reputation as unhealthy and unsafe – large houses or warehouses were divided into a series of often windowless rooms to house the maximum number of people possible, and presented a constant risk of crime, collapse, or disease.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TENEMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Elsewhere, dense settlements such as the Kowloon Walled City in Hong Kong were built along the same model, packing the most people into the minimum space provided, and they attracted many of the same concerns. Reformations in housing law and design largely removed the worst tenements but also introduced new concerns over housing availability in large cities.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--Civ Unique Buildings-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CATEDRAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In 1519 AD, Hernán Cortés led the first Spanish invasion of the Aztec Empire. With him traveled Gerónimo de Aguilar, a Catholic priest. Conversion and conquest came together, blending indigenous ways with Christian imports (a syncretism that is reflected in the centuries before the Spanish – the Aztecs, when they began their conquest, brought their own deity, Huitzilopochtli, and elevated him in local pantheons).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CATEDRAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Catholicism remained important in Mexican history, and, given its history, it is little surprise that new forms of devotion and worship occasionally emerge. The Catedral Metropolitana in Mexico City was built atop the Aztec ceremonial center near the temple of Huēyi Teōcalli, directly symbolizing the substitution of the Christian god for the Aztec ones. The Basilica of Guadalupe is most crucial to Mexican Catholicism; it was built on a site where the Virgin Mary appeared to an Aztec convert and demanded a cathedral. This apparition is the Virgin of Guadalupe – an aspect of the Virgin Mary that embodies both the indigenous and European heritage of Mexico and is the patron saint of Mexico.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_EXAMINATION_HALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A core pillar of Confucian thought is that individuals should be appointed by merit, not by lineage or other arbitrary considerations. To this end, China, for most of its history, relied upon the imperial examination system, a series of tests focusing on writing, reading the classics, and language. The tests required that all high-ranking officials were literate in a common culture. This system was one reason for China’s stability over the years. Foreigners could become Chinese through a deep knowledge and investment in Chinese culture, ensuring that even with invasion, civil war, or other disruption, the structure of society could maintain a common thread.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_EXAMINATION_HALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the Qing era, this system went through multiple changes. Qing, a Manchu and not Han dynasty, sought to promote Manchu language and ethnicity in the upper ranks, and established ethnic quotas for graduates. As the 19th century marched on, the content of these examinations fell under question, as reformers sought to include Western sciences and mathematics within the curriculum.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_EXAMINATION_HALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The system was abolished in 1905, to be replaced by public school degrees.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_FORMAL_GARDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Enlightenment was defined by the human desire to impose a certain kind of rationality and will upon nature. If all natural processes are rational, then natural beauty could be bent to reason’s will. This was exemplified in the French formal garden (contrasting the Romantic landscape garden, which permits nature to run wild in accordance with Romantic ideals). Near the chateaus of the French elite, hedges are coaxed into strict geometric shapes and dotted with faux Roman sculptures. Within these wide lanes, nobility can stroll. Feats of hydrology and horticulture create an entirely artificial landscape out of nature. The most famous example was the gardens at Versailles, 800 hectares in size, laid out along the axes of the compass.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_FORMAL_GARDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Though the gardens of Versailles and the grand chateaus fell out of favor during the Revolution, Napoleon III revived the concept, albeit making gardens available to the public, rather than the cloistered, wigged nobility. Paintings during France’s Belle Époque often depict the bourgeoisie strolling as the aristocracy may have strolled before.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GINKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word “ginko” simply means “bank,” and the Japanese banking sector became the powerhouse it is today during the Meiji restoration. Japan's oldest bank, the Dai-Ichi National Bank, was founded in 1873, and more were soon to come. Japanese banking, in tandem with the zaibastu, was instrumental in funding the wars of expansion under Meiji and subsequent regimes. Banking became a central feature of Japanese statecraft, despite postwar restructuring and internationalization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_JUKOGYO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Heavy industries – jukogyo in Japanese – create precisely what the name implies: large-scale machinery, tools, buildings, and equipment. Heavy industries were favored by Meiji and later Japanese regimes, and companies such as Mitsubishi and Fuji began as such. Mitsubishi, founded in the 1850s at the behest of the shogunate, is a case in point: Dutch engineers built the first major foundry in Japan, which expanded to include shipbuilding and steel working. These proved to be important imperial assets when Japan went to war and required weapons and vehicles, so Mitsubishi factories were a prime target for the atomic bomb attack on Nagasaki.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MONEY_SHOP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The rise of the financial system is an important part of the story of the modern era. From the Japanese zaibatsu to the European joint-stock companies, new institutions allowed individuals to capitalize on the transformations shaping the world. In China, these were the money shops, the qianzhuang. These places operated many of the financial services we expect from banks today but held a special position, placed close to foreign firms working in China at the time, and acting as intermediaries for foreign business enterprises. While they had roots in international (and colonial) finance, qianzhuang also maintained deep networks within the local business community, seeking ways to minimize risk (lending money to someone just down the street, or within one’s family network, was far less risky than lending to a complete stranger).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MONEY_SHOP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The system always scraped the edges of legality and safety. Qianzhuang would often lend out far more than the money shop maintained while holding shareholders entirely liable for debt. For this reason, and despite their role in stitching local communities together, qianzhuang often crashed, bringing down scores of investors with them. Money shops remained in operation for a few years after the Chinese Revolution, finally disappearing around 1952.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_PORTAL_DE_MERCADERES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mexico City’s Zócalo contains all the vital organs of the city: its administration, its religion…and its merchants. The Portal de Mercaderes is a line of shops that have existed at the site in some form since 1521. For most of its existence, the Portal was a covered line of shopfronts that housed other vendors, selling everything from expensive silks to candies, and creating a kind of walking street protected from the rain. This combination of commerce and pleasure was vital in making the Zócalo a civic center as well as a living, breathing space – as the heart of any city should be.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_RAILYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Early railroads in America were built to serve the needs of both industry and transportation. In the first half of the 19th century, the movement of cargo and people relied heavily on rivers, canals, and horse-drawn vehicles. The first trains were pulled by horses, but the arrival of the steam locomotive in 1829 changed everything. Railroads were safer and less susceptible to seasonal weather conditions than naval freight transport; they were also faster, cheaper, and more comfortable for everyday travelers. From 1855 to 1871, the U.S. government sponsored land grants for companies to develop railways, and trains soon ran from the Atlantic to the Pacific.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_RAILYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>On top of facilitating industrial growth across the nation, railroads sparked a massive industry of their own. The needs of track construction, engineering, and maintenance created thousands of jobs that equipped many with mechanical and technological training. As railroads pushed farther west, stations attracted populations to support their infrastructure, forming towns and cities that expedited urbanization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SALON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is the public sphere? Today it might be defined as a loose conglomeration of media outlets, chance conversations, or some aggregate of private discourse. However, nothing embodies the idea of “the public” like the French salon from before, during, and after the Revolution. In the salon, groups of people would come together to discuss literature, music, and art, but most importantly political philosophy and the events of the day. This was where ideas that were vital to the Revolution were discussed, challenged, and elaborated on – and, at times, plans were put into action. Organizations such as the Jacobin Club – the fire behind much of the Revolution – got their start in salons, before they took to the scaffold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SALON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Salons were especially important as places where women could advocate publicly for social transformations, and figures like Olympe de Gouges, author of the “Declaration of the Rights of Women,” used the French salons as places of debate and discussion for issues ranging from universal suffrage and the abolition of slavery to the works of writers such as Jean-Jacques Rousseau. As much as they were starting points for revolutions, salons were also targeted by the Revolution – due to de Gouges' association with a more moderate faction, she lost her head to the guillotine.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_STEEL_MILL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Steel, an alloy of iron and carbon, was discovered thousands of years ago. Though highly valued, it was expensive to produce until the development of the Bessemer process in 1856. Only nine years later, in 1865, America built its first steel mill in Troy, New York, kicking off a massive boom in steel production that soon surpassed the rest of the world. The rapid growth of the nation’s infrastructure heightened the demand for steel, which was used in the construction of buildings, railways, bridges, vehicles, and machinery. American steel was exported all over the world, and its dominance remained untouched by World War II, allowing the industry's global importance to peak. In the years that followed, other countries began to compete in production, but not before the dominance of U.S. steel had ushered the nation into modernity.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--Civ Unique Improvements-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_BANG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A bang, as in “Bang Kok," is a water-based community in Central Thailand. It differs from a “baan,” which is a compound of structures built outside a canal system. In a landscape such as Thailand’s, where land transforms into water during certain times of year, water-based communities allowed for the easy transport of goods and relatively quicker forms of travel, especially when roads were subject to washing out or flooding, and buffalo could only carry so much material. Bang often have a central Buddhist temple, a central canal, basic irrigation system, and a community center surrounded by rice fields or other crops. Historically, the canal (khlong) was the center of life; Buddhist monks made their alms rounds on them, markets were held atop them, and villagers largely came and went through them via water. Today, many bang have been overtaken by concrete and automobiles, but behind concrete buildings the quieter, slower life of the bang carries on.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_KABAKAS_LAKE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Buganda was an empire of lakes. From their great raids against rival groups across ‘Nnalubaale (Lake Victoria) to their reliance on lake resources, the Baganda (the name of Buganda’s people) knew the lakes held their salvation. With this in mind, the kabaka (king) of Buganda, Mwanga II, constructed a lake (partially with his own hands to shame nobles who refused the hard labor) to be a strategic spot in the face of the British threat, which intensified in the late 1800s. Today, only one Kabaka’s lake remains in the city of Kampala, which is the largest man-made lake in the country – but there is no reason why local nobility might not build their own.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_OBSHCHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The model of the individual farmer predominated in Western Europe. But in Russia, the obshchina was a type of long-established collective farm (not to be confused with later Communist collective farms). At obshchiny, individuals held and farmed their own plots. However, plots could not be transferred without the approval of the collective, and if the situation became unbalanced, the collective could re-apportion the land as needed. In this way, peasants in the obschchina were sheltered from the hazards of everyday catastrophe: a death in the community, the establishment of a new household, etc. These communities were not entirely self-governing until the abolishment of serfdom; lords and wealthy landowners still existed, but they retained some degree of (collective) autonomy away from the forces of state and capital. Slavophiles – Russians who saw value in Russia’s Slavic roots rather than in the emulation of European norms – saw something noble in the obschchina. In later years, they were upheld as a proto-Communist formation by those who sought to transform the Russian economy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_STEPWELL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The vav, or stepwell, has been an irrigation tool of India and Pakistan for centuries. The concept is simple: dig a well down to a water table, but instead of lowering a bucket into the dark hole, provide steps for people to climb and haul water. Stepwells are especially important in places with highly variable water tables, like monsoon India, and were built long before the Mughal Empire. Nonetheless, they were an important feature of everyday life for many, providing a source of water and a place for villagers to socialize. Today, many stepwells have significantly reduced water levels, as a mixture of climate change and intensifying human demands have depleted water tables across the region.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--City-State Improvements-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ABATTOIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the 19th century, the Industrial Revolution spurred population growth in cities and significantly increased demand for food, especially meat. At the time, meat production took place in open areas, with meat markets sometimes located in the city centers, as was the case in London. The risk of disease and the moral concerns of the practice, graphic and public as it was, led to reforms that resulted in the abattoir. This enclosed building was typically placed on the outside of cities and governed by several regulations for hygiene and sanitation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ABATTOIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Throughout the late 19th and 20th centuries, veterinarians and physicians attempted to develop more humane methods of acquiring and producing meat for human consumption. Anaesthetics and design changes were implemented to reduce the awareness and pain of the animals. Today, most countries have laws governing the treatment of animals in abattoirs, and many cultures and religions have additional rules regarding the practice. For both animals and humans, meat production is emotionally costly, and debate continues over how to feed the world’s populations both effectively and morally.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CIRCUS_FAIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The modern circus originated in England in the 18th century. Early forms were stationary, located in a single building, but over time, the circus became more itinerant, taking place under the eponymous big top tent. Horse tricks, acrobats, jugglers, and clowns were common sights at early circuses. Later, the menagerie and other exotic acts like fire-eaters became commonplace. The entertainment of the circus spread from England to the colonies, through Europe, and across the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CIRCUS_FAIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the 19th century, the carnival developed independently, but became a common accompaniment to the circus. Originating at the Chicago World’s Fair of 1893, a “midway” of rides and games, often including a Ferris Wheel, would serve to entertain visitors alongside the traditional acts of the circus. These itinerant groups were prevalent throughout North America and England through the 20th century. Though both the circus and the traveling carnival have become less common forms of entertainment, they can still be found across England and the United States at county and state fairs.</Text>
		</Row>			
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ENTREPOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An entrepot is a space in which goods are stored en route to their final destination. Deriving from the Latin “inter” (between) and “positum” (position), entrepots were historically located in port cities or major crossroads. As long-distance trade developed in the modern era, merchants needed places to stop along the way to rest and recharge for the journey ahead or to sell their merchandise to other vendors to relieve the burden of traveling the entire arduous route. Entrepots also benefited their local regions by acting as storehouses for a wide variety of goods, reducing the risk of fluctuation in both supply and price.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_INSTITUTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Institutes emerged from medieval observatories and mathematical academies as a means to support scholars pursuing studies at their highest levels. From the start, institutes encouraged the study of specialized knowledge, providing funding and resources, such as libraries and research facilities, to their members. Originally, these establishments were founded by governments and monarchies to capitalize on the Scientific Revolution; some were attached to universities while others operated autonomously. But independent scholars, such as Tycho Brahe and Thomas Edison, also formed institutes, drawing great minds together to solve some of the world’s most complex scientific puzzles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_OPEN_AIR_MUSEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word “museum” often conjures images of halls filled with treasures from the past. But museums are not always indoors; sometimes outdoor exhibits are the best way to invite the public to explore history. Open-air museums first emerged in Scandinavia as an attempt to preserve old ways of life that were quickly disappearing in the face of industrial modernity. The benchmark for these museums was Sweden’s Skansen. Historic buildings from around the country were dismantled, packed up, and shipped to Stockholm, where they were reassembled in a park, accompanied by interactive exhibits demonstrating traditional activities like crafts and folk dancing. The Skansen model spread widely to other nations looking to capture their past before it vanished. Today the open-air museum model has expanded to include historic buildings and activities as well as sculpture gardens and sprawling sites, archaeological or otherwise.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_SHORE_BATTERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A shore battery is a collection of artillery on the coast tasked with defending against naval attacks. They rose to prominence during the Age of Discovery when coastal fortresses were used as a deterrent to seafaring threats. Advancements in artillery technology increased the size and range of these cannons, and the batteries often used naval guns repurposed for terrestrial use. Shore batteries were so impactful that for several centuries, territorial waters were defined by the range of coastal artillery – the three-mile limit was so called because according to international law, maximum artillery range was roughly three nautical miles. After World War II, the rise of air and guided missiles rendered shore batteries largely obsolete, though they have found situational use in ensuing decades.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Unique Railroads -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_ROUTE_STAATSEISENBAHN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Transportation in the early 19th century required muscle. Moving quantities of goods over land was usually performed by animals pulling carts. This was not an ideal form of transportation, but more efficient modes of transport, such as railcars, required massive investment in infrastructure and material. In that area, Prussia and other parts of Germany excelled. The Prussian state railways, the Staatseisenbahnen, were a collection of private rail lines that crisscrossed the state, revolutionizing logistics and economic development to catapult Prussia to the fore of the industrialized world. These private concerns were nationalized in 1880 to increase standardization, leading to the development of massive, beautiful stations and a more modernized economy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Unique Quarters -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_AVENUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Today, Paris is admired for its architectural heritage – the buildings all of a type, the grand avenues linking monument to monument (exemplified by the Champs-Élysées). However, these developments were historically controversial, built (by some accounts) by a self-aggrandizing architect at the behest of (by all accounts) a megalomaniac dictator obsessed with spectacle. These men were Georges-Eugène Haussmann and Napoleon III, both lovers of spectacle, and both profoundly influential in 19th century France, for better or for worse.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_AVENUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Facing the chaotic slums of Paris, Napoleon III proposed that the city be entirely renovated, removing the vestiges of its medieval past and replacing it with a new, modern city. Haussmann heard the call – and saw the wealth Napoleon III was willing to spend. He blasted the broad avenues of Paris through its existing slums, tearing down rambling old buildings to be replaced by modern blocks (those buildings that are so iconic of Paris today). Much of the old charm of Paris was gone, but so was its disease-ridden alleys and chaotic layout. What remained was a web of avenues stretching across – and defining – the city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_AVENUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>These avenues became centers of Belle Époque life. In the arcades, winding shopping malls between streets – many of which were demolished by Haussmann – lived the flaneur. These urban wanderers and seekers of novelty were incredibly influential to writers such as Charles Baudelaire, Marcel Proust, and their historian, the theorist Walter Benjamin. In turn, those thinkers continue to inspire visitors and residents of the City of Light.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_INDUSTRIAL_PARK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The growth of industry in early America was initially wrapped up in the development of urban centers. Yet as production efforts grew, bringing large businesses together into one dedicated space became more lucrative. These industrial parks typically attracted heavy industries, such as steel mills and machine production, which required more space, materials, and infrastructure than lighter trades. By allocating these facilities to their own districts, cities ensured that these critical industries, which supplied both products and jobs, had room to thrive while reducing their social and environmental impact on the surrounding population.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_INDUSTRIAL_PARK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Heavy industries relied on consistent and extensive deliveries of resources, as well as the ability to distribute their output. As a result, proximity to transportation was paramount to the success of these parks. Ports provided access to shipping, while the advent of the railway greatly expanded opportunities to foster industry across the United States.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_HUIGUAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One challenge for the center of any empire is handling the multiplicity and diversity of its people. Imperial China contained a vast array of people from different provinces who spoke different languages, all with their own networks and links across the empire. These informal networks were formalized within the institutions of the huiguan, the guild hall. When established in distant cities, these places were simultaneously mercantile assemblages, social gathering spots, lending banks, legal resources, and places for the collective worship of particular deities or ancestors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_HUIGUAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Beijing in the Qing era held hundreds of huiguan, tied to various provinces across the empire: prominent examples include the Sichuan Huiguan, the Wuhu Huiguan, and the Hunan and Hubei Huiguan. Today, the management of migrant communities in urban China has transitioned to the state via the hukou system (registration for permanent residence) and is attached to a legal set of rights over where one can access services.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_ZAIBATSU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The corporate world, first anticipated by the joint-stock companies of the colonial age, reached its modern form at the dawn of the 20th century. The Japanese zaibatsu epitomized this evolution: a business conglomerate integrated into nearly all aspects of finance, with a family on top, and deeply involved in politics. Indeed, the push for Japanese wartime expansion in the name of securing resources came as much from private industry (i.e. zaibatsu) as from the imperial state. After World War II, the Allies dissolved the system, but existing conglomerates continue to push this line, as they do elsewhere (American corporations and especially Korean chaebol are similarly economically and politically powerful entities).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_ZAIBATSU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Big Four zaibatsu were Sumimoto, Mitsui, Mitsubishi, and Yasuda – the first two had their origins in Edo-era business practices, and the latter in the Meiji Restoration.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_ZOCALO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Aztec ceremonial centers were built around a central plaza, a city plan that Spanish conquerors emulated in the Zócalo of Mexico City, here generalized to refer to the central plaza of all Mexican cities. It remains the place where important civic functions happen. The buildings surrounding the Zócalo are testaments to their importance in Mexican society: the cathedral, the city hall, and the main halls of administration. This space once contained the principal temple of the Aztec city of Tenochtitlan, and the Zócalo’s orientation toward the cardinal directions is a key outgrowth of its Aztec plan. This is the continuity of empire – the re-creation of a new world resting on the bones of the old.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>