<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>

		<!-- Modern Civilizations -->
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_AMERICA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Thirteen Colonies of early America were not inevitable – they were products of their time and place. Whether or not the eastern coast of North America would become a British domain remained uncertain when the English landed in 1607. Britain initially faced competition with other European powers. The Spanish had a mission near Jamestown, but that was wiped out by Powhatans just a couple of years before the English arrived. The French held Quebec. And Caribbean colonialism had been in full swing for a century. Indigenous powers also existed. The Haudenosaunee had a sophisticated confederacy in the upstate New York region, built and expanded in reaction to colonial contact. Likewise, the Powhatans maintained a loose confederacy in the central Virginia area. These indigenous groups remained formidable foes to the expansionist European presence. They had a keen command of guerrilla tactics, overwhelming numbers, knowledge of the terrain, and very quickly learned to use guns and horses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>And yet, within a century, North America's European-centric future seemed inevitable. The early English presence in the U.S. was heavily influenced by Protestantism and Lockean notions of property, which unified religion and production. One could summarize early United States philosophy as follows: This world is God’s world. Thus, by working the land, we fill our role as agents of God and use what God has chosen for us to use. The original inhabitants of the land are people who do not work the land. They do not make use of what God provides, and so it is natural that they disappear to make way for us.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As time wore on, this notion was stripped of religious meaning, formed the backbone of Manifest Destiny, and provided the rationale for stories that discredited indigenous innovations before European arrival. The expansion of European diseases also contributed to this sense of Manifest Destiny.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The colonies were not homogenous. The Southern colonies were plantation estates much like other English colonies in the Caribbean, built to mass-produce cash crops via the enslavement of Africans kidnapped by slave traders. In contrast, New England was the home of Puritans who conceived of an omnipresent God who commanded diligent labor and austerity from his followers. Pennsylvania was a land grant to a colonial-era venture capitalist. Maryland would be a home for Catholics. Georgia was a penal colony, and so on. Eventually, Virginian plantation elites and New England intelligentsia came together over conflicts about the colonies’ role in a larger British empire. Could the British crown limit the colonies' westward expansion and negotiate with the indigenous powers on behalf of Americans? Could the colonies freely trade with other European powers in the region – especially Britain’s rivals? Were the colonies merely sources of raw materials to fuel English industry, or were they a part of the British nation, complete with voting rights? Wealthy colonists saw themselves as the latter, but the crown saw them as the former. Conflict was inevitable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>An independent United States posed a threat to England, and the British Empire sought to curb their colonies’ expansionist dreams. In this, they had allies: namely, the Haudenosaunee and other powerful indigenous groups. The British also employed this strategy of leveraging indigenous people against rowdy colonies in places like Burma, India, and Arabia. In addition, Britain offered freedom to any enslaved person willing to fight against the Americans. They would lose in this gamble in the New World, but Britain's allies would come out worst of all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The War of Independence established the first real postcolonial state in the world – though it eventually became a colonizing power of its own. This new nation was several things at once. It was a creole state where New World-born Europeans ruled. It was an Enlightenment state, where notions of natural rights inherent to any man held sway over historical privilege. It was an anti-theocratic state. Despite the Puritan nature of New England, and the Catholic nature of Maryland, the United States sought to distance itself from the wars of religion looming over Europe. Anyone could practice anything they desired, so long as they did not infringe upon the rights of others.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>The States began by sorting out some fundamental questions – should they be separate countries, with their own currencies? Should they have a strong central government or a weak one? The Articles of Confederation suggested the latter. Afterward, the Constitution suggested the former. The Constitution won out.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Still, another conflict loomed. The Southern states had been established like Caribbean plantations – factories for producing cotton and tobacco (and indigo) off the backs of slave labor, for the benefit of wealthy owners. The Northern states had their ethos; in the 1800s, this focused on the development of heavy industries powered by European immigration. As the rest of the world tilted towards emancipation and industry gained the upper hand, the South lost ground. It sought to secure its position by encouraging new Western states to replicate its economic model, which relied on enslaved people. The North opposed this, and this conflict eventually erupted into the Civil War. When the war ended, the South had been transformed and slavery had ended.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>The later 19th century was a time of robber barons, railroad tycoons, and wars against the Plains Indians as America moved ever westward. Gold discoveries in California, the purchase of the central part of the U.S.A., and the cession of the Spanish territories further increased the size of the country. By the end of the century, the U.S.A. had annexed Hawaii and the Philippines, defeated the Plains Indians in the center of the country, reneged on multiple treaties with indigenous populations, and settled into the borders that, more or less, exist today. The early 20th century was a time of unchecked industry, mass migration to the country, shocking poverty, and equally shocking wealth. The country had moved from tricorn hats to hoop skirts to “The Jungle” to “The Great Gatsby” in a century and a half.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AMERICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>The United States' inherent ideals transformed the world. The country was an inspiration for the French Revolution and the Vietnamese Revolution. Furthermore, it was a proving ground for democratic nations and republics (though it was far from the first). It can be seen as a place that privileges economic freedom above all, conflicting with states that focused on social or labor freedom even as it conflicted with authoritarian states and absolute monarchies. This was a country where capital, not citizenry nor monarchy, reigned supreme. This ideology took a dark turn during the Cold War, and earlier in Latin America, the Philippines, and Hawaii when the interests of capital became antithetical to democratic interests (indeed, corporate ownership of media is why the USA lags behind many countries when it comes to issues such as freedom of the press). In this way, as in many others, America is an ongoing experiment on the ideal relationship between citizenry and government.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Uganda, Ganda, Buganda, Baganda – these are all terms related to the Bantu land in eastern Africa. Uganda refers to the country in the present day, Ganda refers to its spoken language, Buganda to the kingdom preceding Uganda, and Baganda to its people. The Baganda live in the Great Lakes region of East Africa: the area around Lake Victoria (Nyanza). This is a relatively arid region in present-day Uganda, Tanzania, and Kenya, near the Rift Valley, where humanity’s ancestors originated.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Buganda’s story starts with Aksum, an ancient state where Ethiopia is today. Aksum collapsed at the very end of the first millennium CE. As a result, the southern region formed their own empire: the Empire of Kitara (Chwezi). In local lore, the Chwezi were spirits with red skin and bronze weapons, originating somewhere to the north. This depiction recalls the ancient Egyptians, though the local people now attribute a supernatural origin to this group. In their classic origin myths, the powerful but arrogant Chwezi gave the local people of the region all sorts of technological benefits (e.g. bronze) and terrible curses (e.g. smallpox). They left sites such as Bigo – a series of earthworks originally thought to represent a fortification that may actually have been a marketplace surrounded by an anti-elephant wall.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Chwezi ruled the land with skill, magic, and a magic cow. Prophecy claimed that the kingdom would survive as long as the cow lived. Naturally, the cow died, and the Luo people (of present-day Kenya) overran the Chwezi, taking their title sometime in the 1500s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In broader strokes, this myth depicts a world system along the Nile, where trade flows from sub-Saharan Africa into the Mediterranean. Arab conquests disrupted this link as swift Arab ships used sea routes to trade with Africa along the Swahili coast, and east/west caravans crossed the Sahara. These routes cut off the Great Lakes, isolating Ethiopia, which was aggravated further by Ethiopia’s resistance to conversion to Islam. The Great Lakes fell into obscurity while eastern Kenya prospered – as did Mali, on the other end of that east/west caravan pipeline. The Chwezi rulers fell to the Bunyoro, who in turn fell to Buganda.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The mytho-history of Buganda is contested. British explorers presented one version, which was tainted with colonial assumptions and presumptions; local histories present another, this time mixed with myth. According to local history, a great serpent (Bemba) once ruled the land, but a man from the east (Kintu) gained assistance from a tortoise to slay the serpent and claim the kingdom. Kintu’s children learned the traditions associated with society (e.g. metalworking, law and punishment, etc), and the empire grew and prospered.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Anthropologists do not point to these stories as actual history but as justification for the diversity in clan groups within Bagandan society. Referring to oral history can answer moral or ethical questions – for instance, what do we do when there is no legitimate order? We can turn to the story of Walusimbi's election to chiefdom. We can think of oral history not as an accurate account (not only an accurate account), but as a reference point for life lessons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>The Bugandan Empire is considered an “assimilative state,” or a state that aims to gain converts to its ethnic group. This approach often puts societies in a bit of a bind. Ethnic groups seem primordial, but they typically function and grow by incorporating outsiders into their system. Unfortunately, slavery was key to this strategy. Buganda led war canoe raids on their neighbors to forcibly bring people back for labor…and sacrifice, according to some sources. In short, Buganda was a kingdom with relatively defined borders but had various relations of vassalage and predation with its neighbors (i.e. sources of slaves, sacrifices, and plunder).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>In 1857, Sir Richard Francis Burton, an explorer and a critic of British colonialism, and John Hanning Speke went in search of the source of the Nile River. In so doing, the two entered into the Great Lakes region and encountered the Bugandan Empire at its height. Burton describes fleets of Bagandan war canoes embarking on plundering expeditions across Lake Victoria, detailing the hundreds of sacrifices that followed a successful raid (he remained six months and likely saw some of this).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Burton may have been a critic of colonialism, but his writings were responsible for one of the oldest (and most damaging) ideas about East African ethnicity. He contrasted a southern race of people with a northern one – the latter having more "refined" features (meaning more European), lighter-skinned, and more civilized, which reflected a racist understanding of the peoples of the world. This myth had a damaging synergy with colonialism and was responsible for colonial favoritism of “Nilotic” or northern peoples (e.g. Tutsi) while disparaging others (e.g. Hutu), which laid the seeds for later massacres in the region.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_BUGANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>We think of colonialism as a violent overthrow, such as the treatment of the Aztec or the Inca. However, this wasn’t always the case. For the Bugandan king Mwanga, an alliance with (i.e. the establishment of a protectorate under) the British in 1892 was a way back into power. Kabakas (kings) gained influence and power from association with the British and instituted particular rules that degraded the legitimacy of the office to increase the opportunities for expansion and power, especially over their rivals in the Bunyoro kingdom (Bunyoro were the previous overlords). An alliance with foreigners offered a way to subvert local hierarchies and checks and balances – existing outside of the clan system made it easier to claim rule over all, instead of just one clan. The British liked this system so much that they placed Buganda and Baganda at the center of their colonial efforts, and Baganda became the face of British power in the area. Buganda became a sub-set, but a dominant one, of the colony of Uganda.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the wake of Napoleon’s rise after the French Revolution, the French Empire became a major force on the world stage and Britain's principal antagonist. Though the Revolution deposed monarchies, France moved between various monarchies and new republics before its eventual defeat during the two World Wars. In that period, France became synonymous with culture, arts, and strident military conquest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Kingdom of France was the cultural center of the world for much of the 18th century. Most European courts (Austria, Germany, Russia, etc.) spoke French in an attempt to emulate the finery of Louis XIV's court. By the mid-18th century, France became one of the most powerful and influential forces in Europe. The French system epitomized absolute monarchy, a system that predominated Europe's Industrial era.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>This system was different from what had come before. For example, feudal monarchs were not absolute authorities; they existed in relationship with a tree of marquises, dukes, etc. On the other hand, an absolute monarch gave all control to one person (and often rested atop a merit-based system). As observed by Louis XIV, "L'etat, c'est moi" (“I am the state”). Traditional checks on royal power were removed, which could be terrifying if the ruler was corrupt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Still, this system rested on inequality, and the French Revolution in 1789 sought to correct that. Over the 18th century, the French population grew at an enormous rate leading to famine and calls for redress. Given the opulence of the palace and the U.S.'s example of a different kind of government, the population's desire to overthrow the old regime soon boiled over. The following period was a cycle of moderate steps toward a constitutional monarchy, violent revolution, and violent counter-revolution, etc. By 1799, ten years of chaos had left the French eager for stability. Enter Napoleon, a triumphant army general appointed First Consul by the coup of 18 Brumaire (the revolution had even re-named the months). The chaos of the French Revolution (at times, democratic chaos) tilted toward the proto-fascism of the French Empire. This is where our story truly starts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>In this reckoning, the French Empire refers to a few political systems. Our use in Civilization refers to Napoleon's attempt to take over Europe, and the subsequent period of monarchical restorations and republics. At this time, France was a proving ground for novel political forms: democracy, military dictatorship, a cult of personality (which would later help give rise to fascism), and a call for absolute class equality (what became communism). France also oversaw a massive colonial empire with possessions in Asia, Africa, and a few in the New World.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>While France was being reborn, other European states saw it as a radical, existential threat to monarchical power and launched several attacks – the War of the First Coalition, the War of the Second Coalition, and the War of the (surprise) Third Coalition – which began in 1792 and lasted until 1806. These waves of conflict initially focused on reversing the French Revolution, then containing its spread, and finally restricting the expansion of France. The end result was an embattled France that turned its conflicts outward. France's powerful and influential army, and a triumphantly popular Napoleon, immediately returned to war. Napoleon was defeated at sea but triumphant on land and spread across Europe, reshaping the order of things as he went. Only after nearly twelve years was he finally stopped. The First French Empire existed in this state of near-constant war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>France during the "long 19th century," which existed between Napoleon's defeat and World War I, was a changed place. The traditional orders of power – the Catholic Church and the Bourbon dynasty – never recovered their old positions, and France vacillated between monarchical restoration, republic, and empire. The modernized country could better cope with economic shocks, and the subsequent years were relatively peaceful and prosperous. But this also bred conflicts; peace and prosperity gave rise to bourgeois wealth, which in turn posed a threat to the absolute order founded on aristocracy. An uprising in 1830 led to the end of the weakened Bourbon monarchy and the rise of a more liberal, bourgeois-allied monarch, Louis-Phillippe I. Louis-Philippe did not rule as "King of France" but as "King of the French," an important distinction as he had no pretensions toward divine right over the land, but he ruled a people known as "the French."</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Then came the conflicts of 1848. These arose thanks to the divisions between three social groups: the aristocracy, the bourgeoisie, and the proletariat. The aristocracy were nobles, of course, but nobles with severe limits on their power – absolute monarchies tend to take power away from their own nobles and consolidate it in the king. The aristocracy's power is based on heritage and a sense of natural rule of land. The bourgeoisie refers to business owners, whose power rested on owning property and capital. Finally, the proletariat were people who owned nothing but their bodies and skills, which they had to "sell" to the bourgeoisie for wages or give to their lords in the aristocracy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>What are fair terms for work in such a system? Should protections against the bourgeoisie be given to the proletariat? In the past, the people could appeal to the monarch to intervene, but without a monarchy, how could one seek rectitude? Then, in 1848, the proletariat and petit bourgeoisie (lower middle class) rallied for a state that might curb the excesses of the bourgeoisie and aristocracy. If this sounds like Marxist theory, that is because it was Marx who was writing at the time, using French examples to develop his ideas. In France, these protests led to the overthrow of the monarchy and the formation of a new republic. This uprising wasn't contained to France; across Europe, others were having the same conversations, leading to the same fights.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>The Republic lasted until the people voted for a tyrant – or at least an emperor – Napoleon III. Though his authoritarian reign was a step backward and was marred by poor foreign policy, it was also the source of one of the best pieces of political writing: Marx's reflections on Napoleon's rise, in which he points out how Napoleon III manipulated the symbols of empire to seduce a populace. The essay is considered the first real study and critique of modern fascism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>But that conclusion might be a little unfair. Napoleon III was caught between a few interest groups. Catholics in France were growing increasingly concerned over the unification of Italy at the time, as the new Italian kingdom was secular. The Catholics sought to turn France into the new haven of Catholicism, and Napoleon acquiesced to these demands, although he still permitted freedom of worship. Rising discontent led to mistakes on both sides, but after a member of the royal family killed an opposition journalist, public sentiment tilted dangerously against the monarch. This discontent eventually cracked after France's defeat in an 1870 war against Prussia, and a new republic was born.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Overseas, the French had two colonial empires. The first was largely gone by Napoleon III's time, but the Second Empire expanded into Algeria, West Africa, and Indochina. France was playing two games. On one hand, its heavily militaristic approach produced a deal of bloodshed. On the other, France had always been more assimilationist than the British, imparting more French cultural features onto colonial possessions in a shorter period.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>French society in the late 1800s was a time of peace and a flowering of the arts. The country rapidly industrialized and France embraced new technological innovations as quickly as it embraced new social ones. It was a place of painters, of poets, of electric streetlights, and railroads. During this time, Paris became the City of Light. The Third Republic remained until World War II, when a fascist puppet regime was installed in Vichy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_MEIJI -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEIJI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Japan in 1800 was a tightly controlled place. While the emperor in Kyoto was technically the country's leader, the real power rested with the shogun in Tokyo (called Edo at the time). Japan was largely closed to outsiders, except for a few ports for specialized trade. Noble families were pushed to reside in Tokyo, under the watchful eye of the shogun; due to this proximity, any rebellious daimyo (provincial lord) would suddenly find that his family was being held hostage. Yet the country prospered. The merchant class steadily acquired political influence. Foreign powers, especially the United States, grew increasingly desperate to gain inroads into Japan to capitalize upon its silver and rich manufactured goods. All the while, tectonic plates were shifting deep beneath the earth. All these factors ushered in a new age, when Japan became an international force to rival the great colonial powers of the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEIJI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Commodore Perry arrived in 1853, sailing four ships into Edo harbor straight past the Japanese lines. When the Japanese sent a delegation, he refused to meet and demanded to see a high-ranking leader, threatening to march his troops to the shogun by force. The threat shocked the Japanese political system. Upon Perry’s return the following year, the Americans forced concessions and trading rights on the formerly isolated kingdom.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEIJI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>That was only the beginning. In 1855, a massive earthquake struck Edo, provoking widespread fires and devastation. This catastrophe occurred in the wake of several other quakes, and the confluence of the disasters dealt a significant blow to the shogun's authority. The earthquake created ripples in Japan's social structure – the merchant class began to demand a new and increased role in political society. A new day was dawning.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEIJI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Japanese rulers struggled with these changes. In 1868, the emperor declared he would resume his position as the supreme power, ending the shogunate and embracing foreign technology and global trade. Naturally, old nobles rebelled, and the Boshin War ended with the shogunate dismantled as the emperor took direct control of its lands. Change came rapidly. Over the next four decades, Japan's silk exports exploded to nearly 300 times their initial output. This boom was coupled with a massive investment in steam power and railroads. The middle classes were freed of their feudal shackles, and the forces of industrialism spread across Japan. The Meiji (“enlightened”) era had begun.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEIJI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Politically, Japan weighed its options. Many argued for democratic rule, but nobles worried about the risks and instability involved in such a venture. The Meiji system had political parties, but real power was centralized – a model based on Western imports. Many see the West of the late 1800s as a democratic place, but this was not the case. Nations like the German Empire still maintained a strong authoritarian streak, a model of a modern, bureaucratic, absolute monarchy that favored industry and stability over participation. Meiji Japan took this path. Furthermore, Japan adopted a rhetoric of colonial supremacy mirroring European norms of the time, viewing itself as the vanguard of civilization in Asia, which led to its colonial-inspired seizure of Korea in 1910. Domestically, those newly empowered middle classes formed large corporate conglomerates (zaibatsu) such as Mitsui and Mitsubishi.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEIJI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>During this era, new ideas – nationalism, industrialization, and colonialism – gained root in Japanese politics. They laid the groundwork for later fascist movements. The militarization of Japanese society led to great success, including the Japanese victory over Russian forces in 1905, but it also unleashed a new era of expansionism across Asia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_MEXICO -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The name “Mexico” is derived from a Nahuatl word. The image at the center of the Mexican flag depicts the founding myth of Tenochtitlan, the Aztec capital. Still, how much of Mexico's history is bound with the indigenous inhabitants of the land, and how much originates with the Spanish conquistadors? The colony of New Spain was founded after the arrival of Hernán Cortés in 1519. At this moment in history, the Ming Dynasty reigned in China, Japan was about to descend into its Sengoku wars, and Ayutthaya (Siam) was a struggling city-state beginning to assert its dominance. William Shakespeare had yet to write his first word, and the Spanish had recently – less than three decades earlier – reconquered Spain from the last Arab caliphate. The world had just moved out of the Middle Ages.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Cortés’ conquest should be viewed in light of local events – he was a powerful new figure, and the tribes suffering under Aztec domination believed they could weaponize him. At least, that was the hope of groups such as the Tlaxcaltec. Soon, Cortés’ few Spaniards united with thousands upon thousands of the Aztecs’ indigenous enemies and descended upon Tenochtitlan, overthrowing the empire. New Spain was born.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>And New Spain kept growing. The Inca Empire fell not long after, along with its profitable silver mines. Spain soon colonized the Philippines too, as Incan silver was exchanged for Chinese goods at the port of Luzon. What was once two continents separated by an ocean, Spain saw as a unified system of tribute and trade. By the end of the 16th century, New Spain was incredibly profitable, producing plantation crops (out of Havana), mining precious metals (out of Mexico and Peru), and managing prosperous trade routes (out of the Philippines). The Catholic Church also played a key role, becoming an organizing force around expansion and settlement. Local “criollos” (people of European descent born in the New World) became increasingly influential. As the colony grew, more and more wealthy Spaniards were born in the colonies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Spain reached its height in the 1600s. Soon afterward came its decline. At the end of this period, Spain's Hapsburg king, Charles II, died without an heir. The various European powers saw this as an opportunity, and the French king (of the House of Bourbon) placed one of his relatives on the throne. This was a windfall for France but provoked the anger of neighboring nations. War ensued. The Bourbon king managed to cling to his crown, but Spain was weakened financially and territorially. Someone had to pay the bills.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>In the New World, this conflict led to the reconfiguring of New Spain's viceroyalties, and the colonies' previously independent trade systems were seized by the government. This action severely limited the power of criollo elites. Dissent simmered, especially after the American Revolution. Mass movements (begun by Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla) spread into widespread military defections and popular uprisings. At the end of 1822, Agustín de Iturbide overthrew Spanish rule, establishing a military government under the banner of the Empire of Mexico.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>However, Iturbide was out after a year, and the First Mexican Republic was born. This back-and-forth would become a pattern – the tension between militaristic conservatives and progressive-minded democrats resulted in chronic instability and successive coups d'état. The fluctuations between republic and empire were so frequent and quick that a full recounting would fill many pages. Still, this history is full of dramatic highlights: the would-be Bonaparte of Santa Anna, war with the United States, and a French invasion, not to mention the progressive figure of Benito Juárez.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>In 1876, Mexico achieved a moment of stability: the Porfiriato, dictator Porfirio Díaz's rule that lasted until 1911. Díaz was a mestizo military general who fought against Santa Anna’s empire. He later made a name for himself fighting under the French-installed empire on the fifth of May (Cinco de Mayo), during the Battle of Puebla. Under the Porfiriato, prosperity, development, and stability trumped democracy. The railroads improved every year and bread was cheap. If you’re going to assume absolute power and suppress dissent, you had better get things done.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>For Mexico, the period from 1884 to 1910 was marked by a balance of power. Díaz weighed nationalists against foreign interests (which Díaz saw as necessary for Mexican development). He co-opted local elites while centralizing the state. His overall philosophy was “pan o palo” (“bread or the stick”), meaning get on board and he’d be generous, but go against him and things would not go well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Díaz was corrupt. His foreign deals often took the form of monopolies, where an international company would be given control over local interests. He placed allies in high positions and chipped away at local autonomy (including indigenous autonomy). Díaz favored outside investors, and the state strongarmed indigenous groups and poor landowners, allowing foreigners to expand their operations. To this end, Díaz saw railways as key to national development, so he gave American companies concessions to build US-Mexican rail lines (and lines across Mexico to link ports). By 1910, there were nearly 20,000 kilometers of rail across the country, but these lines were built for foreign profit, not national development.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Díaz also promoted mining operations, pulling in capital from largely American investors. To these interests, Díaz passed a law allowing direct ownership of mineral wealth – meaning foreign ownership. This move generated profit, but much of it flowed out of Mexico, leading to widespread dispossession and poverty as more and more land was seized by landlords based in the U.S.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MEXICO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>In 1910, Díaz held grand spectacles of wealth and power, but everything was about to collapse. On the left, figures like Pancho Villa and Emiliano Zapata represented the peasant and indigenous resistance to the Porfiriato. On the right, Díaz was countered by wealthy landowners. Pressured from both sides, Díaz could not hold power. The Mexican Revolution of 1910-1920 marked the end of this style of reign and the birth of a more nationalistic, more socialistic Mexico.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mughal Empire was many things: an Islamic monarchy imposed upon a majority Hindu population, a place of excellence in poetry and art, and one of the most prosperous and productive nations in the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Mongol Empire reshaped Asia and Europe, but as it collapsed, regional aspirants struggled to claim the mantle of the Khan. Timur was an ambitious Chagatai raider who sought this exact path. To gain legitimacy, he married a descendant of Genghis Khan and became a gürkan, a “son-in-law.” Timur was a ruthless conqueror, but his descendants, the Timurids or Gurkani empire, were less so. They fostered a revival of Muslim culture after the decline of Arabia. This non-Arab Muslim movement was strongly influenced by Persian culture and centered in places like Samarkand and Herat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Scholars like Ibn Khaldun admired the Timurid Renaissance, which saw a flowering of Islamic knowledge and art slightly before the Italian Renaissance; notable figures included the painter Kamāl ud-Dīn Behzād. The Timurids declined in the 1500s, setting the stage for the Mughals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>At the time, the Delhi Sultanate was the center of India, a Muslim state ruling over a largely Hindu populace. It was founded in 1206 when Mamluks (Turkic warrior-slaves) established dominion over the northern part of the subcontinent. Over time, the Mamluks were ousted and an indigenous Muslim group came to rule. This era was rich and culturally prosperous, but the sultans often plundered and destroyed non-Muslim sites, damaging the development of Buddhist learning. The Sultanate stood powerful enough to repel Mongol attacks (from the Chagatai) until Timur’s descendent Babur appeared.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Babur was ousted from his home in the Timurid Empire and set his sights south, pushing down through Afghanistan and defeating the Sultan in 1526, which marked the end of Delhi. Babur believed he was maintaining Timur’s Gurkani dynasty, but Persian writers linked Babur with the Mongols – thus “Mughal.” While Babur established this dynasty, it reached its height under Akbar the Great, the third Mughal Emperor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Even though the Delhi Sultanate was (at the end) an ethnically Indian dynasty, it suppressed and repressed Buddhism and other non-Muslim beliefs across the subcontinent. Akbar did not do this, at least to the same extent (later Mughal emperors re-instated non-Muslim repression). Instead of outright violence, Akbar instituted conquest via marriages and alliances. Furthermore, Akbar abandoned the Muslim tax on non-believers, bringing Hindus into the fold, which they never experienced under Delhi. This tolerance extended to women as well; Akbar had a school devoted to the writings of female authors in his famed library. Ultimately, Akbar moved away from orthodox Islam and began to promote a Hindu/Muslim syncretic (fused) religion (the Dīn-i Ilāhī), though this religion did not last beyond his reign.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Under Akbar, the Mughal Empire expanded, tripling in size and wealth, until it controlled nearly all of South Asia and Afghanistan (except Sri Lanka, the very southern tip of India, the Himalayas, and Burma).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The Mughals were wealthy, which cannot be understated – in 1600, the Mughals were the second-wealthiest empire in the world, surpassed only by the Qing and surpassing all of Western Europe combined. Factory technology and wages were better in Mughal India than in their contemporaries in the West. In terms of wealth and learning, Europe reached its height a century or more later. Routes like the Silk Road were vital to an empire's prosperity – from the Roman Empire to the Arab Caliphate to the Mongols, whoever sat astride the Silk Road reaped its wealth. Prior to 1600, this pipeline ran from through Delhi, funneling wealth direction into Mughal coffers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>But change was in the air. Intercontinental trading ships set out across the seas, and the East India Companies were established. The shift from land-based to ocean-based trade heralded the Mughals’ fall, brought about by stagnation, rebellion, decadence, and a lack of sea power. When representatives of the British East India Company arrived in India, they were mocked as poor, unwashed barbarians. Within a few decades, they brought the empire to its knees. To understand how and why, we should look at the rise of Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Europe was devastatingly poor compared to India and China, but they possessed something important: a middle class. This thriving and politically active group of merchants and artisans existed to challenge political orders and adopt new philosophies. The East India Company was such a group and, along with the Dutch East India Company and the French, steadily grew the European presence in India in the late 1600s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>What did incredible wealth and luxury combined with a relatively moribund middle class mean for the Mughals? In short, decadence. Luxury consumption reigned and the Mughals had little interest in anything other than accumulating riches. Additionally, entrenched wealthy rulers imposed heavy taxes on agricultural peasants, limiting growth. Apathy, decadence, and indolence reigned during the later 1600s, which bred resentment and greed in equal parts. Rebellions and invasions began in earnest (especially from Afghanistan). Local rulers (nawabs) were influenced to sell off cities, permissions, and even entire kingdoms to the Europeans (who were granted approval to open “factories” – feitoria – in various ports) in defiance of the central empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>The European footholds bred several conflicts. The first occurred in 1686 as the East India Company broke treaties with the Mughals. The English do not look too good in these clashes – many of the complaints about the East India Company involved extortion of subjects (including peasants), rampant plundering, and excessive indulgence. All of this serves to amplify the increasing chaos. A Hindu king in Maratha had already broken away from the Muslim Mughals and used the empire’s weakness to launch a storm across the subcontinent. At the same time, the British were attacking from Bengal. No empire can persist under such conditions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MUGHAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>Indeed, none did. The Mughals were forced into a nominal protectorate under Afghan invaders, Maratha attackers, and the British. Technically the Empire ended when Victoria took over in 1876, but the Mughals basically fell under Muhammad Shah (1719-1748) with the emergence of the Marathas.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “German” is a broad category. For the Romans, “Germans” referred to the people across the Rhine. These tribes were small, inhabiting towns with hill forts, basic metalworking, mines, etc. They were illiterate and worshipped a variety of gods, of whom the Romans did not approve. They were not “a people” in the traditional sense, meaning they were not united by a common cultural identity, language, and religion. Ironically, in the Middle Ages, the mantle of Rome was assumed by their descendants – the Holy Roman Emperors claimed their title as a means to recognize their status as the guardian of Christendom (defined as Catholic).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Holy Roman Empire was a series of nominally independent states within a league. These included massive principalities (Bavaria, Austria, Brunswick), several theocratic states, tiny counties, and free cities (Cologne, Bremen, Hamburg). Most states had electors that they could assign to nominate an emperor. The majority of these were “German,” meaning they spoke one of the general languages of the region. Other territories included parts of the Netherlands, Czechia, Slovakia, Poland, Slovenia, Switzerland, and Italy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the later Middle Ages, a single dynasty controlled the Holy Roman Empire: the Hapsburgs. However, this was not an absolute monarchy; the power of the Emperor was limited by consultations with lesser nobles and princes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In the 1500s, Lutheranism was spreading, and while older rulers remained Catholic, free cities adopted the new religion. As the Thirty Years’ War tore the realm apart, this diversity became a liability. The issue was resolved when foreign powers decided that the Holy Roman Empire should be a passive, weaker entity within Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Prussia was an odd member of the Holy Roman Empire. Part of its domain lay outside the borders. This meant that the Prince of Brandenberg (Berlin) was also the King in Prussia, and he held a standing army that the Holy Roman Empire needed to defend its territory. As a result, Prussia and Austria began to compete over rule, seizing land outside of the empire’s borders and using it to amass their separate armies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Prussia had formed under two auspices. The first were the Teutonic Knights, a group of crusaders who were given Baltic land during the Middle Ages and then went on to take over parts of Poland that lay outside of the Holy Roman Empire. The second was the Hansa, a league of trading cities along the Baltic. The Hansa eventually conquered the Teutonic Order, which resulted in the formation of the Duchy of Prussia. As the Hanseatic domination continued, a once-bifurcated Prussia became united.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>By 1740, half of Prussia existed within the Holy Roman Empire while the other half remained outside. Still, Prussia remained diametrically opposed to Austria. As a result, Frederick II of Prussia waged war on Austria, seizing its territory and establishing Prussia as a monumental military force. Despite a brief defeat at Napoleon’s hands, Prussia emerged more powerful than ever in the 19th century. During the social revolutions of the time, Prussia developed into an authoritarian state, powerful and aggressive under the hands of Prime Minister Otto von Bismarck. The tides of German unification were turning; in 1866, Prussia again fought Austria for this mantle. In 1870, William I of Prussia was granted the title of German Emperor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>This late German-Prussian empire was powerful and militaristic. As Bismarck put it, the empire was built on “iron and blood.” Bismarck sought to avoid being outflanked (by a Franco-Russian alliance, for example) and aimed to hold his dominant position in Central Europe. Without a significant overseas empire (he had smaller ones in Tanzania, New Guinea, Angola, and others), Bismarck focused on turning Germany into an industrialized, militaristic, and authoritarian empire in the heart of Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PRUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>The end of Prussia came with the end of the German monarchy after WWI, though the state nominally disappeared in 1870. Prussia was defined by its industrialism, military might, authoritarianism, nationalism, and its embrace of technology. As such, it changed history, but not always for the best; this aggressive, modern, militant Central European power would turn into a nightmare scenario in the 1930s. Nonetheless, advancements in technology and innovation were key to Prussia’s success.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_QING -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Chinese history is long and complicated. The story of the Qing begins with the Ming Dynasty (1368-1644). Ming is often characterized as an insular, Han-centric reaction to the Mongol-led Yuan Dynasty before it, but that is not entirely true. Ming actively courted a central role in the region, setting up tributary states in most of East and Southeast Asia. These were not vassal states, but Ming had varying relations with local leaders who sent offerings to Beijing in exchange for protection or recognition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Still, Ming was large and bloated. Later Ming emperors were obsessed with court life and retreated into the Forbidden City, letting the realm manage itself. From the outside, colonial powers began to encroach.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Gold and silver were always highly important to the Chinese. European metals were traded on the Silk Road for Chinese goods. After the fall of the New World empires, the Spanish and Portuguese increased this flow – Mexican gold crossed the Pacific to Luzon, where it was exchanged for Chinese goods bound for Spain. The Portuguese also set up their base in Macao as an entrepot for exchanging silver from the New World and Japanese for Chinese goods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Cracks eventually started to show for the Ming. Following the closing of Japanese borders during the Edo period, this silver supply waned. While Europeans could do without Chinese goods, the Chinese could not do without silver, and currency prices fluctuated radically. These factors, plus a series of famines, dramatically diminished Ming rule. Northern Manchu tribes began to unify and realized that the Ming armies were weak. Additionally, Ming peasants felt they could no longer afford to pay taxes and internal rebellions erupted. The Ming collapsed under the weight of these threats, and the Manchu armies descended upon China to establish the Qing dynasty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The Manchus were Tungus people, Siberians who had settled on the outskirts of the Sinitic sphere. They had their own language and script – writing derived from Mongolian. Their armies were divided into banners. In fact, the Eight Banners were their signature feature.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The conquest spread from the Manchu homelands in the north across most of mainland China, modern Mongolia, Tibet, and Taiwan. After Qing’s golden age under the Kangxi Emperor in the late 17th century, Qing began to decline due to stagnation, internal dissension, and foreign invasion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Several internal conflicts tore at the fabric of Qing society – generals rebelled and were shut down, sending “banner” armies across Asia as plundering refugees/raiders. While the emperors' Manchu identity appealed to non-Han Chinese – as did their embrace of Vajrayana Buddhism – Han Chinese still felt oppressed and stifled by another foreign dominion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The Opium Wars were indicative of this conflict. Silver remained an issue, even after Japan re-opened. The British were unwilling to continue to supply the Qing with silver and decided to introduce opium. When the Chinese refused to open their ports to this destructive product, the British launched a series of wars to force them open. This devastated and humiliated the Qing, especially when the Europeans took the palace and forced concessions (such as the island of Hong Kong). Likewise, the Japanese seized Korea from Qing's orbit. Reforms came, but they were too little and too late. Eventually, the regime collapsed under internal revolt. The new Republic, under Sun Yat-Sen, ushered forth a modern China.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>The Qing were not strictly xenophobic. Rather, they embraced the Ming bureaucracy and opened the doors for non-Han to enter the service. The bureaucracy was organized into six ministries headed by the emperor and run by the Inner and Outer Court (of the Forbidden City). The Inner Court, later the “grand council,” handled important matters, and the Outer Court oversaw everyday affairs. As with any good Confucian system, entry into the Ministries was governed by imperial exams. Mandarins were officials who achieved a high degree of expertise.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Qing had many cultural achievements. Its literature and art received a high degree of patronage, including the Six Chapters of a Floating Life. The empire was religiously Confucian, although Confucianism's extent as a religion versus a philosophy of rule is up for debate. Buddhism remained extant (both the East Asian Mahayana and the Tibetan Vajrayana schools), as did Daoism. These were not mutually exclusive schools of thought – indeed, one could be all three – though there are fundamental differences (for instance, in the debates between the Confucian obligation to family versus the Buddhist renunciation of the world versus the Taoist cultivation of personal spiritual power). Regardless, in the Qing era, Confucianism grew closer to a religion than ever before, and Confucius was elevated to an object of veneration with public sacrifices at the Altar of Heaven.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_QING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Qing became emblematic of Imperial China’s strengths and weaknesses. It was a multi-ethnic, highly bureaucratic, meritocratic society built on Chinese principles. It gave way to a Western-style republic, which was the last gasp of this major challenge to Westernization and a world order built around global norms. This led to a minor tone in political theory – a suggestion of a Confucian society built around meritocracy and harmony, proper ritual and action.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Russia has always existed on the sidelines of Europe and Asia; it is not fully part of either landmass but has been immensely influential to both. However, Russia was also the center of another world: the Slavic, Orthodox realm. The mythological origins of Russia center on Rurik the Viking who landed in Novgorod and united its warring tribes into a new hegemony. But, in truth, the state emerged when the Duchy of Muscovy extended its power across nearby Slavic, Baltic, and Finnic groups. This happened under Ivan III in the 15th century, and it transformed the meddling hands of the German and Scandinavian powers of the Baltic into a Russian heartland.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>After the fall of the Byzantines, Russia's emperors believed they were the last, best hope for Christendom. Therefore, while Europe was becoming more integrated, Russia remained split. On one side were the Slavophiles, figures that saw Russian identity and the Orthodox religion as the last bulwark of true civilization. On the other side were the more secular Europhiles, Enlightenment-focused individuals who were enamored with Germany and England and especially in love with French culture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Peter the Great was the quintessential Europhile (1672-1725). He embraced political reforms along European lines and brought feudal Russia into the era of European absolute monarchies. This required European infrastructure, European royal ties, speaking French at court, etc. Notably, Russian nobility intermarried with the West: for instance, Catherine the Great was German, but she married an heir to the Russian throne. Another interesting side story centers on how the genetics of England's Queen Victoria may have fueled the Russian Revolution – Victoria's granddaughter married the Emperor of Russia, thereby passing hemophilia to their son Tsarevich Alexei. The stress of this disorder allowed Rasputin to gain influence with the imperial family, and that relationship would contribute to the family's undoing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Back in the early 1700s, as Russia was expanding, Peter the Great desired access to the Baltic Sea. At the time, Sweden controlled the Baltic, so Russia defeated Sweden in the Great Northern War, seizing the area that would become St. Petersburg. The city would be home to a new Russia, a European one that could be a significant player in western affairs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Russia pushed east into Siberia and Alaska, creating a vast colonial empire that was roughly contiguous – its claims to the Pacific region appeared as early as 1700. Then, in 1721, Peter the Great declared his kingdom to be the Russian Empire. This was a realm styled after the European absolute monarchies of its time, but it remained torn between different cultural and religious orientations. Furthermore, it was a colonial empire that did not distinguish sharply between overseas and over-land. Both East and West clashed within its borders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Napoleon’s march on Russia was the stuff of legend. The French army famously fought against the Russians and the cold; as Napoleon marched forward, the Russians retreated, burning the land as they went so that Napoleon lacked supplies in the bitter weather. When he took Moscow, the Russians continued to retreat. Still, Napoleon learned that he could not conquer the winter. After his own retreat, the Russians followed him all the way back to Paris. For this resounding victory, Tsar Alexander I became the “savior of Europe.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Core principles of Russian life were questioned in the wake of the wars. In 1848, Europe was rocked by a wave of social agitation that called for revolution – a recognition of workers’ rights and the livelihood of artisans. Russia got initial wind of these social reforms as the empire moved toward autocracy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The Tsarist Autocracy (samoderzhaviye) of Alexander’s heir, Nicholas I, was contentious. In this system, the Tsar had sovereign authority, with full power over the state and its people. In Russia, this was amplified as no Pope existed to challenge the Tsar’s authority.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Autocracy was actually a feature of many Western powers – but it presented a step backward from the Europhilic reforms Peter favored. Russia retreated to Orthodox religion, an absolute bureaucracy, and an embrace of Slavic nationality. The latter was more inclusive for non-Slavs living in Russia than the name implies, but it was still less inclusive of Jews – antisemitism only grew worse until the Revolution. The idea of a unique “Russian soul” (russkaya dusha) became central to modern Russia, as seen in the writings of Nikolai Gogol, Fyodor Dostoyevsky, and others.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>As the Empire progressed, things fell apart. Powerful nations must project their power – they must always display that they are winning. Losses hurt. And the later 19th century was full of losses – in Crimea, especially. Fortunately, Russia was surrounded by empires that were decaying faster. As the Ottomans lost their holdings in Eastern Europe, Russia became the benefactor. As Qing China collapsed, Russia also gained its Asian possessions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Under Alexander II, Russia instituted a series of reforms against serfdom, especially the 1861 emancipation of the serfs. This move sent former serfs streaming into the cities. Nobles (who lost “their serfs”) were granted concessions while newly freed individuals were left swimming in debt. Alexander may have freed the serfs, but he forever held their ire, and revolutionaries assassinated him in 1881. The next ruler would not make the same mistakes, thereby continuing Russia's autocratic journey toward calamity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>The last Tsar was Nicholas II. Unfortunately, Nicholas was entrenched in the autocratic bubble; he was as committed to preserving it as he was blinded by it. Convinced of European superiority, Nicholas launched a disastrous war against Japan, seeking domination of Manchuria. At home, he treated petitions for reformation harshly.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_RUSSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>Imperial Russia was destined to fall. Hollowed out internally, it needed to project power that it did not have. The system had been heading toward collapse since Nicholas I. The contradictions in the imperial system were too great, and as wave after wave of revolutionary agitation swept the empire, it was only a matter of time before they washed over the palace. That happened in 1917 as the Bolsheviks came to power. What followed was the story of the U.S.S.R. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_SIAM -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the 14th century, former subjects and enslaved peoples formed various new societies from the ashes of the Khmer Empire. This included the Tai. The word “Tai" refers to a large language family. Tai people include the ethnic majorities of Thailand and Laos, and ethnic minorities in China (Zhuong), Vietnam (Black Tai), India (Naga), Burma (Shan), as well as non-Thai ethnic minorities within Thailand (Khonmeuang, Lue, etc.).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Tai had a few things in common: Theravada Buddhism, the idea of meuang (a city-state built around the prestige of a ruler and sacred city planning), “Indic” forms of power, and high degrees of literacy. Accordingly, Tai city-states arose in loose configurations: Chiang Mai, Luang Phrabang, Sukhothai, and Ayutthaya. Over time, these polities congealed into regional powers – Ayutthaya became the heart of the “Thai” region, Chiang Mai the “Lanna” region, and Luang Phrabang the “Lao” region. Each fought wars of prestige and people; in Southeast Asia, people were more valuable than land, but prestige was more valuable than anything. Through these conflicts, the states sought to capture skilled artisans and steal sacred artifacts, such as the Emerald Buddha, Siam’s most holy relic, which was discovered in Chiang Mai, taken to Vientiane [Laos] then stolen when the city was sacked by Bangkok-based forces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Ayutthaya rose in the 1600s and was the most powerful of the Tai states. At one point, this cosmopolitan city boasted a Greek governor and had a sizeable Portuguese and Japanese community. By this time, Cambodia was a shell of its former self…and Burma was powerful. The Burmese sacked Ayutthaya, plundering its wealth and sending the Thais fleeing south. These refugees formed an abortive kingdom at Thonburi, which was soon overthrown by a new dynasty. This one would last. In 1782, the newly founded city was given a glorious name: Krung Thep Mahanakhon Amon Rattanakosin Mahinthara Yuthaya Mahadilok Phop Noppharat Ratchathani Burirom Udomratchaniwet Mahasathan Amon Piman Awatan Sathit Sakkathattiya Witsanukam Prasit. This means, “City of angels, great city of immortals, magnificent city of the nine gems, seat of the king, city of royal palaces, home of gods incarnate, erected by Vishvakarman at Indra's behest,” but most Thais simply called it Krung Thep, the City of Angels. Foreigners mistakenly termed it “Bangkok.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The Rama kings of the Chakri dynasty united Siam – or Rattanakosin, as Siamese eras are named for their central kingdom. These kings began an aggressive expansion, retaking lost territory from Burma and gaining new territory from their neighbors, including Muslim states in the south and Laotian states in the northeast. Siam remained a mandala state – one centered around the prestige, beauty, and glory of the capital. Under mandala philosophy, it was better to wholly transplant a beautiful neighborhood, including its people, to the capital rather than let it linger at the edge of the empire. Thus Krung Thep grew, and grew, and grew.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>During the years 1824-1851, French and English interests were keenly fixed on the region. Both wanted Siam as a prize. What’s worse, Siam's previous conquests were coming home to roost. After a last fierce act of defiance, the Siamese put down Laotian rebels, and Rama III articulated a policy toward the farang (Europeans): Siam should study their innovations to benefit itself, but avoid obsession or worship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Rama IV put these plans into action. Even crippled by illness, he was an astute scholar of Buddhism, science, and history. Rama IV instituted reforms to the Buddhist clergy that might look oddly Catholic, creating a new, unified sect that was loyal to the monarchy, rather than Theravada’s previous devotion to the local community. He uncovered the ruins of Sukhothai, and within “discovered” a Thai precedent for the righteous rule of an absolute monarch. Rama IV also studied European sciences and arranged a great expedition to observe an eclipse in the southern provinces. In this, he presented himself as an enlightened monarch, an equal to European ones, and not a barbarous king. This image also distinguished him from the crumbling Qing empire (allying him with the Meiji emperors of Japan).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Rama V, Chulalongkorn, was the next, and arguably the greatest, Thai monarch. He turned his attention from religion to statecraft, taking Siam to the height of its power. Chulalongkorn, now revered as a god, modernized Bangkok by installing tram lines, instituting rational city planning, and creating a vast bureaucracy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Thai bureaucracy was a complicated system that transformed the country’s way of life. In the Thai feudal system (sakdina), dukes and princes were not lords of fixed territories as they were in Japan or Europe. Instead, these aristocrats served the center. The monarchy called itself the chakri, meaning the great wheel. Lords were appointed from the king’s family, and people often gained the king's favor after sending a daughter to his harem. As a result, there were a LOT of lesser lords to go around. The lords who didn’t receive a territorial appointment might work in the bureaucracy (patterned after the German imperial bureaucracy), which swelled to enormous proportions but remained incredibly productive. Chulalongkorn instituted a professional (not feudal) army, abolished slavery and prostration to the monarch, adopted western dress (selectively), and otherwise transformed Siam into a model of a European state…at least at first glance. Under the façade remained the workings of a divine god-king working within an Indic model. The two blended.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>The late Siamese period deepened in what Michael Herzfeld termed the “crypto-colonialism” of Siam: Western norms were adopted in ways that gave the impression they were already part of Thai tradition. Rama VI built upon Thai nationalism and recast the term “Thai” to denote an ethnic group, rather than a class status. Still, tensions were brewing, especially with the middle class, which was increasingly aware of a better life elsewhere. In 1932, the People’s Party forced Rama VII to abdicate and adopted a constitution, falling just short of proclaiming Siam a Thai Republic (the monarchy would return to a significant position in the 20th century, though the kingdom would technically become a constitutional monarchy). The Thai Phibul government drew close to fascist Italy and Japan, and it allied with the Axis in World War II, partially as an excuse to seize French possessions in Indochina. By the end of the war, elements of the People’s Party were operating at cross-purposes, feeding the Allies information on Japanese positions and opening the door for Siam – now Thailand – to escape punishment for the conflict.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SIAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Thailand remains a hybrid state today – a powerful military, an influential monarchy, and a sizeable bureaucratic middle class – and it holds an influential position within the region.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>