<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Main Modern Age Civics -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_FUTURE_CIVIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“The future is unwritten” proclaimed the punk rocker Joe Strummer, but this has not stopped generations of people seeking to create a new model for society. From Communist republics to millenarian movements, people have long sought to reshape society into forms never before seen, all in a quest to further perfect human belonging. The task remains incomplete, the revolution unfinished, the utopian world unrealized, but this does not prevent us from imagining what could be, just around the corner. Or, perhaps, on the next turn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_NATURAL_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What exists in the world? The discipline of natural history grew out of an attempt to understand the world outside of human constructions – literature, politics, etc. – and outside of the divine. Here, it seeks to understand nature in all its forms (ecology, geology), and how nature shapes human lives.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_NATURAL_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The discipline is often traced back to Pliny the Elder’s Naturalis Historia: 37 books devoted to everything from the stars to the rocks, from folk lives to horticulture. This attempt to catalog nature into a holistic image is not limited to Western works – Li Shizen’s Ming-era Bencao Gangmu is a similar attempt to chart the natural world, as do Yaqut al-Hamawi’s 12th-century works. Nor is it limited to the medieval period: later figures such as Carl Linnaeus, Alexander Von Humboldt, and Charles Darwin likewise sought out the underpinnings of the natural world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_NATURAL_HISTORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Natural history today is scattered across academic disciplines, including ecology, anthropology, geology and the like, but to call oneself a natural historian implies a devotion to the holistic – to both the function and artistry of nature.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_GLOBALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>How do we conceptualize events and connections when there are no more unmapped spaces? We may initially think that the world has only recently become globally interconnected in an era of digital linkages, but we have been linked for a long time. Take the sugar trade – European powers took a plant from Asia (originally from New Guinea, and transplanted elsewhere in antiquity), created plantations for it in the Caribbean, powered those plantations via enslaved people from Africa, and incorporated its refined product into their diets. One spoonful of sugar represents a network encompassing the entire inhabited world. Thinking globally means knowing about chains of production – and creating the economic and political apparatuses to manage them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_NATIONALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Nations are considered ancient; they are not. The Treaty of Westphalia in 1648 was the first document to establish the system of nation-states – geographically bound entities entirely sovereign in their own borders. This system is taken as natural; it is anything but, and in the years since the 17th century, we have been hard at work to reinforce the concept. Benedict Anderson terms the nation as an “imagined community,” where individuals who never met in person imagine they have something in common. For Anderson, this commonality comes from a standardization of languages, a single viewpoint (e.g. the development of the newspaper), and the growth of the centralized, bureaucratic state. When colonial powers traveled to other parts of the globe, they brought this idea of bounded nation-states with their own ethnicities, histories, and geographies – quantities inseparable from their neighbors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_POLITICAL_THEORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Philosophy in its classical sense combined natural science, rhetoric, theology, and the like – in essence, everything. The notion was that there was an underlying unity to the world. But as the sciences continued their trajectories, the bodies of knowledge differentiated themselves – the question of governance, the notion of lawfulness, legitimacy, and authority became the purview of political theory. Names in modern political theory include John Locke, Jean-Jacques Rousseau, Karl Marx, and John Stuart Mill, among others. What is a just society, and how do we build one? What is conservative, and what is liberal? What is authoritarian, and what is libertarian? These philosophies are governed by political theory, as are the particular ideologies within them. Political theory helps create a common language for governance and makes comparative politics easier.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_CAPITALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Capitalism is not free trade, though free trade is a key part of it. Instead, capitalism posits that any one planner cannot anticipate all of society's needs, but the natural law of supply and demand works (like an “invisible hand”) to help fill the needs of the masses. One thinks of the writings of Adam Smith, or Friedrich Hayek. For Karl Marx, capitalism was a system where those who owned the means of production (e.g. a factory or its machines) would hire workers, and profit was generated when the value of products produced exceeded the wages paid. In this way of thinking, capitalism was exploitative. When certain command economies fail and unexpected needs arise outside the purview of a planner, capitalism can succeed and fill that gap. On the other hand, capitalism's failures are seen in situations like the Indian famine of 1884, when railroads allowed grain to be moved to places where it yielded higher prices – leaving peasants unable to purchase it and starve. Capitalism remains the dominant form of economic exchange today – even communist societies such as China and Vietnam embraced certain aspects of capitalism through the 1990s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_MILITARISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is the proper role of the military in society? Should the army take a back seat as the servant of a democratic process, or is the military an active participant in politics? In militaristic societies, the choice is clearly the latter – leaders often come from the ranks of generals, and the military acts as the custodian of national values and norms. Terms such as “junta” are often used to describe militaristic societies. As dissent and debate are curbed, democracy often wanes under authoritarian regimes. We can see Napoleonic Europe as one example of this – gone were the old aristocracy, with their models of care for and stewardship over the population; instead, a military moved in, ostensibly standing outside issues of social class as it organized society to fit its own model.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_HEGEMONY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In its ancient use, hegemony referred to the dominance of one state or group over another. In its modern form, it refers to the writings of Antonio Gramsci, who posited a model wherein one group uses its cultural influence to establish a status quo in accordance with its interests. The theory seeks to answer a simple question – why do people act against their own welfare? What is considered possible? What becomes unquestionable? This echoes the rhetoric of democracy at large today – nearly every world power positions itself as a democracy (even when these claims are dubious on their face), but each power seeks to maintain the status quo. Modern hegemony becomes a kind of replacement for imperialism – rather than projecting hard power abroad, a powerful nation can shape international debate to its own norms. The United States and USSR were both examples of global hegemons in particular times, as each was able to dictate what was considered rational, normal state behavior. Challenging these norms proved treacherous, and risked a coup d’état…or worse.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_MODERNIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Modernity refers to a particular time and mode of thought beginning in the 17th century and continuing into the early 20th. In very broad strokes, modernism posits that things, be they industrial lines or political practice, are reducible to basic elements and forces. Modernization, then, seeks to make those elements and forces move most efficiently, maximizing output and minimizing input. As such, it has gone hand-in-hand with scientific thought, industrialization, and the growth in size and scale of the economy. Politically, modern movements have run the gamut: representative democracies, fascist dictatorships, bureaucratic monarchies, and single-party Communist states are often all modern movements.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_MODERNIZATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Modernity’s critics argue that in the reduction of life to a matter of input and expenditure, efficiency and rationality, other, more essential qualities are lost – these critics include the Romantic movement in art and literature as well as social critics such as Max Weber, who described modernity as the “iron cage,” one that traps thought and activity both, and from which there is no escape.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_DEMOCRACY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Democracy refers to the ability for citizens to affect the policies of their government. It is always limited in some way; historically, societies have excluded women, people without property, enslaved people, felons, or people with certain mental conditions. Athens is popularly presented as the birthplace of democracy, but in this modern definition, democracy is often associated with the establishment of certain rights for all citizens (voters or not). Some democracies retain a monarch (these are constitutional monarchies, not republics), while some democracies are capitalist and others are not. Some democracies permit all political parties, some exclude certain parties (e.g. fascist or communist parties), some limit political participation to one particular party, and some operate without political parties – though all have the vote.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_LIBERALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Liberalism is an often-misused word. In brief, liberalism refers to the rights of an individual as enshrined in the social contract, especially when such rights might conflict with the norms of the majority. Economic liberalism indicates the rights of individuals to operate economically as they see fit through an absence or minimum of regulation or taxation, whereas social liberalism seeks to protect the rights of the individual in terms of language, identity, or expression. Historically, the principles of liberalism, especially as articulated by philosophers such as John Locke or Thomas Hobbes, were foundational to the French and American Revolutions, as evinced by the former’s Declaration of the Rights of Man and the latter’s Bill of Rights. While often associated with “left” politics due to its social aspects, liberal philosophy leans more towards capitalism on the economic spectrum.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_PROGRESSIVISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Liberalism believes the state is limited in its ability to effect change, so it places its faith in individual action. This view of limited government often suggested that powerful individuals had greater influence than the general populace. From a progressive perspective, state power – and the advances of science and technology – should be used for the benefit of society, the growth of equality, and the mitigation of economic inequality. Progressives include Theodore Roosevelt and Woodrow Wilson, as well as modern-day figures (who may not identify with these historical figures) such as Bernie Sanders and Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_FASCISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fascism properly refers to the Fascist Party of Italy, though it is used more generally to refer to an ultra-nationalist form of government that embraces totalitarian control in the name of a nation and race. Fascist governments often revolve around the figure of a particular leader, and embrace military control over every aspect of political life, reinforcing this control with an ideology of racial superiority – often with a simultaneous focus on technological development and a flagrantly incorrect nostalgia for symbols and traditions of the past. Fascist movements usually arose from the petit bourgeoisie, rejecting intellectualism and a focus on workers’ rights from the left, while also rejecting the economic right’s interest in global trade. All aspects of fascist society, from factory to university, were mobilized for the nation and organized around the military. Criticism, under fascism, was tantamount to opposition to the nation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_FASCISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While World War II-era Italy and Germany were the quintessential fascist states, Imperial Japan of the time had nearly all of the trappings of fascism as well (present there, and absent in Italy and Germany, was an old monarchy). Fascism’s origins can be traced to other disturbing marriages of militarism and populism, from Julius Caesar’s takeover of the Senate in the name of the people (and with the command of the army) to Napoleon’s militaristic France and Louis Napoleon’s aesthetic authoritarianism. While fascists made communism their principal target, Stalinism contains more than a small dose of fascist ideology, and fascist groups remain active today in many countries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_RADICALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Consider France on the eve of its revolution. It was not a feudal monarchy; it was monarchical absolutism at its height. An absolute king governed a state from atop a vast bureaucratic apparatus. It was a would-be hegemony of Catholicism and tradition. Liberals sought to reform the state while moderate humanists, such as Lafayette, aspired to build a more honest monarchy. Meanwhile, radicals aimed to overturn the entire thing. From renaming the months, which were antiquated references to Latin, to abolishing the monarchy, to removing the church from its privileged position, radicals looked toward a future that would be devoid of the trappings of the past. In the Anglophone world, the writings of Thomas Paine and Mary Wollstonecraft emphasized a rational, secular break.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_RADICALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Elsewhere, radical ideas emerged in relative philosophical isolation (such as the Ikko-Ikki of the Sengoku era in Japan), focused on the more pressing issue of decolonization, or emerged after socialism replaced radicalism as the voice of the far left.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_AUTHORITARIANISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Legalist scholar Shang Yang, the architect of the Qin Dynasty’s philosophical underpinnings, envisioned a society in which all served the state. People’s wild impulses would be controlled by a strict legal code, where all came to serve the state, and the state served Qin’s military machine. Peasants were forced to marry, inefficient farmers were enslaved, and efficient workers were rewarded. Qin was one of the first real authoritarian states – it would not be the last. The reach for a strong central state and a firm hand guiding the population (especially via the military) would be a feature of societies from Napoleonic Europe, Stalin’s USSR, and the fascist world. Authoritarians see human nature as inherently in need of guidance and often turn to strong leaders for that guidance. In Napoleon’s France (as in others), the chaos of radical reforms and the omnipresent threat of counter-revolution meant authoritarianism was a means of the state’s survival. But at what cost?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_COMMUNISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to Karl Marx, economies contain contradictions that, in their resolution, push history forward. For instance, in feudal societies the rising urban artisans and merchants would eventually realize aristocracy was nothing more than fancy titles on an outmoded economic model and move toward its overthrow. The bourgeoisie – people with money and no titles – eventually set up a capitalistic system, but this featured its own contradictions: organizations only yield a profit if the wages they pay are less than the labor is worth. For Marx, the working class would eventually realize that they were being exploited, and seize the factories and machines – the means of production – for themselves. Then those who worked would have control over their labor, and communism would be realized.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_COMMUNISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thus, communism is both a political and an economic system, but Marx never saw it realized. While communist systems have, historically, flickered in and out, the Russian Revolution that led to the Soviet Union was the first major successful communist revolution. While Marx envisioned a society without the aristocracy or bourgeoisie, the Soviets and later communist states saw their revolution as unfinished, requiring a formalized Communist Party to educate and lead the masses (and stave off counter-revolutions from abroad). This party-led Leninism gave way to other varieties of communism: Trotskyism (a union of workers from every nation, eventually ignoring and surpassing borders), Stalinism (a nationally-focused ideology centered on a particular nation and leader), and others. Various communist states today embrace different variations of these philosophies, and communist parties in multi-party states focus on workers’ rights and unionization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_CENTRALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As states expand their bureaucracy and their reach over their citizens, their burdens grow. No longer does the populace need to be pacified, but schools, public health, transportation, administration, and the like all become important to the national good. Such measures require the growth of national bureaucracies. In the 19th century, in capitals from Tokyo to Paris, from Bangkok to London, such ministries grew, and with them so did the priority of the city over its hinterlands. If the modern nation was a body, these central ministries and departments were the brain and nervous system. However, with centralization comes a certain kind of domination – Parisian French, Tokyo Japanese, and Siamese Thai became the languages of the state, as Occitan, Osaka-ben, and Kammeuang withered. Local forms of cultural and religious practice took a back seat to metropolitan preferences, and capital cities ever expanded.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BRANCH_SOCIALISM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “socialism” has been widely misused everywhere from a synonym for communism (which it is not) to its adoption by fascist regimes (to which it is opposed). In short, socialism refers to the public ownership of institutions that are in the public's interest. Schools, hospitals, and welfare systems are often socialized, as free-market principles usually make little sense in those arenas. For instance, the public's interests are served when its citizens are educated. Other services also perform a general public good: police, fire departments, roads, and the like. Some socialist countries expand this concept – if steel is vital to the public interest, then it could make sense to nationalize refineries. While communist parties (after Vladimir Lenin) led the vanguard against capitalism, socialist states sought a middle ground, keeping private industry while ensuring citizens received everything they needed to survive and prosper. All states have some aspects of socialism – private fire departments are hard to find – but present-day socialist states may include Scandinavia or central Europe.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--Civ Unique Civics -->
		<!--America-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_AMERICA_YANKEE_INGENUITY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The early United States was split from its founding, with plantation-dependent, slaving societies to the south and independent farmers and tradesmen in the north (and, increasingly, a west composed of homesteaders pushing against indigenous polities). In the north, Yankee (a word referring specifically to New Englanders, not all Americans) descendants of religious refugees and new immigrants alike experimented with novel ways of being. Sociologist Max Weber described how Calvinist notions of salvation through labor transformed into a secular ethic of asceticism, accumulation, and constant re-investment in society and industry. This change led to a dynamic and innovative – but frugal and sometimes joyless – pursuit of capital. In the end, this society set a template for modern-day entrepreneurship and ingenuity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_AMERICA_CAPTAINS_OF_INDUSTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the humble beginnings of the ascetic Yankee tradesman to the robber barons of the early 20th century, America was shaped by capitalism on a massive scale. Under figures such as Cornelius Vanderbilt, John D. Rockefeller, and other captains of industry, enterprise worked both through and for financial institutions. Building upon America’s industrialization and growing rail and petroleum dependency, business tycoons used virtually unregulated markets to secure monopolies and adopt new technologies, leading to the exploitation of labor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_AMERICA_CAPTAINS_OF_INDUSTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>An economy built around the wealthy few may signal the waning of the state, but this gave rise to private philanthropic enterprises, especially the growth of universities – Vanderbilt, Cornell, Stanford, and Carnegie Mellon, among others, are all named for the robber barons of the Gilded Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_AMERICA_WARTIME_MANUFACTURING_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>With some adjustments, factories designed for automobiles can produce armored personnel carriers. Cans of food intended for supermarket shelves can easily be diverted to the front lines. During wartime conditions, the United States turned its newly formed industrial might into the backbone of its war machine. This transformation enabled rapid growth of logistics, but also graft and corruption. Wartime profiteering – the exploitation of government contracts in the interests of profit – was and continues to be a massive problem of wartime manufacturing, so much so that President Dwight Eisenhower decried the “military-industrial complex,” a union of military and capital that served profit over patriotism (as Joseph Heller’s Milo Minderbinder epitomized).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_AMERICA_MANIFEST_DESTINY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The American Revolution was fought for freedom against mercantilism and the exploitation of the colonies, but land ownership also played a part. The British hesitated at the colonists' westward push and limited American expansion past the Appalachian Mountains – a paper decree more than a real restriction as Americans were rapidly setting up towns and farms beyond official borders. After independence, and especially after the Louisiana Purchase of 1803, the United States began to believe it possessed a divine claim to all land from the Atlantic to the Pacific. In the words of an editorial writer in 1845, this was “manifest destiny,” a marriage of religious fervor, capitalist acquisition, and colonialist expansion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_AMERICA_MANIFEST_DESTINY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As Shawnee and other indigenous resistance movements demonstrate, this policy was highly detrimental to people already existing in lands that destiny had “given” to the United States. As the USA pushed westward towards the Pacific, they encountered resistance from people like the Haudenosaunee, Shawnee, Apache, Lakota, and even European-descended separatist groups (in Utah, for instance).</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Buganda-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BUGANDA_NNALUBAALE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Africa’s largest lake, and the largest lake in the tropics, Nnalubaale is perhaps more widely known by its English name: Lake Victoria. This body of water was the lifeblood of Buganda. Kabaka (the kings of Buganda) sent their war canoes across the lake on devastating raids, creating a lake-based empire that was on the rise when the British took power in 1884.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BUGANDA_NNALUBAALE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the 1800s, the ecology of Nnalubaale was rich and varied, hosting a variety of fish, fowl, and animals such as hippopotamuses, crocodiles, and otters. Cichlid fish were notable as Nnalubaale hosted hundreds of species, many of which remain undescribed. Unfortunately, Nnalubaale was the victim of a devastating ecological catastrophe; after Nile perch were introduced to the lake in the 1950s, they took over the ecosystem, pushing a mass extinction and subsequent disruption of the water chain and food cycle. It remains a testament to the destructive effects of seemingly small changes in complex systems.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BUGANDA_BLUTABAALO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Baganda military strikes, or blutabaalo, were rapid, devastating affairs. A fleet of two hundred or more war canoes and a hundred thousand infantry could descend on a lakeside town and plunder it in minutes. Through these raids, Buganda expanded its power; it was an expansion its rulers felt was necessary. By the late 19th century, Muslim trading circuits were making inroads into East Africa, and European colonialism was also making its first forays into the area.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BUGANDA_BLUTABAALO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Baganda military were lightly armed with spears; they focused on speed and surprise. Guns arrived in the latter part of the 19th century as connections with Turkish-controlled Sudan and Swahili traders increased.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BUGANDA_NYANZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Great Lakes of Africa are where humanity first came into being. The nyanza (lakes) were formed during the tearing of the Great Rift, a cracking of the African tectonic plate that raises mountains and forms valleys running from Ethiopia south to Mozambique. Some lakes, such as Nnalubaale (Lake Victoria) drain into the Nile. Others drain west into the Congo. And Lake Malawi feeds the Zambezi, forming the heart of most of Africa’s vital river systems. Some of the lakes, such as Turkana, feed into nothing and have developed unique hydrologies; in Turkana’s case, the lake is highly alkaline.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_BUGANDA_NYANZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Ganda and other Bantu people have long relied upon the nyanza as sources of food, irrigation, transportation, and interconnection. This is especially true for Nnalubaale-based groups, where the lake forms Africa’s largest inland fishery.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--French Empire-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_FRENCH_EMPIRE_BELLE_EPOQUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the calm between wars, at the end of the 19th century, Paris truly became a “city of light.” As peace reigned on the continent (and colonial profits rolled in), Paris transformed into a hub for art, literature, music, and the like – at least for those who could afford it. This was the life of Baudelaire’s flaneur, the wanderer of the city streets who did not have a destination but sought the simple pleasure of being out and alive in the city. This was the world of the Moulin Rouge and the Eiffel Tower, Haussmann’s grand avenues, Marcel Proust and Arthur Rimbaud, impressionism, and the birth of cinema.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_FRENCH_EMPIRE_BELLE_EPOQUE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>All of this came crashing down during the devastation of World War I, a conflict that revealed how the technology that lit cities and brought them to life could also destroy them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_FRENCH_EMPIRE_VOIE_TRIOMPHALE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Triumphal Way is a thoroughfare in Paris that includes the Champs-Élysées and highlights 19th-century French monuments and architecture. The iconic avenue starts at the Louvre and extends to the Arc de Triomphe, passing gardens, palaces, and parks along the way. Many of its features were originally emblems of the ancient regime – the monarchical system overthrown by the Revolution – but this makes the Voie Triomphale a testament to France’s adaptability and resilience, as former palaces become parks and public museums. This beauty is a product of destruction; as with other Parisian avenues, the wide, tree-lined avenue was built to erase the city that came before. Baron Hausmann, the planner who undertook the renovation of Paris under Napoleon III, intended lanes that could accommodate cavalry units, uniting beauty with authoritarianism. Nonetheless, today the street is often referred to as the most beautiful in the world, and it is a symbol of France, high culture, and the allure of cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_FRENCH_EMPIRE_GRANDE_ARMEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Napoleon sought to reshape the world into a new empire. The Grande Armée was his tool – a fighting force of over half a million men, adopting new tactics and technologies for conquest. This army included the standard line infantry, dragoons, grenadiers, cuirassiers, as well as Napoleon’s elite Garde Impériale. In the Grande Armée, soldiers of almost any background could rise in its ranks; Poles, Austrians, Italians, and even Prussians served under the French flag.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_FRENCH_EMPIRE_GRANDE_ARMEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The army was powerful, but winter was more so. As the Grande Armée marched on Moscow, they faced constant military engagement with Russian forces and relentless rain only to discover Moscow was a burned-out shell. The Russians had destroyed their capital in order to save it. Napoleon’s retreat marked a turning point in his fortunes. The waves of French imperialism had not dashed against an unstoppable force, but petered out in the frozen Russian landscape.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_FRENCH_EMPIRE_CODE_CIVIL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Code Civil des Français, or the Napoleonic Code, was a body of civil law based on the legal code of the Byzantine emperor Justinian, and part of it remains in effect today. As a civil law code, its contents were designed to apply to everyone, and could only be amended via legislature. Though many countries rely on civil law systems today, this approach was revolutionary at the time. The Code was written in vernacular French, making it readable by everyday citizens (and it was intended to be read). It excluded references to religion and placed all – judge or priest, monarch or citizen – under the law.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Meiji-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEIJI_BUNMEI_KAIKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As American gunboats threatened Edo, it was clear that the power of the Tokugawa Shogunate was over. Japan faced an existential threat: adapt to foreign ways or fight. While conservative forces gained some initial ground, the policy of bunmei kaika, or Westernization, became the path forward during the Meiji Restoration. This entailed adopting parliamentary political norms and industrialization as well as seemingly unrelated cultural norms: cutting hair short and eating Western-inspired food such as croquettes, tonkatsu, and pasta. This interrelated mix of politics, cuisine, and aesthetics speaks to the profound level of change that occurred during the Meiji period – the notion was that every aspect of everyday life needed to shift for Japan to achieve equality with foreign powers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEIJI_OATH_IN_FIVE_ARTICLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As Meiji Japan opened up to the rest of the world, the emperor decreed a list of five principles that Japan should follow: assemblies should be formed to discuss all matters openly, all classes should be involved in the administration of the state, all individuals should be able to pursue their own ambitions, “evil” traditions should be abandoned for the “laws of Nature,” and outside sources of knowledge should be pursued.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEIJI_OATH_IN_FIVE_ARTICLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While these principles marked a direction forward, they were exceptionally vague. For instance, the “laws of Nature” are open to interpretation – every social system believes it has given up evil traditions. Holding assemblies seems democratic, but how much power should assemblies be given? (The military held significant, and eventually complete, power until the 20th century.) The freedom for all classes to pursue their ambitions was indeed revolutionary, but classes still existed. In short, things changed but remained the same.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEIJI_SUPREME_WAR_COUNCIL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Meiji Japan, westernization meant more than a cultural change; it was an alteration in systems of authority. Based on German imperial bureaucracy, the Meiji administration sought to keep the emperor at the heart of things. The Supreme War Council was a means to this end, and it created a collection of ministers and heads of staff that responded directly to the emperor, bypassing civilian oversight. These were the rails on which fascism could run and were a key part of the Meiji administration’s steps towards an eventual authoritarian government.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEIJI_KANTAI_KESSEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Originally designed from a naval theory by Alfred Mahan, the Kantai Kessen or Decisive Battle Doctrine became the organizing principle of the Japanese navy in the early 20th century. It took inspiration from the Battle of Tsushima, when the Japanese navy wiped out the entirety of the Russian Baltic fleet within the space of a single night. Tsushima’s success was owing to logistics – the Russians had sailed nearly around the world, technology – the Japanese ships were newer and faster and sported wireless technology, and the Japanese had a more experienced crew.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEIJI_KANTAI_KESSEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As such, in future engagements, the Japanese fleet sought to goad an opponent into a single confrontation, on terms and grounds selected by the Japanese fleet, and thus end a future war in a single stroke.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Mexico-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEXICO_PLANES_POLITICOS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is a revolution without a manifesto? In Mexico’s long series of revolutions, revolutionary leaders and those seeking to quell rebellions created plans for a new order. These plans struggled with topics like the nature of power (authoritarian or egalitarian, democratic or military) as well as the shape of the new society (Catholic or secular, nationalist or global).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEXICO_PLANES_POLITICOS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>There are over a hundred planes politicos in Mexican history – we feature only three.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEXICO_PLAN_OF_IGUALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Plan of Iguala was promulgated in 1821 as Mexico's declaration of independence from Spain. However, as often happened in revolutionary histories, the Plan left significant aspects of society intact. As a result, independent Mexico became a Catholic monarchy. While all Mexicans – white, black, and indigenous – were given equal rights to peninsulares (Spanish-born Mexicans), the structure of society remained profoundly unequal for most Mexicans.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEXICO_PLAN_OF_IGUALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Plan, drafted by to-be Emperor Agustín de Iturbide and revolutionary Vincente Guerrero, is often called the Plan of Three Guarantees. These guarantees were: Catholicism, independence from Spain, and social equality for all, regardless of ethnicity. However, Iturbide’s empire fell just a couple of years later, opening the path for a new, more democratic order.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEXICO_PLAN_OF_AYUTLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Revolutions do not always lead to freedom. In its early days of independence, Mexico experienced periods of dictatorship and empire (even a monarchy). The Plan of Ayutla was an attempt to defeat one of these. Under Santa Anna, Mexico was increasingly centralized and militarized. This fostered dissent from Mexican liberals. The Plan pushed for a more representative republic, one that would end dictatorial control and restore Mexico to a democracy. The principal leaders of the Plan were Juan Álvarez, Ignacio Comonfort, and Benito Juárez, who fought on different fronts but eventually succeeded in cutting off Santa Anna and forcing his surrender and abdication in 1855. This move ushered in a democratic period until Mexico again became an empire in 1863.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEXICO_PLAN_OF_TUXTEPEC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mexico's late 19th century was defined by Porfirio Díaz, a former revolutionary and political leader who embraced a policy of order and progress, one that was nominally democratic but practically authoritarian. And yet he gained his entry into politics opposing these measures. The Plan of Tuxtepec was drafted in 1876 in opposition to the re-election of the former vice president of Mexico, Sebastián Lerdo de Tejada. Foreseeing that Lerdo de Tejada sought a constant grip on power, the Plan focused on banning re-election. After a brief attack, Díaz won out, and the Plan was put in place.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MEXICO_PLAN_OF_TUXTEPEC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>This did not last long. In a supreme irony, Díaz himself implemented the authoritarianism he seemingly opposed. While Díaz resigned after his first term as President, he ran for a second time in 1884 and did not relinquish power until 1911, winning (often corrupt) elections year after year, until the Mexican Revolution ended his reign.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Mughal-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MUGHAL_ZABT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mughal rule over India involved the establishment of centralized power over a diverse array of formerly independent kingdoms. As with so many monarchies and colonial polities in the modern period, this required a bureaucratization of power and the implementation of tools for knowing the land and its residents so they could be harnessed for gain. In the late 1500s, the Mughals surveyed and cataloged land yields and productivity. This recurring survey, and the subsequent taxes placed upon the resources that it found, was known as the zabt. Significantly, the zabt was collected in cash and paid to the zaminda. This was not the corvée system of the premodern time, but a new revenue stream for a new order.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MUGHAL_ZABT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Mughals used their newfound revenue to create an exceedingly wealthy state, which became a tempting target for foreign adventurers and militaries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MUGHAL_JAGIR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Bureaucratic regimes often ruled by subverting local nobles. In Mughal India, this was achieved via the jagirdar system, wherein land grants (jagir) for life were granted to those who served the central administration well. This structure provided an incentive for capable soldiers, wealthy merchants, and learned scholars to contribute to the systems of rule. And since these grants were linked to individuals and not a lineage, they ensured control would return to Delhi when the owners passed away; the name jagirdar is Persian for “placeholder.” The system remained in place with Mughal’s successors, including the British Raj, and was abolished in 1951.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MUGHAL_MANSABDARI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As opposed to a feudal system, a centralized monarchy like that of the Mughals institutes a regimented system of order and rules, ranks and duties, all dependent upon the center. These structures epitomize the mansab of Mughal India, a system that established a hierarchy of 33 categories assigned by the king to deserving nobles. It allowed for a more standardized system of rule, one that relied on the constant maintenance of favor from the Mughal king for advancement. The non-inheritable nature of mansab was vital to preserving this center-oriented system. This element was especially important as the Mughals ruled over a poly-ethnic, poly-religious community. A central authority would always be shaky in this situation, and local lords were enabled to create local dynasties that could pose a threat to the central system after a few generations – and indeed they did.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MUGHAL_GARDENS_OF_PARADISE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mughals were descendants (of a sort) of ancient Persia. Persian culture and religion had long had a profound influence on Central and South Asia. When the Mughals seized power in India, they brought adaptations of the ancient Persian pairidaeza (paradise garden). These Mughal gardens were simulations of the Islamic heavens, a geometrically arranged union of nature and culture. Their intent was best exemplified by the concept of the charbagh, a garden laid out in four corners, and a design visible in Mughal constructions such as Humayun’s Tomb and the Taj Mahal. They remain vital spots for tourism, as well as rest and relaxation, in present-day India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Prussia-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_PRUSSIA_RUHR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Ruhr describes a river and its valley located in western Germany. However, the term became synonymous with Germany’s industrial revolution of the region. In the 1700s, industrialists built mills along waterways and exploited the region’s coal resources to produce high-quality iron and steel. By World War I, the region was the beating heart of Germany’s industry, including weapons manufacturing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_PRUSSIA_RUHR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Targeting the Ruhr was a vital part of Allied strategy during World War II. Bombing pushed production to a standstill, and the region took several decades to recover. When it had, the world had, partially, moved on from coal-powered heavy industries. It remains a piece of Germany’s industrial cultural heritage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_PRUSSIA_ZOLLVEREIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Germany was not always Germany. In previous years, disparate German states (most notably Austria and Prussia) vied for control over a loose feudal union – the Holy Roman Empire (and later the German Confederation). As the region’s economy became more interdependent, the various borders between German states became hindrances. The temptations of industries to look outside Germany for resources became a threat to the economy. Therefore, industrialists and those seeking economic independence were unified in promoting a toll-free trading zone within Germany: the Zollverein. The Zollverein tied them firmly to Prussia (as the agreement excluded Austria). Furthermore, as small states gained a great deal of income from tariffs, the creation of a tariff-free union eroded local power to the benefit of the center. A unified Germany took one step further into existence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_PRUSSIA_EMS_DISPATCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If World War I was an apocalyptic clash of rival nationalisms, the stage for that conflict had been set long before. One of the preludes to the Great War was a clash in 1870 between Prussia and France, a conflict that displayed the incendiary power of popular sentiment and the destructive potential of nationalism. After the Austro-Prussian war in 1866, Prussia became ascendant in Central Europe, and its rise sparked fears across Europe. After a Hohenzollern (Prussian ruling dynasty) candidate was suggested for the vacant Spanish throne, France’s Napoleon III voiced protest, seeking the candidate’s withdrawal and a promise that no Hohenzollern would ever again stand for the position. This was the final straw for the Prussian chancellor Otto von Bismarck. The dispatch’s message alerting him to this demand landed in the popular press in Germany and France, and nationalist sentiments boiled over.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_PRUSSIA_EMS_DISPATCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The resultant Franco-Prussian War had one decisive result: the unification of Germany in a Prussian-led empire. The clock ticked one notch towards the calamity that detonated forty years later.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_PRUSSIA_BEWEGUNGSKRIEG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hit fast and where the enemy is weakest – this was the philosophy of maneuver warfare, bewegungskrieg. Rather than attack fortified positions to whittle away the enemy’s troops, Prussian troops excelled at crippling supply lines, command centers, and other weak points that were vital to fortified centers. But Friedrich II’s military was not alone in this strategy – the principles of maneuver warfare undergirded other militaries, namely the Mongol hordes. A superior force of soldiers could crumble under low morale, lack of supplies, and outdated information.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Qing-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QING_TEN_GREAT_CAMPAIGNS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the reign of the Qianlong Emperor in the second half of the 18th century, China sought to expand and reinforce its borders to the north, west, and south. Between 1755-1792, the emperor launched a series of ten campaigns. The first three wars brought an end to several decades of conflict with the Dzungar Khanate, an Oirat Mongolian empire in the northeast. Subsequent campaigns saw Qing invasions of Burma and Vietnam, and the suppression of several internal revolts. The Qianlong Emperor widely promoted the Ten Great Campaigns through commemorative works, commissioning painters to illustrate his battles and self-penning poems and documents to instruct future generations on these accomplishments.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QING_OPEN_CUSTOMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the 18th century, the world was quickly expanding. Travel was faster than ever, fostering global trade systems that boomed in both volume and frequency. As more merchants arrived on Chinese shores, the Qing found themselves in a position of power, particularly in the face of European expansion. China had many goods that the West desired, such as tea, porcelain, and silk. The empire primarily needed one thing in return: silver, which it used for currency to keep the native economy flowing. European trading companies shipped the metal from the New World to East Asian ports. The Qing kept tight control over local customs, eventually funneling all international trade through a single port city, Canton, and moreover through a single merchant guild, the Cohong. Although these measures are sometimes interpreted as limitations that narrowed the Qing economy, the opposite was true and the consistent import of silver ignited the internal economy, continuing the tradition of strong markets from the Ming era.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QING_KANG_XI_TAX_REFORMATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Kang Xi Emperor was the second ruler of the Qing dynasty, an impressive warrior and administrator with a particular knack for state finances. He was thrifty in his personal life, keeping a small and inexpensive court and self-funding his travels, whether for business or pleasure. However, his frugality did not extend to his people. The Kang Xi Emperor never raised taxes during his reign. Instead, he consistently lowered them, and, through his meticulous attention, maintained this policy even during wartime. In 1711, he announced his most ambitious reformation: all taxes would be collected based on the population at that very moment, freezing collections for households even if they continued to grow in the future.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_QING_STABILIZING_FRONTIER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Qing dynasty oversaw a period of immense geographical expansion for China. These new borders were ambitious and required careful administration to maintain and govern. A wide variety of methods were used to stabilize these borderlands. Within China, a special agency called the Lifan Yuan was assigned responsibility for the governance of frontier territories in Inner Asia. However, the Qing also forged relationships with neighboring countries to maintain peace. They established a tributary system with states in East and Southeast Asia, through which they assumed significant influence. Meanwhile, in the far northeast, they signed a treaty with Russia that calmed relations and allowed for trade between the two nations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Russia-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_RUSSIA_SERFDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Serfdom is a form of bondage that ties people to land. When a noble acquired or sold property, the farmers who worked the land stayed with the land. In theory, serfs had no freedom to leave, but, unlike slaves, they could not be bought or sold individually. However, as the Russian economy modernized, the line between serf and slave blurred. This was not lost on Russian writers – for instance, Gogol’s “Dead Souls” followed a merchant purchasing “dead souls,” serfs who have died whose deaths had not yet been recorded.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_RUSSIA_SERFDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Serfdom is not unique to Russia. It was a feature of most medieval societies, and aspects of the system were also incorporated into many agricultural societies. However, Russian serfdom was unique in that it persisted later than anywhere else in Europe, and the institution influenced many works by great Russian authors and artists; the life of the Russian serf became a lens that refracted Russian nationalism and national literature. Serfdom became a sign of the profound inequality of imperial Russia. It was the specter of a past age against which socialist and communist movements organized.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_RUSSIA_SERFDOM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Serfdom was abolished in 1861 by Alexander II, partially in an attempt to stave off a revolution. However, the terms of emancipation were often onerous, requiring serfs to pay back the cost of their freedom at inflated rates, wasting a fair amount of goodwill.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_RUSSIA_TABLE_OF_RANKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The replacement of feudal systems of nobility with an institution that stemmed from the center was key to the development of centralized, bureaucratic monarchies. This was the case in Siam, Mughal India, Meiji Japan, and across Europe. Russia was no exception. The Table of Ranks was a codification of this system – titles were established by the tsar and nobles moved from feudal lords to bureaucrats. While other systems (e.g. the Mansabdari system of the Mughals) eliminated hereditary titles, Russian titles could be inherited, after a point.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_RUSSIA_TABLE_OF_RANKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Table of Ranks was created by Peter the Great in 1722 and was abolished by the Bolsheviks in 1917.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_RUSSIA_SAMODERZHAVIYE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The modern era was a time of absolutism, at least in some places. The desire for information – to catalog, categorize, monitor, survey, and manage – increased along with the size and scale of nations, armies, and economies. Given this overload of information, one could either let the system manage itself (and risk chaos), or place it all under the control of one person. Imperial Russia chose the latter. Samoderzhaviye, or tsarist autocracy, rejected democracy and feudal nobility, seeking to elevate the tsar as the ultimate manager and arbiter of the state.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_RUSSIA_SAMODERZHAVIYE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The policy was abolished after the rise of the Soviet Union, but some historians maintain that autocracy gave the Soviet Union – and later Russian powers – their authoritarian character.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Siam-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_NINE_GEMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Nawarat, or Nine Gems, are important symbols of fortune and health across South and Southeast Asia. They are not a specific set of gems, but an association between gems and the planets: a ruby for the sun, a pearl for the moon, a diamond for Venus, and so on. The term indicates the system of royal and elite astrology patronized by the Siamese during the late 19th century (and continuing to the present day), seeking to harness some of the cosmic power of the universe in material form.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_NINE_GEMS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In early Southeast Asia, Hinduism was a key means through which the charisma of the monarch was established and cultivated. As Hinduism gave way to Theravada Buddhism, many of these rituals remained relevant: cities are still founded on auspicious days, kings still conduct fortune-granting rituals, and amulets featuring past monarchs or sacred signs and symbols (including the Nine Gems) are still features of Thai life. Even the full name of Bangkok translates, in part, as “the heavenly city built at Indra’s request, home to the Nine Gems,” and the name of the royal island Rattanakosin means “the place of the jewels.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_MANDALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A mandala is a circle. Naturally, as a political system, a mandala is a political circle – a radiance of power, using a combination of charisma and force, to draw in the hinterlands. This encapsulated the political systems of Southeast Asia before the mid-19th century: borderless kingdoms where one could fall between competing spheres of power. These ideas of land and lordship were different from European ideas of power (especially those of post-Westphalian Europe). Today, a nation has complete authority up to its border (and none across it), but in the past authority radiated outward. It could be bright in the center and diminish towards the edges.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_MANDALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Powers caught between mandalas, such as Laos, Cambodia, the Shan States, or Lanna (Chiang Mai), might pay a small tribute to each potential center, and could even be a lesser mandala in its own right. Scholars have termed this system “a galactic polity," Just as a star draws in its planets, each planet can have a pull on its own moons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_MANDALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>As a political system, the mandala ended with the rise of colonialism. The Siamese and British argued incessantly over where to place boundaries between new British conquests in Burma and Siamese dependencies on the frontier. The British sought to define a distinct border, whereas the Siamese argued that only an enemy would insist on a border (and they did not seek enmity with the British). However, the Siamese soon caught onto the rules of the game and spent much of the later 19th century converting formerly independent states that were marginally under their rule into parts of a kingdom with firm borders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_SRIWILAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Thai word “sriwilai” is a direct transliteration of the word “civilization.” But like so many loanwords, its meaning in Thai is different from English. As colonial powers expanded their presence in Southeast Asia, Siamese elite sought to adopt the manner and form of the colonists, at least in some respects. Edicts went out about proper public behavior (measures against the chewing of betel nut, for instance), public dress (in a head-scratching turn of logic, Thailand’s military ruler in the 1940s declared traditional Thai dress inconsistent with Thai culture), and sources of education and knowledge. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_SRIWILAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But all of this had a very real political project in mind: to ensure that the Siamese would be seen as more or less equals by those powers that posed an existential threat. With the monarchies of Vietnam, Cambodia, Burma, and Laos fallen, the adoption of “sriwilai” as a cultural code was a demand to be seen as equals, as people to be treated as fellow colonial powers, and not as a potential subject nation. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_SIAM_SRIWILAI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Finally, in its very spelling, the word reflects the intellectual work in building a sense of nationalism of the early 20th century in Siam. While “sriwilai” is an English loanword, its characters and spelling (e.g. the “sri” instead of “si”) are reminiscent of Sanskrit loanwords, thus in one swoop uniting an idea of Siam as the inheritors of a past Sanskritic civilization as well as a new, modern, European-style nation. The strategy seemed to work: Siam remained independent of direct foreign rule, despite heavy-handed influence from Britain and, later, the United States.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_SOCIAL_QUESTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civic life in the 19th century was in a state of flux, as the old medieval order began to decay and former farmers flooded into the city. Under feudal arrangements, local lords were at least putatively responsible for the well-being of their subjects, but in the city, no such noblesse oblige existed: workers were alone to face exploitation, squalid living conditions and poverty – the profits and industry that drove the industrial revolution were directly dependent upon the exploitation of those working the machines. Perhaps more influentially, those with power could see directly the suffering of those around them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_MO_MAIN_SOCIAL_QUESTION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>This, then, raised the “social question:” what is to be done? Is there a sense of justice that the state must respond to, or is this a matter for churches and humanitarian organizations? Workers began to see themselves as a collective force, to whom some justice was owed. From here came a wide variety of responses: welfare, humanitarianism, socialism, etc., which had in common a notion that squalor and suffering were not a natural occurrence that extends from the soil, but something that society both caused and could remedy. It is a question with which we still contend today.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
		