<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!--Tier 1-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_EXPLORER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civilizations have long been built upon the bones of what came before, and interest in past civilizations’ leavings has been a feature of human society – Ramses II’s son famously sought to study and renovate the step-pyramid of Djoser, a monument that was at his time already nearly a millennium and a half old. But the principles of modern archaeology first became applied in the 1800s. These focus not on recovering treasures or unearthing monuments, but on stratigraphy: the layer-by-layer excavation of a site that reveals far more detail than can be gleaned from artifacts themselves – how and when an object came to be in a place is often the most informative part of the excavation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_EXPLORER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Colonialism fueled much of the interest in early archaeology, as empire facilitated the movement of scholars to colonized areas, and sciences such as anthropology (in its 19th century form) sought to understand the evolution and development of cultures. Figures here like Augustus Pitt Rivers, William Flinders Petrie (who studied the Great Pyramid of Egypt), and Heinrich Schliemann (who excavated the ruins of Troy) formed the core of the discipline, and later archaeologists refined this to focus on the day-to-day aspects of ancient societies as a means to understand everyday life, beyond the massing of pyramids and temples.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LINE_INFANTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Arranging troops in lines makes sense in a battlefield simulation. Each soldier faces forward, and with the pull of a trigger, a deadly volley flies toward their enemies. This is how line infantry was utilized during the 18th and 19th centuries. For instance, the Napoleonic Wars call to mind pictures of regimented lines, resplendent in their elaborate uniforms, marching in order across an open battlefield. The line infantry era is known for its cult of military discipline – of rulers' pleasure in ordered parades and demonstrations that mixed discipline with pomp. However, a line only remained orderly for a moment, before the crack of fire erased the sound of a commander’s voice, the haze of gun smoke obscured each soldier's vision, or the cavalry charge bit into a line’s flank. Line tactics were only effective for the opening salvos, after which the battle devolved into the sorts of independent fighting that war had always known. Still, a good unit’s first volley could sometimes win the day.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_FIELD_CANNON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Artillery changed warfare. Early bombards ended the dominance of castles across the medieval landscape, but Napoleonic generals took artillery seriously as a centerpiece of strategy and brought it onto the battlefield proper. The field cannon epitomized this shift – it could be relocated from place to place, allowing for strategic bombardment of enemy positions even as the enemy moved. The resulting barrage meant line infantry could be destroyed even before they had the opportunity to form.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CUIRASSIER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>How does an army compete against horse archers? In the medieval period, this was the operative question for anyone whose land bordered Central Asia. These fast, mobile, ranged troops constantly harassed armored infantry. As gun technology grew in the 16th and 17th centuries, a new and more deadly take on the horse archer rose – the armored pistol-wielding cuirassier. These soldiers were swifter ranged units who could kill from far more than two or three yards away. As lancers declined in importance, the cuirassier's popularity boomed. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CUIRASSIER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Cuirassiers wore breastplates but kept their limbs free to swing a saber or fire a pistol. The breastplate (cuirass) wasn’t powerful enough to stop long arms fire but could defend against slashes, lance thrusts, and smaller-caliber gunfire. Cuirassiers were substitutes for the heavily armored knight, and they quickly assumed a ceremonial function, becoming prominent as royal guards or as part of the style-obsessed Napoleonic legions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MORTAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mortars were as simple as they were deadly. Unlike the rifled howitzer or other artillery, a mortar launched a bomb (stabilized with fins) in a high parabola toward a nearby target. Their accuracy depended on the calculation of trajectory, winds, and other battlefield conditions. Mortars primarily served to keep a besieged city in a constant state of fear or to rain destruction on a military camp. Artillery often accompanied a larger force, but mortars could be fired by a small squad and moved before a target retaliated.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MORTAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The concept has been used for centuries, most notably in medieval Korea. Since World War I, light hand-carried mortars or larger mechanized mortars have been deployed by both regular and irregular troops. In that conflict, mortars were especially feared, as shells could drop into trenches that were otherwise immune from line-of-sight rifle fire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_IRONCLAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The British Navy was the empire’s “wooden wall.” But what is more effective than a wooden wall? An iron one. Cladding naval warships in iron plates seemed ludicrous at first, but proved an effective defense against enemy fire. A classic matchup between ironclads was the 1862 battle between the Confederate Virginia (previously the Merrimack) and the Union Monitor at Hampton Roads, a body of water near Norfolk, Virginia. Both ships were anomalies – the triangular, turtle-like Confederate ship and the low-slung, almost submarine Monitor. Although the battle was indecisive, the duel showcased the ironclad’s power and durability, prompting the addition of Monitor-class ships to the United States fleet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_IRONCLAD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Ironclads flourished elsewhere in the late 1800s, including the Erzherzog Ferdinand Max of Austria, and the Re d’Italia of Italy, though neither shared the Monitor’s unusual profile (one that may have contributed to its sinking in poor weather). Ironclads suffered by being at the leading edge of technology; as soon as one was completed, a new metallurgical or engineering advance had already made it obsolete.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_FRIGATE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The frigate was the star of the Napoleonic Wars. A classic frigate had only one gun deck, but what it lacked in firepower it made up for in operational range. This benefit was especially valuable as frigates belonging to colonial powers were tasked with managing wars that could span the globe – all the more impressive for a sail-powered vessel. Most frigates had between 20 to 40 guns and could deliver a devastating broadside assault.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_FRIGATE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While classic frigates were light, some of the late-era ships were massive. The British navy found success with the Endymion-class frigates during the Napoleonic Wars. Meanwhile, the HDMS Jylland was a hulking 2500-ton hybrid steam and sailship launched by the Danish navy for use against Austrian and Prussian fleets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Tier 2-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_RIFLEMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Putting spin on a projectile allows it to fly straighter. This is true for everything, including bullets, arrows, and (American) footballs. But how does one spin a bullet? The answer lies in the spiral grooves inside a rifle's barrel. While musket balls often flew wildly, a spiraling rifle bullet could fly straighter and farther, allowing for entirely new kinds of warfare. The musket-toting line infantry, whose tactic was to advance as far as they dared before unleashing a deadly torrent of fire, was now vulnerable to concealed snipers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_RIFLEMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The first mass-produced rifles appeared on the American frontier in the 18th century and were increasingly used across the Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars. The development of breech-loading guns with encased cartridges in the later 19th century set the stage for subsequent phases of warfare, most notably in the deadly exchanges that began in the 20th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_FIELD_GUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Artillery changed warfare. Early bombards ended the dominance of castles across the medieval landscape, but Napoleonic generals took artillery seriously as a centerpiece of strategy and brought it onto the battlefield proper. The field cannon epitomized this shift – it could be relocated from place to place, allowing for strategic bombardment of enemy positions even as the enemy moved. The resulting barrage meant line infantry could be destroyed even before they had the opportunity to form.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LANDSHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Thanks to precision rifles and machine guns, seen enemies were soon dead enemies. As a result, by World War I, trench warfare dominated the field, and soldiers spent long periods hiding in fortifications only to spend a few terrifying seconds rushing across the field, trying to make it to the other side alive. The idea to bring the trench to the enemy led to the development of the landship – an early tank, mounted on treads (to roll over barbed wire and ditches) and designed to be a rolling fortification.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LANDSHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Landships came in a variety of shapes as militaries began to experiment with the possibilities. During the Battle of the Somme, the British were the first to deploy these vehicles in combat. They spread fear in the German ranks, at least at first. The Germans quickly learned to defeat a landship by hitting the machine in a vulnerable spot with an explosive charge. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LANDSHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But landships quickly evolved into the tanks of World War II.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HEAVY_ARTILLERY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The arms race between fortifications and artillery ended thanks to two major factors: airpower and heavy artillery. For its part, heavy artillery could throw explosive charges over fortifications, and it could do this over long distances. In fact, heavy artillery could dispense incredible destruction even when it was outside of the enemy's range of sight. This changed the nature of warfare, as mathematical calculations replaced a commander’s keen eye, and personal bravery mattered less than detailed trajectories. Howitzers were a key example of this trend; a howitzer charge, explosive and deadly, could be fired over most walls. The German “Big Bertha,” deployed during World War I, was notable as its shells could demolish the best star forts, and their explosions disrupted masonry protected by layers of earth. Even today, conventional artillery provides a constant threat in places like Seoul, where North Korean artillery could deal nearly as much damage as a nuclear attack. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CRUISER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A cruiser originally referred to a mission, not a ship. The mission was a long cruise (not the leisurely kind) on a ship powerful enough to deal with enemy threats. In the late 19th century, cruisers were distinguished as ships that were not entirely ironclad – their lighter design allowed them to travel longer distances (and still utilize wind power). Cruisers could engage enemy capital ships or raid enemy shipping lanes. Famous cruiser models included the HMS Dorsetshire, credited with the crippling of the massive Bismarck battleship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CRUISER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Cruisers were able to survive even while larger battleships were phased out, and they remain in use today, especially as platforms for missiles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DREADNOUGHT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The HMS Dreadnought was a British ship put to sea in 1906, a massive ironclad warship powered by a steam turbine and carrying a main battery of five 45-caliber naval guns. Revolutionary for its time, the vessel heralded the transition between ships of the line and the battleship. Similar dreadnought-style ships became the most feared vessels of World War I. In addition to their swift engines, dreadnoughts focused on large guns, emphasizing bombardment. Even before the heights of air power, dreadnoughts still had to fear underwater mines and early torpedo boats – simple craft outfitted with deadly torpedoes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BIPLANE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The World War II-era Spitfire and Zero receive much of the glory surrounding fighter aircraft. However, World War I also had its fair share of fighter craft. Most of these were biplanes – aircraft with two wings, similar to the Wright brothers’ original (though some had three, like the Fokker Triplane). The advantage of two wings was structural support, but the design created drag. This style of plane held two people: a pilot and someone who could fire a weapon. Handheld guns were not as useful as mounted guns, but mounted guns ran the risk of shredding the craft itself. This was especially problematic as the ideal place to mount a gun was right behind the propeller. The ingenious solution was to sync the firing of the gun with the turning of the propeller so bullets flew between the blades as they turned. Biplane dogfighting was made famous by the “Red Baron,” Manfred von Richthofen, a German fighter pilot during World War I who boasted over 80 planes shot down. However, once aluminum reached broad use, individual wings became stronger, and the biplane ended use.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TRENCH_FIGHTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Aircraft’s initial purpose in war was reconnaissance, but as war technology rapidly advanced during World War I, planes were developed for specialized tasks. Alongside the two-seater reconnaissance planes, the strategic bombers, and the air-to-air combat fighters came the need for attack aircraft to support infantrymen on the ground. These small craft called trench fighters could bombard with precision, strafe over trenches, and provide air-to-ground cover for advancing troops. Despite their speed and maneuverability, the early iterations of these aircraft encountered a loss rate of up to 30% due to their limited defensive protection and vulnerability to ground artillery. Even with such high losses, the effect of ground attack aircraft could turn the tide of battles, inflicting damage on morale and manpower alike.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>High ground has its advantages, as even Paleolithic tacticians understood. And what is higher than the sky? Early bombers were ordinary planes outfitted with pilots who could drop standard hand grenades. By 1913, these had evolved into aircraft with bombsights and salvos of up to a dozen bombs. The Germans loaded Zeppelins with bombs, allowing their ordinance to be dropped behind enemy lines at angles against which artillery struggled to defend. Bombers were especially important in attacking logistical lines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During World War II, bombers were vital elements of the military’s arsenal, and specialized bombers could launch torpedoes or unload heavy ordinance. Some bombers were dedicated to hitting enemy lines while others were equipped for enemy shipping lanes. As fighters proliferated, air combat modernized. The catastrophes of the Blitz, the destruction of Dresden, and the bombing of Tokyo all demonstrate the destructive capacity of airpower.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Tier 3-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_INFANTRY_COMPANY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The World Wars were infamous for pitting individuals against all the horrors of the modern era: bombers, artillery, poison gas, tanks. In open fields, machines had the upper hand, but many battles took place within urban zones or tricky terrain. Consider the battles of Berlin, Stalingrad, or the beaches of Normandy where the most maneuverable unit was an individual on foot. The classic infantry company was a group of soldiers with little more than their skin and wits to protect them from oncoming fire. Despite this, infantry were as well-provisioned and well-trained for warfare as anyone could be.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_AT_GUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tanks revolutionized the battlefield. Armored, mobile troop carriers and other cannons on wheels acted like mobile trenches, and stopping them was a desperate necessity. Tanks could resist rifle fire but direct artillery strikes could disable or destroy them. The first anti-tank guns were simply cannons turned to fire horizontally. After World War I, specialized guns for stopping tanks were developed, and they featured faster, more powerful projectiles to break through armor. As the world wrenched from war to war, tanks grew more and more protected, and anti-tank weapons grew increasingly specialized with shaped charges instead of regular shells to better penetrate tank armor and turn those mobile shells into stationary deathtraps.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TANK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>An outgrowth of the World War I-era landship, the tank proved vital during World War II. By this time, tanks retained the same basic design as a landship – treads and guns – but favored a single heavy cannon on a turret, supported by machine guns. The mobility of new tanks allowed divisions to quickly roll through enemy defenses – defined by the German Blitzkrieg, or “lightning war.” Tanks could bypass enemy strongholds to penetrate deep into enemy territory and isolate the fortifications; trenches would never return.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TANK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The rise of tanks was aided by industrialization and fed the rise of local industries – Sherman tanks were built in Detroit, Tiger tanks were built by Porsche, and the Japanese Chi-Ha was made by Mitsubishi. Indeed, the construction of heavy armor in World War II led to the rise of the industrial mega-corporations that were influential in the Cold War.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_ASSAULT_GUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Artillery remains vital to any military venture; much as the cannon ended the era of castles, artillery placed cities at risk. Artillery movement and setup are slow, but adding tank treads allowed for easier positioning. Assault guns were first deployed en masse during World War II. They provided direct fire (i.e. shooting straight at the enemy) and indirect fire (i.e. launching shells in a high arc into populated areas or fortifications) and soon became a core feature of German and Soviet armies. These weapons could also be easily converted into anti-tank machines, and the German Sturmgeschütz became the exemplar of this service.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DESTROYER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Consider the torpedo. A miniature, unmanned craft that could cruise under the water, out of gun range, and deliver a powerful explosive charge. A simple torpedo posed a threat to even the mightiest dreadnought. Before submarines, torpedoes were launched by small, swift torpedo boats, but these boats were often victims of the destroyer, a lighter craft created for escort duty. Over time, these escorts acquired torpedo tubes and became torpedo boats themselves.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DESTROYER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Destroyers excel in versatility, which has kept the model afloat even as heavier battleships have been decommissioned. They could operate alone for humanitarian matters or accompany larger fleets to handle more asymmetrical threats. These threats often came from submarines, so destroyers with depth charges were tasked with eliminating these unseen enemies before they surfaced. Significant destroyers included the French Fantasque, the Japanese Fubuki, and the first destroyer (built in 1893), the British Havock.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BATTLESHIP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Armed sailing ships were massive vessels with row upon row of cannons. Battleships were a 20th-century iteration – massive warships that could singlehandedly swing the fortunes of a naval war. 19th-century doctrine held that a single battleship could outclass a host of cruisers, destroyers, and other ships; the conflict between multiple battleships could decide the entire conflict. The height of the battleship era was World War II, but the end of their reign was written during the conflict. Battleships could outperform cruisers and other light warships, but they were severely challenged by the rise of torpedoes, submarines, and aircraft, demonstrated by the dramatic sinking of the Japanese battleship Yamato in 1945.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SUBMARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Objects under the surface of the sea are protected from the worst winds and weather – and they can move silently and unseen. Submarines are the ultimate naval assassin unit. They can bypass enemy blockades and polar ice caps and covertly strike merchant ships or deploy soldiers behind enemy lines.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SUBMARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Submarines are capable of submerging underwater and operating independently, in some cases, for months at a time. Early submarines were human-powered, including a Confederate sub armed with an explosive that sabotaged its target while sinking itself. Submarines were widely adopted during the two World Wars, especially the German U-boats that devastated Allied shipping lanes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_FIGHTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Aircraft were first deployed en masse in World War I, and could scout territory or drop bombs on enemy positions with relative ease. As bombers entered the fray so did the aircraft intended to stop them. Fighters were light, maneuverable planes designed for speed, and they were traditionally armed with lighter weapons intended to combat enemy aircraft – this meant machine guns, at least until rocketry. During World War II, the superstar fighter was the British Spitfire. Along with the less famous Hurricane, the Spitfire ended the German bombers' reign of terror on Britain. These fighters were also effective against the Japanese Zero, which was a remarkably light and maneuverable craft in its own right. Fighters remain in use today, though they have grown heavier and more complex – for example, the Soviet MiG-21 and American F-14. Thankfully those two craft never saw a great deal of action against each other.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DIVEBOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Heavy bombers are often wasteful – to destroy one ship, a heavy bomber might need to drop many tons of payload, spilling most of the explosives into the sea. This challenge is compounded by the fact that bombs dropped from a heavy bomber do not fall straight down, but continue in the plane’s trajectory until slowed down by air friction. Divebombers alleviate this challenge by driving straight at the target before deploying their payload.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DIVEBOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Pilots of these crafts needed strong nerves – and stomachs. Divebombers were primarily used during the two world wars, but rocketry heralded their decline as rockets offered greater accuracy and speed without risk to a pilot. If the tactical nuclear missile signaled the end of the heavy bomber, the cruise missile signaled the end of the divebomber.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HEAVY_BOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A heavy bomber's concept is simple: create a plane that can carry as much weight as possible, and make that weight bombs. Bombs dropped from aircraft do not need precision...as long as they destroy everything in sight. The first heavy bombers appeared during World War I, while air power was still in its infancy. Early bombers included the Soviet-built Sikorsky Ilya Muromets, which were biplanes with four engines. Years later, planes like the American B-17 Flying Fortress and the B-29 Superfortress participated in bombing runs at Dresden and Tokyo (Tokyo being the most destructive raid in history) and later dropped atomic bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HEAVY_BOMBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Before the age of the jet, bombers could compete with fighters. However, jet fighters, especially the Soviet MiG-15, were harder to outrun. On the other hand, by the time jet engines entered the fray, so had nuclear-tipped missiles. Bombers remained in use, but they were no longer the figurative tacnukes of war – not with real tacnukes in play.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civ Unique Military-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_ABAMBOWA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The guards to the kabaka, the king of Buganda, the Abambowa are an elite group of warriors and caretakers, close to the heart of Gandan rule. Ganda's kingship has a dual nature: a sacred monarchy is represented by regalia while other sources of divine power have their emissary (the word kabaka means emissary) in the body of an individual. The king’s body is sacrosanct, and outsiders are generally not permitted near them, so the Abambowa are a line of defense between the world and the monarchy. Abambowa adhere to a strict code of conduct, abstaining from food and drink before their shifts so they will not have to use the toilet on duty. More to the point, they are equipped with a set of ceremonial equipment: a spear (now a gun), a shield, a machete, and a length of rope for securing potential captives.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CHANG_BEUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the medieval and early modern periods, a Siamese war elephant (a yuthahathi) was a royal steed, intended to carry knights and lords into pike duels with other kings. However, after the advent of guns, the elephant became a tank. Rather than using the archaic term “yuthahathi,” we have translated “machine gun elephant” as simply “gun [carrying] elephant,” or “chang beun.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CHANG_BEUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Howdah-mounted swivel guns, weighing 50-100kg, were a feature of the Thai/Burmese wars of the early modern era. Elephants retained some advantage over motorized tanks, as they could move more quietly through jungle and across rivers. These massive animals could also withstand bullets that horses and other living mounts could not. As such, they were deployed in conflicts that required mobility across difficult terrain, such as the Haw Wars (1865-1890). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_COSSACK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word “Cossack” comes from the Turkic term “kazak,” meaning “free man.” Cossack refers to a people of the steppe of Ukraine and Russia – a people with their own (often democratic) traditions who live independently of the regimes usually imposed by Russian tsars. The Russian Empire (as well as the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth) permitted Cossacks to retain their traditional way of life in exchange for military service, and they were renowned for their skill on horseback.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_COSSACK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Expansionist Russian designs often clashed with independent-minded Cossack groups, leading to the development of a special class for Cossacks: a “sosloviye,” or “military class." In the field, the Cossacks were a feared element of imperial armies, most notably in the Russian Revolution against the Bolsheviks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_GARDE_IMPERIALE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Napoleon’s elite troops formed the Garde Impériale, or Imperial Guard, which was under his direct command. The Imperial Guard was not a particular troop class, but represented the best of the infantry, cavalry, and artillery available to the French army; this included dragoons, grenadiers, and even mamluks from Napoleon’s Arabian possessions. In total, the Imperial Guard numbered somewhere between the low thousands to 100,000 men. The Old Guard, or “grognards” [grumblers], were Napoleon’s favorites, but the Garde Impériale ceased when Napoleon’s empire fell and their leader was sent into exile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HUSSAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Friedrich the Great is famous for thinking holistically about battle. Rows of soldiers positioned to withstand enemy fire are well and good, but those warriors must first travel to the front lines and their morale depends on a full belly as much as an inspirational speech. As the Prussians understood, logistics are key to victory – and destroying the enemy’s plans is equally important. Hussars were lightly armored rapid cavalry bearing pistols, sabers, and lances, and they were masters of disrupting enemies through raids.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HUSSAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As befits their swashbuckling image, hussars were often dressed in elaborate uniforms. The Prussian hussars sported a skull and crossbones motif – an image that would later be re-used in the German empire to terrifying effect. Friedrich formed the first of these regiments, dressed all in black, and this uniform was in use throughout the Napoleonic Wars and into the trenches of World War I.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_GUSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Numbers can be misleading. The Qing's so-called Eight Banners (or “gusa”) were actually twenty-four: eight for each of the Manchu, Han, and Mongol cohorts. Scholars estimate that a single gusa comprised about 18,000 troops and their families, but exact numbers remain unknown as records were kept hidden, likely for security reasons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_GUSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The gusa were more than military entities and represented an entire segment of Qing society, maintaining their own social and administrative customs. Membership in the gusa was hereditary, and service to one of the Eight Banners dictated one's ethnicity – for instance, a large group of Han bannermen transferred to the Manchu ranks became Manchu.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_GUSA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Though modernization and westernization eventually rendered the gusa obsolete, for a time they were the might and pride of the Qing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_KATYUSHA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Long-range artillery has a few inherent problems. Over long distances, rockets run a very real chance of missing their target (without modern guidance systems). The Soviet solution to this problem was simple – why fire one rocket when you can fire 48? The Katyusha was a system of rails mounted on the back of a truck and loaded with rockets that could be fired in a single horrific salvo. While the Katyusha took more time to reload, its series of launchers could obliterate its target – and anything remotely close to it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_KATYUSHA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>German and Finnish troops referred to the Katyusha as “Stalin’s organ,” which wasn't a reference to the rocket’s shape, but to the howl the missiles made as they were fired, an unearthly, siren-like whistle that preceded a hellish bombardment. Katyusha systems remain in use in Africa and the Middle East.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Put simply, marines are land combat units deployed at sea for use in amphibious invasions (or to seize other ships). Until large cannons were deployed on ships, most naval combat was performed by the ancient equivalent of marines – navy ships from Rome to Majapahit to the Chola would close in on their enemy, and soldiers would attempt to board and capture the other vessel. In this sense, ships are merely a means of transport; later innovations in naval technology were needed for ship-to-ship combat (Greek fire and other such weapons were outliers).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>However, marines are not simply ship-to-ship fighters. They became vital as an advance force for major wars, especially those overseas where forces could establish a foothold on an enemy coast and pave the way for a larger army invasion. In World War II, the United States Marine Corps was crucial in securing sites in battles such as Normandy and Iwo Jima. These kinds of invasions were especially crucial when air power entered the picture – a rapid, amphibious force can seize an airfield, which in turn offers support for a greater advance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MIKASA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Japan’s industrialization was meteoric. In 1867, Edo Japan was a prosperous but isolated society, shunning foreign influence in favor of its own order. In the following years, the Meiji regime launched an ambitious plan to shape Japan into one of the world’s leading industrial, and colonial, powers. Modernizing Japan’s military was an essential goal, and the development of warships that could compete with those of the West was key.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MIKASA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the Russo-Japanese War of 1904-5, a pre-dreadnaught battleship called the Mikasa was the flagship of the imperial fleet. She was constructed in the United Kingdom, housed nearly a thousand crew members, sported four 40-caliber twelve-inch guns, and featured an array of smaller armament. The Mikasa sank when her magazine exploded after the end of the conflict, but she was refloated the following year and continued to serve in subsequent wars until decommissioned in 1923.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SEPOY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The name “sepoy” initially referred to infantrymen in the Mughal Empire, armed with muskets and daggers, but through usage by the British East India Company, the term came to broadly refer to Indian soldiers under its employ. Sepoys were generally of low rank but were well-paid and trained in the arms they used.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SEPOY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1857, numerous sepoys (and other Indians) rose against the British East India Company. This rebellion came about as the Company sought to expand its ranks – local recruits vastly outnumbered the British, and the Company had largely recruited from upper-caste and well-remunerated locals (especially from Bengal). Integrating these units proved costly as higher-caste sepoys were granted separate dining facilities and exemption from fighting far from home. As the Company began to falter, it revoked many of these privileges and leaned on local troops. As missionaries became more and more visible, rumors abounded that the British were out to undermine Indian religion, both Hindu and Muslim. Finally, more rumors arose that the new Enfield rifle had charges laced with animal fat, which seemed to confirm the Company’s hostility to local beliefs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SEPOY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the wake of the rebellion, Britain took direct control over the Company’s possessions, citing mismanagement of public opinion as well as the exploitation of India for profit (but those practices didn't change much under the new regime).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SOLDADERAS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mexican Revolution was a decade-long conflict between multiple power groups, beginning with the collapse of the dictatorship of Porfirio Díaz. In 1911, Díaz had jailed a prominent opponent, a wealthy landowner from the north of Mexico who had launched a rebellion against Díaz and his “Porfiriato” – and won. This sparked a series of rebellions, reactions, coups, and attempted coups that eventually settled into a period of stability that has lasted from 1920 to the present day.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SOLDADERAS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Female soldiers and army attendants, or soldaderas, played a key role in these conflicts. These varied across different armies and theaters of the revolution, from bands of female soldiers to camp followers to the wives and children of soldiers, thus increasing cohesion – and the humaneness – of soldiers in a chaotic battlefield. Famous soldaderas of the southern revolutionaries included Petra Herrera (a soldier in Pancho Villa’s army) and Ángela Jiménez (a master of demolitions).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_STUKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The German Junkers Ju 87 or "Stuka" was a ground-attack aircraft deployed in World War II, and was primarily used to disrupt shipping during the first few years of the conflict. The Stuka was designed to drop bombs as it dove toward the ground at an incredible velocity; it even included automatic recovery systems in case the pilot blacked out. Imagine the shock of a Stuka strike – its sirens blaring as it descends hundreds of feet in seconds, pulling away at the last minute. It would have been a terrifying strike for both pilot and target alike.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_STUKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>That steep, precipitous drop revealed a vulnerability within the Stuka design. Heavy bombers flew at a high altitude with a contingent of protective fighters; what they lacked in accuracy they made up for in relative pilot safety. However, hitting specific targets forced pilots to leave this formation and rendered them vulnerable to the increasingly sophisticated fighters of the era. By the end of the war, the era of dogfighting and dive-bombing was replaced by rockets and remote artillery – ominous signs for the ICBM arms race to come.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_ZERO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mitsubishi A6M was a light, maneuverable fighter aircraft. It was named the reisen or Zero after the imperial year of its manufacture (2600, or 1940 in the Gregorian calendar). Japan's demands for the Zero were extreme: it had to be small enough to fit onto a carrier, durable enough to fly for eight hours, armed well enough to pose a threat, and fast enough to be effective. Mitsubishi achieved this by incorporating new forms of aluminum and stripping the craft of everything that would weigh it down.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_ZERO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thanks to its range and handling, it dominated the Pacific skies during the early part of World War II. Notably, the Zero could drop to speeds of 69 mph without stalling, giving it a tight turn radius in comparison to Allied craft of the time. However, as the war progressed, the Zero grew increasingly outdated and, by the end of the war, carried doomed kamikaze fighters into their last spiral.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_PARTISAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The art of warfare is not solely reliant on combat between national military forces but often employs irregulars. Of these, partisans play a crucial role in the defense of the homeland. These forces are recruited or formed from civilian populations and are most commonly associated with the resistance movements of World War II.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_PARTISAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Partisan warfare typically takes two forms: guerrilla and covert operations. Because partisan troops are typically local to the regions in which they fight, their familiarity with the terrain makes them ideal for surprise attacks and acts of sabotage. In populated areas, covert tactics expand beyond direct combat to include espionage and subversion through rumors and news sources in order to undermine the enemy presence and strengthen the national armed forces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civ Unique Civilian-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_JACOBIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Jacobins were the most prominent political group during the French Revolution. Founded in 1789 as the Club Breton, the group originally organized to discuss issues relating to Brittany's Third Estate (the common people). These conversations quickly began to include neighboring provinces, and the club evolved into the Société des Amis de la Constitution (Society of the Friends of the Constitution), nicknamed the Jacobin Club.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_JACOBIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>After relocating to Paris, membership grew rapidly as France's political situation heated up. The club initially aimed to defend the rights of the French people, but inner divisions over loyalty to the king resulted in a member exodus. Maximilien Robespierre led those who remained to increasing radicalization, and they soon took a leading role in the French Revolution and the ensuing Reign of Terror. Although the Jacobin Club was officially closed in 1794 after the fall of Robespierre, its ideals survived in contemporary movements across Europe, and its role in the French Revolution marks a turning point in political philosophy in the Western world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MWAMI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The mwami (plural baami) was a chief in Baganda society. Traditionally, they were local administrators. The mwami’s duties included organizing labor for agriculture or building projects, leading religious rituals, and resolving issues within his community. These tasks were performed in exchange for tribute, forming strong social bonds based on reciprocity. While baami had individual connections anchoring them to specific ancestral sites, their territory was largely dictated by where their population lived. If their people moved or migrated, the mwami’s control over the land moved with them. People could switch their allegiance to another mwami at any time, either by relocating or forming a relationship with a new chief.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_REVOLUCIONARIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Two major internal conflicts shaped the history of modern Mexico – the Mexican War of Independence (1810-1821) and the Mexican Revolution (1910-1920). In both cases, revolucionario (revolutionaries) arose to challenge a status quo they felt was holding back the nation, and they claimed power to change the course of its future.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_REVOLUCIONARIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>After three hundred years of Spanish rule, the War of Independence emerged from several armed conflicts across the country. The Napoleonic Wars had weakened Spain, and growing national identity across Mexico came to a head with a widespread but unsuccessful revolt in 1810. This uprising was quickly put down, but the sentiments of its leader, Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla, inspired the population toward additional acts of protest and violence, resulting in an alliance between two leading forces in 1821. This force finally overcame the colonial Spanish government and heralded the founding of independent Mexico.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_REVOLUCIONARIO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>One century later, revolution ignited once more, this time against the dictatorial rule of Porfirio Díaz. Although Díaz soon went into exile, the ensuing decade saw several presidents acquire and lose power as the country was engulfed with conflict over political, social, and economic factors, including redistribution of land among the peasant class and expanded rights for indigenous populations. While the war ended in 1920, conflict continued on for years as factions sought to secure the Revolution’s central goals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_UPARAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Siamese uparat was a viceroy, second in command of the state and presumptive heir to the throne. The tradition has a long history. Imported from India, the position was first employed during the 15th century. When Prince Naresuan was appointed uparat by his father, the king built him a palace in front of his own; therefore the role of uparat has come to be called Wang Na (Front Palace). However, the role of uparat was commonly held by the king's brother, who functioned as the presumed heir (sometimes co-ruler) until the king bore a son.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_UPARAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In modern Siam, the position became more powerful, with uparats commanding their own military forces. In 1874-1875, tension between the king and the Front Palace escalated into a brief armed crisis that resulted in the abolition of the uparat position entirely. It was replaced by the role of Crown Prince.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HANGSHANG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Beginning in the 1760s, the city of Canton was the gateway for trade between China and the world. International trade was exclusive to its port, limiting visitors’ access to the empire proper. The “Canton System” permitted only one group of merchants to conduct trade on behalf of the Qing: the Hangshang. These independent merchants, also known as the Cohong, only dealt with other independent trading companies representing Western interests. In this way, the Chinese and European governments benefitted from the exchange of tea, porcelain, silk, and silver without direct contact. The Hangshang were often forced to offer bribes and gifts to the government agents who managed them. Even so, they benefitted immensely from their monopoly on international trade; despite the low status of merchants in the Confucian worldview, they quickly became some of the wealthiest people in China.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_PROSPECTOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>On January 24, 1848, gold was discovered in Coloma, California. Over the following years, over 300,000 people raced to the Pacific Coast in the hopes of pulling immense wealth from the earth. These Gold Rush prospectors largely relied on panning to uncover flakes and nuggets that were carried out of their original deposits by streams and rivers. More ambitious prospectors diverted these waters to search the beds directly or dug shafts into the banks looking for paydirt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_PROSPECTOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Life as a prospector was far from easy. The work was physically taxing, often involving over 12 hours of back-breaking labor each day. Mining camps were remote and typically lacked sanitation and proper housing, allowing disease to run rampant. Due to the money at stake, trust was hard to come by, and violence was common in these temporary communities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_PROSPECTOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The allure of gold ultimately outlasted its prevalence. Early prospectors hauled away much of the easily found metal, and as more and more people crowded the rivers and mountains, many left empty-handed. The immense influx of migrants catalyzed the exponential growth of nearby cities and allowed California to quickly establish itself as the 31st state in the U.S. in 1850.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_ZAMINDAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mughals ruled over a diverse population, in language, religion, caste, but also in administrative styles. In some regions, Mughal rulers took over princely states ruled by their own raja, in others, Mughal leaders appointed rulers to take charge of particular areas. These were all categorized by the Persian word “zamindar”, or estate-holder. While in practice zamindars formed a network of wealthy and well-connected local families, especially in North India, in theory many zamindars could be appointed and recalled at the behest of the Mughal state – a classic feature of bureaucratic monarchies. Zamindar rule was appropriated by the British Raj after the Mughals, and only dissolved in the middle of the 20th century. The families, though, remained influential as powerful local elites.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CARRIER_COMMANDER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In 1843 hot air balloons rose from the decks of the SMS Vulcano, a steamer in the service of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. These balloons were loaded with bombs intended for Venice, which had rebelled. This was the first recorded combination of air power and sea power, but it would not be the last. Fixed-wing aircraft took off from naval vessels in World War I, but became decisive in World War II, as ships such as the Enterprise and Saratoga show. Just as flight radically changed land warfare, in one step overcoming trenches and walls, so, too the aircraft carrier ended the supremacy of the battleship. But they are expensive: owing to the necessity of landing and deploying aircraft from their decks, carriers are the largest naval vessels afloat today.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>