<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>At the end of the 15th century, Morocco was undergoing tumultuous change. The Marinid dynasty, one of several Berber empires that rose in North Africa in the wake of the Islamic caliphates, had controlled much of the western edge of the Maghreb for two centuries. By the 1470s, they were replaced by the Wattasid dynasty. But Morocco was stumbling. The Portuguese, seeking control of Gibraltar and a sea route around Africa, captured many coastal settlements, curtailing trade opportunities, while decades of chaos had undermined the economic and cultural prosperity of the region. In 1492, the Emirate of Granada fell to Catholic Spain, ending the Reconquista and dealing a further blow to Muslim power in North Africa.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1471, a kasbah was founded at Chefchaouen by Ali ibn Rashid al-Alami, a former soldier who had fought in Granada during the Reconquista. The settlement quickly attracted exiles from Granada as the Emirate fell, and grew into a thriving city. Located inland from the northern coast near Gibraltar, Chefchaouen was in a prime position to challenge the Portuguese. The city was home to both local resistance fighters knowledgeable in mountainous terrain and exiles from Granada who arrived with expertise in coastal defense. Under the governance of al-Alami, this influx of Granadans imbued Chefchaouen with a mixture of Andalusian and Moroccan culture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Al-Alami’s daughter, born sometime between 1491 and 1495, grew up between these two traditions. Her real name is disputed in the sources, but she came to be known as Sayyida al Hurra, the “Noble Lady.” Her childhood was stable, and she received a thorough education from some of Granada’s finest scholars. In 1510, she married Sidi al-Mandri II, ruler of Tétouan. This city, north of Chefchaouen, presided over a critical stretch of coastline. By the 14th century, it had become a haven for pirates and was destroyed twice by Iberian powers, first by Castille in 1399, then by the Portuguese in 1426. After the fall of Granada, Sidi al-Mandri’s uncle, Ali al-Mandri, and his followers settled in the city’s ruins and began to rebuild. These efforts were aided by al-Alami of nearby Chefchaouen, forging a close alliance between the two men and their respective cities that was further strengthened by the interfamilial marriage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Sayyida al Hurra seems to have begun her political career during her marriage to al-Mandri. Tensions were high between Tétouan and nearby Ceuta, a Portuguese stronghold along the Strait of Gibraltar. Al-Mandri appears to have entrusted his wife with a prominent voice in his government, and for good reason. In addition to her powerful familial connections, she had grown up watching her father rule Chefchaouen, and her education included proficiency in Portuguese and Spanish. During their marriage, she may have ruled the city in her husband’s stead when he was away traveling.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Upon al-Mandri’s death in 1515 (or 1519), Sayyida al Hurra became the sole and undisputed ruler of Tétouan. During this period, she received the moniker “al Hurra,” a title given to women in power across the Islamic world. As Tétouan’s governor, she inherited the responsibilities of not only fostering the city’s continued rebirth, but also the ongoing struggle against Portugal and Spain. These relations were always fraught, and European sources portray her as a clever and well-respected diplomat, though at times verbally aggressive with Ceuta’s Portuguese ruler.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Sayyida al Hurra’s most famous claim to fame today is her association with pirates. Despite Tétouan’s local strength as a city-state, the population was still small, unable to field a large army or navy. Moreover, Iberian dominance of the coast had left the Moroccan resistance disadvantaged in naval conflict, especially when faced with large European fleets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>However, there was another strong naval power in the region – the Barbary corsairs. These pirates emerged from North Africa during the Middle Ages, but they became far more organized and dangerous by the end of the 15th century, a rise accelerated by the expansion of the Ottoman Empire. The Ottomans had claimed the caliphate title as the leader of the Islamic world, while Spain had positioned itself as the leader of the Christian world. The two powers clashed vehemently during this era, particularly through naval conflict in the Mediterranean. Although the Barbary corsairs were a multinational community, their operations were based in Ottoman territories, and they became increasingly associated with the empire. Overlap between the corsairs and the Ottoman navy was not unusual – some pirates served as privateers, while others eventually joined the navy as officers. And their attacks on Iberian ships and settlements also found them fighting side by side with local North African populations struggling against the same enemies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Alliances between Sayyida al Hurra and the Barbary corsairs were mutually beneficial. Sayyida al Hurra gained a stronger military presence in the area as well as greater control of the surrounding sea; importantly, Tétouan also benefited economically from corsair raids on merchant ships. Meanwhile, Tétouan was one of the only ports in Morocco that remained independent of Portugal or Spain, making it a safe harbor in the western Mediterranean for pirates restocking their ships or launching attacks. Her most famous associate was Hayreddin Barbarossa, a powerful Ottoman pirate who later became a naval admiral.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Sayyida al Hurra ruled Tétouan alone for over two decades before she remarried, this time to Sultan Ahmed al-Wattassi in 1541. The Sultanate was based in Fez, but on her demand, the ceremony took place in Tétouan – this was the only time a Moroccan sultan married outside of his capital, a testament to Sayyida al Hurra’s power and the respect she commanded. The marriage seems to have been primarily political in nature, adding royal legitimacy to her authority while allowing the Wattasid dynasty to consolidate power in the north. After the ceremony, Ahmed al-Wattassi returned to Fez, leaving Sayyida al Hurra to continue her solo reign.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_SAYYIDA_AL_HURRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>But the Wattasid dynasty was in decline, and the marriage was not enough to preserve her power. Only a year later, in 1542, Sayyida al Hurra’s son-in-law from her first marriage seized Tétouan and exiled her. She returned to her hometown Chefchaouen, where she led a quiet life until her death in 1552.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>