<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_TONGA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The history of Tonga is long and remarkable, and also largely hidden in the mists of time. Much of Tonga’s story is accessible only through archaeology and oral tales; written sources start very late, with the arrival of Europeans in the 17th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tonga’s first inhabitants landed on its shores around 3200 years ago, c. 1000 BCE. These were the Lapita people, originally from Southeast Asia, talented navigators who rapidly spread across the Pacific. Their presence is marked largely by the remains of their distinctive pottery, mostly cooking and storage containers, featuring ornate repeating geometric designs. However, within two centuries they had ceased to decorate their pottery – the reason for this sudden shift is unknown.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The subsequent Plainware Period (700 BCE-400 CE) saw the transition to a permanent Polynesian society in Tonga. While the first generations of Lapita settlers lived along the coast and relied almost entirely on the ocean for food and livelihoods, the Plainware people moved inland, establishing farms and plantations and raising livestock. But around 400 CE, another unexplained shift occurred – Tongans stopped producing pottery altogether, again for unknown reasons. The absence of pottery and other archaeological evidence lasted for several centuries, and very little is known about what occurred during this Dark Age. However, society persisted, continuing to develop and grow, and around 950 CE, the Tu'i Tonga clan started to consolidate power on the island of Tongatapu.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>According to legend, the Tu'i Tonga (“kings of Tonga”) were descended from the half-divine 'Aho'eitu, son of the god 'Eitumātupu'a and the mortal woman 'Ilaheva. This sacred provenance placed them above their predecessors, and over the following centuries, the Tu'i Tonga expanded their power into a maritime empire. Male relatives of the royal family were sent to neighboring islands to bring them under their control, and therefore the control of the Tu'i Tonga, through conquest or marriage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The challenge of maintaining cohesive rule over an empire of oceanic islands required innovative ways of thinking about empire. Direct rule was not possible, but the ships of the Tu'i Tonga were capable of making regular journeys between islands, keeping them in dialogue with one another. The reach of the Tu'i Tonga created avenues for widespread trade, both within its domain and to other Pacific island kingdoms beyond. The divine origins of the Tu'i Tonga and associated beliefs and practices were also central to maintaining power. The king held a deep connection with the earth, and its fertility was assumed to come from him. In order to ensure his favor, all islands submitted a tribute of the first harvest ('inasi), in exchange for which the Tu'i Tonga would grace them with good weather and fertile soil so that the next harvest would also be successful.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The sacred nature of the king extended to his physical body. Anything that touched him, including food, became sacrosanct (tapu), and direct contact with his body by others was limited. His hair could not be cut, and any tattooing had to take place in Samoa, as the Samoans were exempt from the tapu by which Tongans abided (although, according to one account, they could still die from proximity to the king). The Tu'i Tonga was served by matāpules, spokesmen who mediated his interactions with the world and who were often foreigners in the early centuries, for the same reason as above – as non-Tongans, they were immune to some of the tapu surrounding the king’s divinity. The matāpule was not a political advisor, but directed the court on a daily and ceremonial basis, such as arranging and leading kava ceremonies. He was also a companion to the king, who was otherwise isolated from the rest of the world, and engaged with him in ways others were not permitted, such as eating together.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>The Tu'i Tonga reached their height in the 13th century with the advent of the Monument Building period. During this era, their power and population ascended to the point of building monumental structures, many of which are still visible in the landscape today. Mounds were built in earnest for varying purposes – some were mounds where chiefs would sit ('esi), some were burial mounds (langi), and some were used for the royal sport of pigeon-snaring (sia heu lupe). Vaikaukau, conical manmade wells, were constructed nearby as sacred bathing spaces reserved for the king. The famous trilithon Ha'amonga 'a Maui was also erected during this period by Tu'i-tā-tui, the 11th Tu'i Tonga, as was the nearby royal throne, Maka Fa'akinanga. These monuments required significant infrastructure, both in the manpower and organization required to construct them and the social order in which they played an important role, particularly for kings and chiefs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_TONGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>By the 15th century, internal and external strife began eating away at the power of the Tu'i Tonga. Following the assassination of the 23rd Tu'i Tonga, Takalaua, his successor Kau'ulufonua created a diarchy, with the Tu'i Tonga led by himself and a new dynasty, the Tu'i Ha'atakalaua, led by his brother Mo'ungāmotu'a. Under this model, the Tu'i Ha'atakalaua took over political control of the empire while the Tu'i Tonga remained the spiritual power. Samoa became increasingly influential in the governance of Tonga, intermarrying with the Tu'i Tonga and establishing a new role, the falefā, to advise and influence rulers on political matters. Another administrative division two centuries later saw the Tu'i Ha'atakalaua submit to the junior Tu'i Kanokupolu dynasty. Europeans first arrived in Tonga in 1616, and the Tu'i Tonga line ended in 1865.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Constructibles-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_TOFI_A_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tongan society was organized according to a complex hierarchy and ranking system. Arable and hospitable land was owned by the king who granted some portions of it to his chiefs. Those chiefs in turn granted parcels to their kinsmen and loyal subjects. The chief's estate, the tofi'a, would often have his own areas for bathing, for hunting pigeons, for cooking, and an area close by for his attendants and their families. The common folk who lived and worked the rest of the chief's land would provide a portion of the food and other products from the land to him. In turn, the chief would send on gifts to the Tu'i Tonga. This network of relationships and tribute created a stable system of rule for the large area that the Tongans controlled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_TOFI_A_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In modern times, land ownership is determined by the Constitution and titles are granted only by succession or directly from the king. These titles grant a tofi'a which the noble can parcel out to men without titles who then pay a rent on the land. Rather than a complex system of kinship and mutual exchange, modern Tongan society is changing into one determined more by class and education.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LANGI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>There are at least 22 known burial mounds, or "langi," around Lapaha, the ancient capital of the Tongan Empire, though oral records tell of 45 sites throughout the Kingdom. Each one of the massive tombs was created to serve as the burial place for one of the Tongan kings or his family members. The practice continued from the mid 14th century through the 18th century, and still today, local Tongan families keep oral histories of who is buried in the langi and follow traditions of caring for the sites.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LANGI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Langi appear today as large mounds, vaguely rectangular in shape, bordered by tiered beach rock. To build the langi, workers would have had to excavate the limestone and coral from quarries either on the coast or on a nearby island. Tales tell of workers using large canoes to transport the giant stones to the site of the tombs. The stone slabs were fitted end to end and joined at the corners to enclose a platform of earth. Multiple stepped layers form what look like the base of an earthen pyramid lined with stone.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_VAI_KAUKAU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Tu'i Tonga and his chiefs were considered sacred in many ways. To avoid the pollution associated with a common person touching or viewing a chiefly person in an incorrect way, high-ranked individuals like chiefs had separate bathing areas called the vaikaukau. Chiefs and the Tu'i Tonga bathed in wells or cisterns that were dug by their subjects for this purpose. While some chiefs may have allowed their attendants to also use the bathing pools, a commoner who did so would be expected to get sick and even die due to the tapu nature of the chief’s water.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_VAI_KAUKAU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Many of these wells still exist across the Tongan landscape, several of which are known to have belonged to the Tu'i Tonga. Occasionally, he and his chiefs would bathe together and be entertained by a duel to the death between two men fighting near the pools. One of the extant wells is named Hoaheu in reference to this activity meaning "a pair (of men) warding off blows." Other pools are named for the nearby pigeon mounds where the chief's men would catch pigeons to bring home. The people would dress and cook the birds in coconut milk, providing a meal for the community before leaving the chief and his attendants to bathe and retire for the night.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civics-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_TONGA_LAPITA_ORIGINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Archaeological evidence shows signs of the Tongan islands being colonized no later than 1000 BCE. The early settlers were part of a community known as the Lapita cultural complex, a group of Neolithic Austronesian peoples who settled much of Oceania. They developed a robust system of maritime trade across Polynesia, trading their unique style of pottery marked by a signature geometric pattern. They primarily settled on coastlines though over time, we see settlements move inland and agriculture become more important.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_TONGA_LAPITA_ORIGINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>A few hundred years later their unique pottery had disappeared. Though the Tongan islands remained inhabited, pottery production ceased completely by 400 CE for unknown reasons and never returned. Later, during the time of the Tongan maritime empire, a new form of tradecraft developed – ngatu, decorated bark cloth, also known as “tapa cloth,” made from the mulberry tree. Pieces of bark are flattened with a mallet and joined together to create a fabric. In the past, ngatu was used for clothing as well as ceremonial purposes, with the latter being beautifully decorated with imagery of fauna and flora. Today, Tongans use ngatu in weddings, funerals, and other important cultural events.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_TONGA_ESI_MAKA_FAAKINANGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Near the Ha'amonga 'a Maui stands a tall and wide stone made of coral and limestone named the 'Esi Maka Faakinanga, or “stone to lean against.” It dates from the same period as the Ha'amonga 'a Maui stones, constructed in the 13th century by the 11th Tu'i Tonga. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_TONGA_ESI_MAKA_FAAKINANGA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The stone is said to have been the king’s throne though it is purely vertical and he would have sat in front of it rather than atop it. Tu'i-tā-tui, the king credited with constructing these monuments, is said to have been very tall, over seven feet, and could stand with his back to this stone, protecting himself from any assassins. From this location, one has a beautiful and far-reaching view of the island, allowing the king to see anyone approaching him far in advance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_TONGA_KAVA_CEREMONY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Kava, a mild intoxicant made from the kava plant, is a significant element in past and current Tongan society. When the Tu'i Tonga returned from a voyage, gained new territory and subjects, or died, a grand Taumafa Kava or Royal Kava ceremony would be held. Strict lines of hierarchical rank were respected, with an inner circle of the highest ranking individuals seated in the center of the ceremony, with the king at its head. Beyond the inner circle is a much larger outer circle where the commoners would observe. The ceremony signifies the responsibilities that the nobility and the people have to each other – the king and chiefs protecting the people, the people providing for and serving the king and elites. Smaller kava ceremonies were also important in the daily life of Tongan society. With no structured judicial system, a king or chief would hold a daily audience with kava where his attendants and family heads from his subjects would raise any concerns. Today, the Taumafa Kava is still important for the succession of kings, and kava drinking is a regular pastime for Tongan men.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_TONGA_KAVA_CEREMONY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Kava features in the origin myth of the Tongan kings and their sacred nature. As the story goes, a young man named 'Aho'eitu, son of a mortal woman and a god, left home to seek his father. He climbed a giant tree up to the sky realm of the gods where he met his father and a host of older brothers. They played and competed in a variety of sports, and quickly 'Aho'eitu proved to be the favorite. Jealous, his brothers murdered him, throwing his head into the bushes, and cooking his body to eat. When their father asked after 'Aho'eitu, he realized what the brothers had done. Calling for a great kava bowl, he forced the brothers to vomit up 'Aho'eitu into the bowl and to place his head in as well. The bowl was covered and left overnight; in the morning, 'Aho'eitu had miraculously come back to life, revitalized in the kava. His father sent him back to earth to rule as the Tu'i Tonga, a demigod, forever straddling the line between life and death.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_CIVILIAN-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TEHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Tongan society was a complex network of rank and status dependent on sibling and marriage relationships. Polygamy and divorce were common, so kinship lines could result in heavy competition for land and influence. A tehina, or "younger brother," was often such a man, possibly an actual brother but perhaps a cousin or other close kinsman. The Tu'i Tonga would send these men out to other islands with the task to find a wife, marry into the local governance structure, and absorb the territory into the greater range of the Tu'i Tonga's rule. The chief would supply the tehina with the ships and warriors possibly needed for the expedition, but it was up to the tehina himself to acquire a wife of high rank and build a network of support in the new area.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TEHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>A successful tehina would wrap his new territory into the system of 'inasi, or "tribute," that bound the Tongan maritime empire together. As a new de facto chief, his subjects were responsible for providing a portion of the land's product to him, and from him, on to the Tu'i Tonga in the center. In this way, the periphery continually expanded, and the network of kinship and exchange bound the center to the outward islands in what was a stable and lasting arrangement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_KALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The kalia is a double-hulled canoe with large triangular sails similar to the drua of other Polynesian peoples. It developed from an earlier double-hulled vessel called the “tongiaki” which was similar to a catamaran. Kalia served two primary purposes in Tongan society – warfare and the transportation of goods. A kalia could hold dozens of men as well as carry food and prestige items from the periphery to the center, thus playing an important role in symbolizing the power of the king. Tongan navigators were a special class of people, valued for their expertise, and employed directly by the king or his chiefs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_KALIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It could take up to seven years to build a kalia, and the need for wood in their construction led Tongans to develop trade with the Fiji islands where lumber was more available. Tongan shipbuilders would establish outposts in Fiji, eventually developing into full settlements. Though it seems that Tongans originally acquired kalia by winning them from Fiji in warfare, Tongans came to hold a monopoly on their construction and use. No kalia would sail without a Tongan navigator and no resident of Fiji could visit Tonga except by kalia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_KALIA_2_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The kalia is a double-hulled canoe with large triangular sails similar to the drua of other Polynesian peoples. It developed from an earlier double-hulled vessel called the “tongiaki” which was similar to a catamaran. Kalia served two primary purposes in Tongan society – warfare and the transportation of goods. A kalia could hold dozens of men as well as carry food and prestige items from the periphery to the center, thus playing an important role in symbolizing the power of the king. Tongan navigators were a special class of people, valued for their expertise, and employed directly by the king or his chiefs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_KALIA_2_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It could take up to seven years to build a kalia, and the need for wood in their construction led Tongans to develop trade with the Fiji islands where lumber was more available. Tongan shipbuilders would establish outposts in Fiji, eventually developing into full settlements. Though it seems that Tongans originally acquired kalia by winning them from Fiji in warfare, Tongans came to hold a monopoly on their construction and use. No kalia would sail without a Tongan navigator and no resident of Fiji could visit Tonga except by kalia.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				