<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Buildings -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_CITY_HALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civic governance – rule outside of the monarchy or church – has a surprisingly long history. Early models of state formation imagined agricultural societies based around the sharp division of people into classes, with a despotic ruler above all. But even societies such as Egypt could move from locally-focused governance to top-down rule, and societies such as those in Scandinavia, upland Southeast Asia, indigenous North America, and others relied on the consultation of local voices with decrees from above. The city hall is where this happens, a gathering point for local notables to decide on municipal administration, as evinced by their name: “state house” in many Germanic languages, and “central pavilion” in Siamese. City halls, especially in the modern era, could be architectural wonders or simple pavilions in the center of town. In either case, these were places of collective input – a model that assumes the public is capable of governing with its own interests.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_PALACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The early modern lawyer Edmund Plowden wrote that kings have two bodies: one on the earth and one that belongs to something beyond, whether legal or divine. In Buddhist kingship, the perfect king, the cakkavatin (chakravarti), is both world-conqueror and world-renouncer. Each speaks to the problem of royalty: royals are mortals, bound by flesh like everyone else, but they embody something larger. These worlds collide in the palace. On one hand, palaces hold dining halls, sleeping chambers, and lavatories that fulfill the needs of the monarch's earthy body. On the other hand, palaces possess the ritual and bureaucratic apparatus that attends to the king’s "other" body. As a result, palaces were grand edifices; while the king did visit the privy, he did so in a way that implied he'd surpassed the peasant's experiences. In addition to earthly needs, palaces held an aura of inviolability, fascinated outsiders, and held the administrative offices required for monarchical affairs. In the absolute monarchies of recent years, palaces became sprawling locations, as bureaucrats and other functionaries required offices – such as the “rear palace” of Siamese courts or the vast administrative wings of Versailles.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Improvements -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_EXPEDITION_BASE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Expedition Bases serve as places where centralized empires could interact with areas within their borders, but beyond their control: mountain ranges, broken terrain, inaccessible swamps. Here, trade or tribute from those living beyond these zones could be collected, while they themselves remained less visible to systems of mapping and production. Such bases allowed goods (such as ivory, forest products, or furs) to flow, while maintaining some degree of boundary between the spaces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FARM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One of the cornerstones of the Neolithic Revolution was the deliberate cultivation of plants and animals. However, that starting point is surprisingly vague – if fruit trees grow out of the discarded pits in a trash pile, is that cultivation? As early as prehistoric times, human settlements had groves of naturally occurring beneficial plants. Even our domesticated animals (namely dogs) may have domesticated themselves, understanding the benefit of allying with the otherwise dangerous primates sitting around fires. However, conscious farming introduced a body of knowledge and expertise about certain crops, most notably grains: maize, wheat, rice, barley, etc. These crops also bear seed at a particular time, making them useful for states interested in controlling populations (potatoes and other root vegetables notably do not seed). Each early civilization had a signature crop: maize for Mesoamericans, potatoes for South Americans, rice in southern China, and wheat nearly everywhere.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mining is an old practice – older even than humanity. Neanderthals dug mines into European hills to extract flint for tools. However, the oldest known mine made by modern human hands was not for production, but beauty. This was the Ngwenya mine in Eswatini, where miners gathered red ochre for paint. As societies began to depend on minerals, mines grew larger and more complex – the Egyptians mined malachite, copper, and turquoise, as well as the famous gold mines of Nubia. In Southeast Asia, the Ban Chiang culture mined copper from the hills to make bronze.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Mining technology moved away from carving at cave walls and cliff faces to extensive underground complexes, chasing subterranean seams of metal and mineral. Today, mining companies find it more expedient (and safer for the miners) to blast the mountain away and scoop up the remaining valuable materials.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CLAY_PIT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The earliest ceramics emerged nearly 30,000 years ago, in the Paleolithic, although these works seem to be artistic or ritualistic objects and not everyday vessels as we commonly know them. The first evidence for the latter comes from China around 18,000 BCE. The firing of clay is a marker of the Neolithic, and often heralds the beginnings of large-scale changes in societies, such as agriculture (except for some regions where pastoralism remained important), the use of smaller and smaller stone blades, and the like.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CLAY_PIT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Clay pits were dug out of the ground where good clay exists and were often kneaded by foot to remove impurities before they were carted to potters. Unlike with bricks, pottery was often not made directly at the pit but happened in artisan’s workshops. The most famous variety of clay is the white kaolin, first used in China to make the expensive porcelain that enthralled global markets in the 1700s.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_WOODCUTTER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some human societies make homes from the hides of animals, propping them up on their bones. Others make houses from solid ice and snow. But for the most part, humanity is full of woodworkers – making homes of wood, crafting tools of wood, and burning wood for cooking and warmth. The history of woodcutting extends as far back as stone tools, well past the domain of Homo sapiens and into the realm of its more distant cousins. Here, a woodcutter is a solitary figure in the forest, chopping lumber for transport (often down rivers), or burning wood to make charcoal fuel. However, trees grow slowly and high populations demand more and more lumber – in China, Japan, Renaissance Italy, and increasing elsewhere, cities often mandated replanting, an attempt at creating a sustainable lumber industry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FISHING_BOAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Boats have existed for millennia, and we have used them to access waters rich in fish since we first set out upon them. The settlement of Australia, Crete, and Flores suggest that humans have traveled to shores unreachable by foot for nearly 50,000 years. Protein traces from fish in human remains from 40,000 years ago (in present-day China) indicate we have been eating fish for nearly as long. Early fishing was performed with nets, baskets, harpoons (for larger fish), and even bone hooks – the legend of Maui and his fishhook indicates the importance of fishing for many societies. A fishing fleet is simply the intensification of these survival strategies, an adaptation of sea-going people to urbanization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CAMP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Camps for rounding up animals, hunting, and gathering resources are nothing new. Indeed, roving camps were likely an early feature of human life before humans were even humans. These involved temporary structures (or sporadically inhabited ones) where people could go and collect resources before moving on to the next point, occasionally visiting trading posts to sell what they found. Camps are naturally seasonal, as certain animals are easier to hunt at certain times – winter might be uncomfortable but sparse vegetation allows for an easier time spotting game. Camps might be bases of operation for particular ethnic minorities – for instance, the Bedouin or Kazakhs – who might achieve a level of security and prosperity from trading with settled communities (such as the Arabs or Russians, in reference to the earlier examples).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PASTURE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Domesticated herd animals are mainly creatures of the open plain; their fast movement allows them to cover wide spaces, minimizing their impact on localized vegetation. Early animal husbandry required leading herds on a continual search for greener grasses across unsettled lands. Over time, new approaches were discovered: a farmer could intentionally fertilize land for grazing or fence off a series of meadows to herd animals as they depleted the vegetation, allowing for more control over the animals and leading to higher populations. These controlled grazing zones are called pastures; they are neither open rangeland nor heavily cultivated farms.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PLANTATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “plantation” simply means a place of agriculture. But historically the term represents much more: farming on an industrial scale, governed by a plantation estate to yield products intended for commercial sale. Just as factories relied upon machinery and the alienated labor of displaced peasants during the industrial age, so too did plantations. In a factory, the owner possesses the building, the tools used to make products, and the final output. Likewise, plantations were the property of one wealthy owner who used a variety of paid laborers – or enslaved labor, as was the case of the plantations of the New World. The case was similar in ancient Rome where influential aristocrats commanded hundreds of enslaved workers to operate their “latifundia.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_QUARRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Early builders knew the value of good stone. They also knew that quality stone often needed to be carved from the sides of mountains, especially to yield regular-sized materials or products with special qualities (e.g. marble). Workers used bronze tools (or exploited the expansion of freezing water and wet wood) to extract certain shapes before rolling the stones on logs, often over long distances. Significant quarries include the stoneworks at Aswan, the Roman marble quarries at Luna, and indigenous North American quarries used for calumet pipes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_OIL_RIG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most of the earth’s surface is covered with water, which means most of the minerals (and petroleum) upon which industrialized countries rely are covered by water. At the end of the 19th century, offshore oil rigs were developed to detect and extract these resources. They were often constructed on the end of piers extending into shallow water, but more mobile barges were built in the 1930s. Such platforms kicked off an era of oil extraction and consumption, enabling social transformations such as the American car industry (and the lifestyle built on its back)…as well as the rise of global warming.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>