<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Concepts -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GETTING_STARTED_TITLE">
			<Text>Getting Started</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CHAPTER_INTRO_TITLE">
			<Text>Welcome</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CHAPTER_INTRO_PARA_1">
			<Text>Welcome to the Civilopedia for Sid Meier's Civilization VII. Here you will find detailed descriptions of all aspects of the game. Using the search function on the top right will take you to the various major sections of the Civilopedia. The Navigation Bar on the left side of the screen will display the various entries within a section. Select an entry to go directly there.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WONDERS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Wonders</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WONDERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WONDERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Wonders are monumental structures that stand out thanks to their unique presence and significant bonuses. Each Wonder is modeled after an iconic real-world landmark that has left a lasting impact on history. Wonders require significant time to complete, but once constructed, they provide Civilizations with immense benefits and resource buffs. Wonders can only be constructed during certain ages, but they remain ageless, meaning their bonuses carry over from one age to the next.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WONDERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each Wonder can only exist once in each game. If players begin construction on a Wonder but fail to complete it before another player, they are refunded 50% of their invested production.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WONDERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Every player has access to all the Wonders, and each one can be unlocked from either the Tech or Civic tree. However, each Civ also has an associated World Wonder, which means they receive a 30% bonus towards that specific Wonder's construction. Associated Wonders are also easier to unlock since their Civ has one additional place within the Tech or Civic trees to unlock them (Civ's can unlock their associated World Wonder from either location.)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WONDERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Wonders provide an adjacency bonus to all buildings, so surrounding a Wonder with other buildings is a powerful strategy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Diplomacy and Influence</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Influence is a new Yield introduced in Civilization VII. It is the main currency for diplomatic gameplay. Players accrue Influence from various sources and spend it to undertake Diplomatic Actions with other players and Independent Powers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Diplomatic Actions include Endeavors, Sanctions, Independent Power interactions, and more. Endeavors are actions that benefit one or both parties which raises the relationship scores. Sanctions are actions that hurt the targeting party which lowers the relationship scores. Palaces, Buildings, and Wonders all award Influence, but it remains less abundant than other Resources. Once Influence is spent, it is not returned. However, the player does regain the Influence used if the opponent rejects an action.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Since Influence is the currency used to generate War Support, saving up a significant amount of Influence before going to war is a good strategy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Statehood: Civs</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Introduction</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civilizations, commonly referred to as "Civs," are the core entities players control and develop throughout the game. Each Civ represents a unique cultural, political, and historical identity, embodying distinct strengths, abilities, and strategies. The goal is to lead a Civ to prosperity and dominance through various means, such as military conquest, cultural influence, scientific advancement, or economic domination.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each Civ comes with unique attributes, such as special units, buildings, traditions, and abilities that reflect their historical and cultural heritage. These unique attributes provide strategic advantages and encourage diverse playstyles. Choosing a Civ that aligns with your preferred strategy can significantly impact your success.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>A unique set of Civs is available each Age, meaning no Civ lasts forever. As new Ages dawn, new Civs emerge, replacing those from previous eras. However, the Traditions researched by earlier Civs persist into the next Age. This layering of history ensures continuity and evolution, reflecting the dynamic nature of a civilization.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Statehood: Villages</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Independent Powers have replaced the concept of Barbarians from previous Civ titles. All Independent Powers start the game at the Minor level. Through interaction, Independents can be promoted and advance to the Major level, which affords them the additional gameplay mechanics of city-states from previous titles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_2_CHAPTER_VILLAGES_TITLE">
			<Text>Villages</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_2_CHAPTER_VILLAGES_PARA_1">
			<Text>If a Minor Independent has a Friendly Affinity, it is set to be Friends with the nearest Major Power at the start of the game. If a Minor Independent has a Hostile Affinity, it is set to be Hostile with all Major Powers. If a Minor Independent has neither affinity, it starts in a Neutral state. Regardless of these starting positions, Minor Independents’ relationships will grow and evolve as the game progresses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_2_CHAPTER_VILLAGES_PARA_REMOVED">
			<Text>If players attack a Minor Independent, they become Hostile. Likewise, an Independent’s friendliness reduces if players found Settlements near their Village. If the Settlement is within 3 tiles, the Independent immediately becomes Hostile; if the Settlement is 4 to 6 tiles away, the Relationship degrades one level (i.e., Friendly to Neutral; Neutral to Hostile). Players can Befriend an Independent through diplomatic actions once their Village has been discovered; this increases a progress bar, which raises the Independent’s friendliness level.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_2_CHAPTER_VILLAGES_PARA_2">
			<Text>Raiding is the main interaction between players and Independent Powers. An Independent Power will occasionally raid a nearby player, sending units to attack them. The player can also use diplomatic actions to incite the Independent Power to raid other nearby civilizations if the Independent is Hostile towards the Civ.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREAT_WORK_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Great Works</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREAT_WORK_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Great Works are important pieces of art or information curated by your Civilization. Every Age has a different Great Work to collect: Codices, Relics, and Artifacts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREAT_WORK_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To activate Great Work bonuses, you must display them in specific Buildings. Your Palace will always have a Great Work slot. In addition, every Age will also have special Buildings such as the Library or Museum that can display the current Age’s Great Work.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GREAT_WORK_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Some Wonders have Great Work slots, and some reward Great Works upon completion. if you're looking to collect Great Works, they are worth constructing.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CODEX_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Codex</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CODEX_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CODEX_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Codex is a type of Great Work useful for earning the Scientific legacy points in Antiquity. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CODEX_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Codices are displayed when they are slotted into a building – open the slotting menu by selecting the Greatworks icon. Both Libraries and Academies contain slots as does the Nalanda Wonder. Your Palace (your Capital’s city center) also contains one slot by default. To excel on this legacy path, Players will need multiple Cities with the appropriate constructibles.	</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CODEX_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Most Codices are awarded by mastering Tech, but some come from the Civic Tree, narrative events, as a City-State Suzerain bonus, or for completing the Nalanda Wonder. Some Civs can also earn a Codex through Great People.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CODEX_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Focusing on the Science Yield and building a few Cities with the required buildings is the best way to reach the milestones on this path.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Statehood: City-States</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Independent Powers have replaced the concept of Barbarians from previous Civ titles. All Independent Powers start the game at the Minor level. Through diplomatic actions , Independents can be promoted and advance to the Major level, which affords them the additional gameplay mechanics of city-states from previous titles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_3_CHAPTER_CITYSTATES_TITLE">
			<Text>City-States</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_STATEHOOD_3_CHAPTER_CITYSTATES_PARA_1">
			<Text>Major Independents are not present at the beginning of the game. Instead, they emerge when a Minor Independent is promoted by a Major Power (who becomes their Suzerain) via the Befriend Independent diplomatic action. When promoted, Independents gain an Urban hex, City Hall, and additional defenses (such as Walls) to reflect their new status as a Major Independent. Players who become a Suzerain will get to select a Suzerain bonus, and the Major Independents they promote will remain under them until the end of the Age. Major Independents will also align with the war/peace status of their Suzerain when interacting with other Major players.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WARWEARINESS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>War Weariness</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WARWEARINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WARWEARINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>War Weariness represents the willingness of the Civ’s population to continue a war effort. Wars that lack Support and have not achieved victory can lead to complete societal stagnation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WARWEARINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>War Weariness is represented by the difference in Support between players during a War Support Action. The player with less Support incurs a penalty that is calculated based on the size of that difference.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WARWEARINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Every point of War Weariness will reduce City Yields as follows: reduce Happiness by 3 in Settlements you founded, reduce Happiness by 5 in Settlements founded by someone else (unless it is a power you are currently At War with), reduce Happiness by 7 in Settlements founded by a power you are currently At War with, and reduce all Combat Strength by 1 (up to a total of 20).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WARWEARINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>War Weariness does not stack across multiple wars. Only the highest War Weariness value will apply for happiness penalties. Combat Strength penalties only apply while fighting units from the player causing War Weariness - battles with other Civs are unaffected. All War Weariness effects are removed once the war ends.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WARWEARINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: You can spend Influence to increase War Support by selecting the portrait of the Leader you are at war with and then selecting the War icon.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Gold Income</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Gold is an empire-wide resource, similar to Science and Culture. Unlike those resources, however, unspent Gold accumulates in the player's treasury – after automatic expenses are deducted from income. The amount of Gold in the treasury is always visible in the upper left corner of the UI, alongside your Gold Income, which reflects the difference between your empire's expenses and earnings. Unlike other resources, it is possible to have a negative Gold income, which could severely hamper a Civ’s development.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Gold has many uses, such as purchasing Units and Buildings, and covering the maintenance fees for those assets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOLD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Towns are key players in a Civ’s economy. Towns convert their Production directly into Gold, making the expansion of your empire essential for maintaining a vibrant economy. However, this expansion introduces potential conflicts and risks, necessitating a careful strategic approach.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_TITLE">
			<Text>City Capture</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To capture a settlement, attackers must gain control of a City/Town Center and any Urban tiles with its walled defenses. At times, there may be more than one capturing player. In this case, the player who controls the most urban tiles is the victor. In the case of ties, the Civ who captured the last urban tile is the winner.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_CHAPTER_URBAN_TITLE">
			<Text>Urban Districts</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_CHAPTER_URBAN_PARA_1">
			<Text>The City Center district starts with 100 Health and all other Urban districts start at zero. Districts with a health value are considered "defensible," and a district’s health must be reduced to zero before an attacker can advance onto that tile. Walls add health values to districts. Combat against a district only applies damage to the district and does not affect the buildings within. By default, districts reciprocate damage to an melee attacker. Damaged defensible districts will regenerate health automatically over time, provided the following conditions are met:[BLIST][LI]Must be controlled by the City owner.[LI]Cannot be occupied by an enemy unit or have adjacent enemy units.[LI]The City where the urban district is located has not had any district attacked for a number of turns.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_CHAPTER_WALL_TITLE">
			<Text>Wall Defenses</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_CHAPTER_WALL_PARA_1">
			<Text>Wall defenses increase a district's health by 100. However, walls from a previous age only provide half the defense bonus and half the district health while walls older than one age provide no benefit. Walls from previous ages can be upgraded by overbuilding them with the current age walls. Wall defenses are not repaired through the City production queue; they automatically repair over time as long as they are not under attack and have no adjacent enemy units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_CHAPTER_WALL_PARA_2">
			<Text>Wall defenses cannot be purchased with Gold, except in the City Center. Instead, walls in urban districts can be constructed one tile at a time from the City build queue, using Production. Walls cannot be constructed on Navigable River hexes and must be built adjacent to other wall defenses from the same settlement, starting with the City Center. Walls cannot be built adjacent to walls owned by a different settlement, except in the city center, which is always allowed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITYCAPTURE_1_CHAPTER_WALL_PARA_3">
			<Text>When a unit attacks a defensible district, combat is resolved by taking the attacking unit's strength and comparing it to the defense strength of the district, which is calculated based on the strongest melee unit trained by the district owner minus a set value (10). Walls and all City or Town centers deal reciprocal damage to melee attackers.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TILES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Urban and Rural Tiles</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TILES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Two types of tiles exist within a Settlement: Urban and Rural. Rural tiles are obtained through border expansion, while Urban tiles are created by placing buildings on a Rural tile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TILES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>During a growth event, placing a point of population on a Rural tile results in an Improvement. Basic Improvements include Farms, Mines, Woodcutters, Clay Pits, Fishing Boats, Camps, Pastures, Plantations, Quarries, and Oil Rigs. Conversely, placing a point of population on an Urban tile grants a Specialist. Specialists provide benefits such as increased Science, Culture, and building adjacency bonuses (+2 Science, +2 Culture, +0.5 Adjacency Bonus), but they also reduce the City's Food and Happiness (-2 Food, -2 Happiness).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TILES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Urban tiles with at least one building are referred to as Districts. When an Urban tile is completely occupied by buildings from the current Age or Ageless category, it is designated as a Quarter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TILES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: While Towns can acquire Urban tiles by purchasing buildings, only Cities can gain Specialists.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_REPAIR_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Repair</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_REPAIR_1_CHAPTER_BUILDINGREPAIR_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_REPAIR_1_CHAPTER_BUILDINGREPAIR_PARA_1">
			<Text>Damaged buildings and improvements can be repaired through either the production queue or the purchase queue of the corresponding Settlement. However, tiles occupied by enemy Units cannot be repaired until enemy Unit moves away or is defeated.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NATURALWONDER_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Natural Wonders</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NATURALWONDER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NATURALWONDER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Natural Wonders are unique terrain features scattered throughout the world. Cutscenes play once a Natural Wonder is discovered. These formations are relatively uncommon and provide powerful bonuses to nearby civilizations. Players should seek out Wonders, settle next to them, and use growth events to place population on the Wonder tiles to collect the bonuses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NATURALWONDER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>All Natural Wonders base yield scales by game age. Each Age provides an additional +50% yield to the Natural Wonder tiles. For example, if an Antiquity Natural Wonder tile provides 6 Food, that same tile would provides 9 Food in Exploration, and 12 Food in Modern.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_NATURALWONDER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Natural Wonder yields are substantial, so discovering one early could significantly influence your expansion strategy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISCOVERIES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Discoveries</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISCOVERIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Discoveries replace the traditional “Goody Huts” from previous Civilization games. These special points of interest are placed on the map during its initial generation, and some may even reappear as exploration progresses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISCOVERIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>There are three types of Discoveries, each increasing in complexity, rewards, and rarity:[BLIST][LI][B]Basic Discoveries[/B] function similarly to classic Goody Huts. When a unit enters the tile, the discovery provides an immediate small reward and then disappears.[LI][B]Investigations[/B] require more investment, either by damaging a unit at the location, paying a resource yield such as gold, science, production, happiness, or culture—or a combination of both. Completing Investigations provides medium-sized rewards.[LI][B]Mythic Quests[/B] offer substantial challenges but also grant large rewards. These Discoveries task the player with completing specific quests or achieving certain milestones before claiming their generous prizes.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISCOVERIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Always prioritize sending scouts or idle units to explore Discoveries early. Basic Discoveries give quick boosts, while strategic investment in Investigations and Mythic Quests can significantly accelerate your civilization’s progress.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISTANTLAND_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Distant Land</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISTANTLAND_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Distant Land becomes a crucial concept starting in the Exploration Age, acting as a battleground for specific legacy paths. For example, Treasure Convoys can only be created in Distant Land settlements that possess one or more Distant Land Treasure resources. Additionally, certain units, such as Conquistadors, receive special bonuses when operating in Distant Land.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISTANTLAND_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To identify Distant Land, use the continent lens to view the map.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISTANTLAND_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Being the first to discover a Distant Land can provide significant advantages in the Exploration Age. Don't be afraid to take risks and explore the ocean. However, be aware that your units might take attrition damage if they stop on an ocean tile without having researched the Shipbuilding tech.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISASTER_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Disasters</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISASTER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISASTER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Disasters are natural events that occur automatically, often causing localized destruction. The level of destruction scales with the severity of the disaster. However, some disasters also enhance the productivity of affected areas by "fertilizing" tiles, which increases their basic Food, Production, and/or Science yields without changing the tiles’ inherent characteristics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISASTER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Fertilization is not guaranteed with every disaster, and the probability of fertilization is determined separately for each tile. As a result, a single tile could potentially receive fertilization in one, two, or all three yield types from a single disaster, or it could not benefit at all. Only land tiles are eligible for fertilization. Over time, a tile hit by multiple disasters can become a high-yield tile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISASTER_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Generally, the more severe a disaster, the more likely it is to fertilize tiles. Work to minimize damage (i.e. do not station units along a river to avoid flood damage) and you can learn to use disasters to your advantage.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISASTER_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Disaster Damage</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DISASTER_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Natural Disasters damage man-made structures and units on the map. However, settlement populations are directly tied to their buildings and improvements. Still, Settlements only lose population if they suffer structural damage. Therefore, there are only three possible types of damage:[BLIST][LI]Improvement Damage: This has a chance to cause damage to improvements, resulting in the loss of 1 Rural population.[LI]Building Damage: This has a chance to cause damage to buildings, resulting in the loss of Urban population for a building of the current age.[LI]Unit Damage: Military units are always affected by a disaster. The HP damage generally ranges from 30-70.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Army and Commanders</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civilization VII introduces new rules surrounding the ability to combine multiple units into an Army that moves as a single entity thanks to the use of Commanders. Additionally, players can use Army-level commands to automate certain operations and tasks, reducing micromanagement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Basic Rules for the Armies Mechanic:[BLIST][LI]Army Formation: Each player can form one or more Armies. Armies can only be formed by a Commander unit. Once an Army is established, units can be added or removed either individually or in groups through the 'Assemble' and 'Deploy' Commander actions.[LI]Army Capacity: Each Army has a capacity limit for both primary and civilian units. An Army’s initial capacity is 4 units, but this can be increased through various advancements like Promotions, Techs, Civics, etc.[LI]Movement: Commander units have a base Movement of 2. When packed with other combat units, the Commander gains a +1 Movement bonus.[LI]Unit Commands: Units and Armies possess unit-level commands that facilitate the addition and removal of units.[LI]Civilian Protection: Civilian layer units are typically unpacked as a stacked group with a primary layer unit for protection.[LI]Unpacking Requirements: Armies must Deploy when they get attacked by enemies with sufficient strength.[LI]Commander Actions: Army Commander units can perform special actions when packed and unpacked. When Unpacked, Commander actions apply to all friendly units within their Command range (default range of 1).[LI]Overrun Attack: Armies can brush off smaller enemy forces with a special Overrun attack, allowing them to kill the opposing unit and enter their tile (expending a movement cost to enter that hex). Armies need combat odds of approximately 5:1 or greater to Overrun an opponent.[LI]Promotions: Promotions are assigned to the Commander unit at the 'army level.' Individual units no longer gain experience or promotions. Commander units with suitable experience levels will advance from one Age to the next, allowing investments in military action to continue through the Ages.[LI]Respawning: Defeated Commanders respawn after 20 turns on Standard Speed. They also respawn after Age transitions.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Unlike previous Civilization titles where different units had their own promotions, promotions are now exclusive to Commanders. They are also Ageless units, meaning they can survive through all Ages. Commanders are your most valuable asset on the battlefield. Never fight a war without one!</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Combat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Combat is initiated by Military Units, which are produced or bought in Settlements. Air units can only be produced in Settlements with an Aerodrome, while Naval units can only be produced in Settlements founded on coastal tiles or navigable river tiles. Land units can be produced in all Cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Combat in Civilization VII retains many core principles from previous titles. Each military unit has a set of statistics that defines its combat capabilities, which can be enhanced through Commander promotions, terrain advantages, and other special bonuses. Key statistics include:[BLIST][LI]Hit Points (HP): Each unit has 100 hit points, also known as Health. When a unit takes damage, its HP decreases; stronger attacks cause more significant HP loss. A unit is destroyed if its HP drops to 0.[LI]Combat Strength (CS): This stat indicates a unit’s overall combat effectiveness. For melee units, this represents both its offensive and defensive power. For ranged units, this only accounts for its defensive power.[LI]Ranged Strength (RS): Specific to ranged units, this stat measures a unit’s attack power from a distance. However, ranged attacks are less effective against City Defenses and naval units.[LI]Range: This stat determines the distance a unit can attack and is relevant to ranged/siege units, some recon units, and Immortals. For example, a Range of 1 limits attacks to adjacent tiles, while a Range of 3 allows attacks up to three tiles away.[LI]Movement Points (MP): These points are used when units move or perform actions. Typically, 1 MP per tile is required to move over plains and water, but this can change with roads, hills, river crossings, and enemy zones of control. Units need sufficient MPs to move and attack, making high MP values beneficial for covering territory with fewer units.[LI]Sight: This stat indicates how many tiles a unit can reveal around its position, removing the "fog of war." Most units have a Sight range of 2. While not a direct combat stat, Sight is crucial for allowing ranged units to identify targets.[LI]Bombard Strength: Bombard attacks are more effective against fortified tiles compared to ranged attacks, making actual siege units the preferred choice for delivering superior firepower against such defenses. Both ranged and siege land units use their bombard strength when attacking naval units, resulting in ranged units inflicting less damage and siege units inflicting more damage on naval targets.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Positioning a melee unit in front of a ranged unit is a classic and effective formation. Aim to use this tactic frequently! If you're having difficulty in warfare, look for different ways to boost your units' combat strength.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ATTRIBUTE_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Attribute</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ATTRIBUTE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Attributes are traits your leader earns throughout a Civilization campaign. These add an RPG element to the game. Each Attribute represents an area in which a leader might excel, such as Science, Culture, or Military. Accumulated Attribute Points can be spent on corresponding Skill Trees, granting bonuses that persist across every Age. This system lets players customize their leaders in various ways and even play the same leader in different ways in multiple games.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ATTRIBUTE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Leaders have six categories of Attributes: Cultural, Diplomatic, Economic, Expansionist, Militaristic, and Scientific. Points spent in these categories enhance a leader's abilities in those areas, granting bonuses and new Diplomatic Actions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ATTRIBUTE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Once an Attribute Point is earned, it can be spent immediately or saved. However, saving Attribute Points is rarely necessary. Points can never be lost, so even if a player gains a point from a constructible and that constructible is then lost, the Attribute Point is retained. Attribute Points can be acquired from the following sources:[BLIST][LI]Leader Choice: Every leader is awarded 3 points through Narrative Events – 1 point each Age. These narrative events occur on turn 25 (standard speed).[LI]Civ Choice: Every civilization is awarded 3 points through Narrative Events. The first event occurs on turn 50 (standard speed), and the other two come after players complete additional Narrative Event quests[LI]Completed Wonders[LI]Victory Rewards[LI]Narrative Events Rewards[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ATTRIBUTE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Unlocking an attribute does not automatically unlock the next attribute tier. Be sure to follow the arrows that indicate the unlock requirements! This feature is similar to the Tech tree.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PANTHEON_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Pantheon</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PANTHEON_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Pantheons represent the earliest forms of spirituality, predating organized religions. They involve the worship of various minor gods typically associated with nature and natural phenomena, and they grant small bonuses often linked to the Altar.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PANTHEON_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Pantheons are a Belief type that is only available in the Antiquity Age. Players can choose a Pantheon after unlocking the Mysticism Civic. Once a Pantheon is selected, it is removed from the pool and cannot be chosen by other Civs.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PANTHEON_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>All Pantheons require the Altar building, which is unlocked with the Mysticism Civic.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Government</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Governments are part of the Culture system and are key decision makers in each Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>At least three different Governments are selectable in each Age. Once a government is chosen that choice is locked in for the Age and cannot be changed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GOVERNMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Every Government type provides the player with 2 Celebration effects to choose between every time they earn a Celebration moment. These effects last for 10 turns, encourage the player to focus on specific gameplay for their duration, and are unique to each Government type. In addition, every Celebration will grant a new Policy slot.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Endeavors</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Endeavors are positive actions players can initiate with another player. To start, go to another Civ’s diplomatic screen and select an action to undertake. Actions cost Influence and have a fixed duration. Their rewards can be symmetrical or asymmetrical, depending on the project. After an action is selected, a leader scene plays out and presents the target with three options.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Players interacting with the AI will receive a response either immediately or by the next turn (depending on technical constraints and with a preference for immediate responses). The options are:[BLIST][LI]Support: The target player spends Influence to increase the benefits for both players. This action also provides a relationship gain over time.[LI]Accept: This option is free for the target Civ, but both Civs receive a smaller bonus than if the action was supported.[LI]Reject: The target player spends Influence, and the endeavor is immediately canceled. The player who initiated the action receives a full refund. For the next 10 turns, endeavors cannot be started between the two Civs, and they receive a relationship penalty. Rejections can also be done retroactively.[/LIST] </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Starting or supporting an Endeavor is an excellent way to improve your relationship with another Civ. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Sanctions</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A sanction is a negative action that can be taken against a Civ. However, sanctions are gated by relationship status, which means sanctions are not available against a Civs with a friendly or better status. Likewise, more aggressive Sanctions become available as relationships degrade. Sanctions are initiated much like endeavors and last for a fixed duration. The target player is shown a leader scene and presented with these options:[BLIST][LI]Accept: This option is free for the target. They incur the full effects of the sanction and suffer a relationship penalty.[LI]Reject: The targeted player can spend Influence to cancel the sanction. This can also be done retroactively. The player who initiated the sanction does not receive a refund.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Sanctions are an effective way to rapidly decrease a relationship with another Civ. Consider using sanctions before starting a war, as initiating war against Civs with whom you have a good relationship typically incurs penalties. </Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Treaties</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Treaties can be either positive or negative and include actions such as open borders, denouncing military presence, and improving trade relations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Initiating the improve trade relations treaty is a great way to jumpstart your Economic legacy path in the Antiquity Age. </Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Espionage</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Starting an espionage action involves selecting it from the diplomatic action menu and paying an associated influence cost. Once initiated, the target player is not informed. The action takes a random number of turns to complete, with each action specifying an average duration plus or minus a few turns. During this period, the player loses influence per turn, making the final cost variable. Upon completion, the player receives the reward for secret missions or has a chance to receive the reward for top secret missions. There is also a chance of the action being revealed, influenced by the nature of the action and any modifiers. If the initiating player is discovered, they incur a per-turn influence loss and a relationship penalty with the target player. In some cases, the target player can see the effect and has a chance to identify the initiator.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>If at the start of your turn you have zero influence in your bank and a negative influence per turn, all current espionage actions are canceled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Counterspy is a unique espionage action that can be deployed against a specific player. It doubles the average time to complete espionage actions and increases the likelihood of them being revealed, making them harder to execute effectively and more costly in influence over time. Counterspy actions also decrease the success rate of top secret missions. There is an initial cost, a per-turn cost, and a set duration. During this period, any espionage action takes double the time to complete, even if the counterspy action ends during that time. Actions already in progress will have their remaining time doubled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>This robust counterspy mechanic forces high-level players to interpret the cause of a drop in someone's per-turn influence. Questions such as whether counterspying has begun, if it is directed at them, or if another espionage action has been initiated, add a layer of intrigue to the system.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: Monitor your influence carefully when engaging in espionage. A sudden drop could indicate counterspying or other clandestine activities.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_6_TITLE">
			<Text>Agendas</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civs are impacted by two types of Agendas: Leader Agendas and AI Biases.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_6_CHAPTER_LEADERAGENDA_TITLE">
			<Text>Leader Agendas</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_6_CHAPTER_LEADERAGENDA_PARA_1">
			<Text>Leader Agendas specifically affect the relationship between two Civs. For example, Hatshepsut’s agenda, Wonders of Iteru, decreases your relationship with her Civ by a small amount if you have more Wonders than she does, but it also increases your relationship by a medium amount if you have fewer Wonders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_6_CHAPTER_AIBIAS_TITLE">
			<Text>AI Biases</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_6_CHAPTER_AIBIAS_PARA_1">
			<Text>AI Biases are hidden from players, but these influence the behavior of AI leaders. For example, Amina tends to be more militarily aggressive.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLOMACY_6_CHAPTER_AIBIAS_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Playing to the needs of a leader’s agenda is a great way to befriend them rapidly.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Improve Resource</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Allocating a Population to an empty tile zones it as Rural and adds an Improvement based on the terrain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>If a tile has a Resource, that Resource determines the basic Improvement. For tiles without Resources, the Improvement varies by Biome. Examples include:[BLIST][LI]Flat Terrain: Farm - Provides Food.[LI]Hill Terrain: Mine - Provides Production.[LI]Vegetation Feature: Woodcutter - Provides Production.[LI]Wet Feature: Clay Pit - Provides Production.[LI]Navigable River or Coast: Fishing Boats - Provides Food.[/LIST] </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Other factors regarding Resource Improvements include:[BLIST][LI]Contiguity Requirement: Improvements must be contiguous with other Urban or Rural tiles in the Settlement.[LI]Zoning and Determination: When a Population is applied to an empty tile, it is zoned as Rural and receives an Improvement based on the terrain.[LI]Core Yield: Improvements have a core yield determined by the natural tile yield, and are influenced by terrain, features, and resources.[LI]Resource Enhancement: If a tile has a Resource, the Improvement provides 1 quantity of that Resource for trading, in addition to its natural yield.[LI]No Maintenance: Improvements do not incur Maintenance costs.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Improvements can be enhanced with Warehouse buildings. If you have a lot of improvements that provide the same type of yield, make sure to build the corresponding Warehouse building.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RESOURCES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Allocate Resource</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RESOURCES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Resources can be allocated to Settlements when you improve a City, Bonus, or Factory Resource. Or anytime you begin a Trade Route.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RESOURCES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Types of Resources:[BLIST][LI]Bonus Resources: can be allocated to any Town or City.[LI]City Resources: can be allocated to any City. Some City Resources are more powerful in certain Cities, depending on the Age.[LI]Empire Resources never have to be allocated to a Settlement - they are fully effective for your empire as soon as you obtain them.[LI]Treasure Resources: do not need to be assigned and help the creation of Treasure Convoys.[LI]Factory Resources: one type of Factory Resource can be assigned to each Settlement with a Factory. Once a Factory Resource is slotted, it changes into an Empire Resource. [/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RESOURCES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: The Resource Assignments Available Notification will appear when you obtain a new Resource or when a new Resource Slot is available.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RESOURCE_SLOT_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Resource Slots</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RESOURCE_SLOT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Every Settlement can be allocated a Resource, but only if it has the infrastructure to handle it. While every Settlement starts with a single Resource Slot, you can unlock more by building specific Buildings, like the Market, or changing a Town's Focus.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RESOURCE_SLOT_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Economic Legacy Paths will benefit from having plentiful Resource Slots, and Resources can help keep your population happy in times of struggle.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_HAPPINESS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Happiness</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_HAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Happiness functions as both a global and local resource, similar to Gold. Here are the important highlights of Happiness:[BLIST][LI]Production: Settlements generate Happiness through their features, such as constructible projects, Wonders, Natural Wonders, and resource gathering.[LI]Consumption: Settlements consume Happiness to maintain their specialists, preserve their buildings, and address conditional effects from other gameplay events or situations. These are listed under the "Sources of Local Unhappiness" section.[LI]Buffs: Technologies, Civics, Traditions, and other gameplay elements may introduce new sources of Happiness.[LI]Global Yield: Happiness can be granted to Civs directly in lump sums.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_HAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Happiness influences your civilization on two levels:[BLIST][LI]Global Level: Happiness allows you to earn Celebrations.[LI]City Level: Happiness is used for the upkeep local specialists and buildings. Settlements that exceed their cap, war weariness, and unrest from captured Cities also contribute to local Happiness upkeep.[/LIST] </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_HAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: If your settlement’s Happiness dips below zero, you will trigger the Consequences of Unhappiness. Please see the Unhappiness: Consequences page for more details.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Unhappiness: Consequences</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_EFFECTS_TITLE">
			<Text>Local Unhappiness Effects</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_EFFECTS_PARA_1">
			<Text>Failing to maintain positive Happiness in a Settlement results in reduced yields:[BLIST][LI]Each point of net local Unhappiness conveys a -2% penalty to other local yields, such as Gold, Production, and Science.[LI]An efficiency model is used to calculate the penalty to prevent yields from going negative.[LI]Negative Happiness from a Settlement does not get added to the Global Happiness yield that advances Celebrations. [/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_GLOBAL_TITLE">
			<Text>Global Unhappiness/Happiness</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_GLOBAL_PARA_1">
			<Text>Similar to Gold, Happiness accumulates globally. When the total accumulated Happiness crosses a threshold, it rewards the Civ with their choice of a Celebration. Low global Happiness significantly hampers policy slot unlocks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_METHODS_TITLE">
			<Text>Methods to Mitigate Unhappiness</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_METHODS_PARA_1">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]City Happiness Buildings: Serves as a must-have Happiness building before other buildings are constructed.[LI]Resources allocation: Dates, Dyes, Wool, Pearls, and Wine are sources of Happiness during a Celebration.[LI]Commander Influence: Commanders reduce Settlement unhappiness by 10% when stationed in a City/Town center, and each Commander promotion adds 10% more to their effectiveness. This effect is removed from the Settlement as soon as the Commander moves away.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNHAPPINESS_1_CHAPTER_METHODS_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Boost your Happiness by stationing commanders in your City/Town centers when not at war. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CELEBRATION_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Celebration</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CELEBRATION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Celebrations unlock a Policy slot. Additionally, Civs experiencing a Celebration can select one of two duration-based buffs from Government-specific effects. For example, during a Celebration, a Classical Republic Civ unlocks a Tradition Slot and then picks between +20% Culture for 10 Turns or +15% Production towards Wonders for 10 Turns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CELEBRATION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each successive Celebration costs more Happiness than the previous one. During a Celebration, Happiness accrual does not does not cease, and can lead to chaining Celebrations.[/LIST] </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CELEBRATION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Monitor the number of turns remaining until your next Celebration to strategically plan and maximize the benefits of your Celebration effects.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITY_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Cities</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Cities are vital to a Civ’s success. They allow Civs to build units, buildings, and wonders. They are also places to research new technologies and gather wealth. Civs cannot win without powerful, well-situated Cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Capital Cities are constructed by Settler units. If a Settler is positioned in a location where a City can be constructed, the "Found City" action button will appear. Select this button and a new City will replace the Settler.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>After this initial City founding, all subsequent Settlers found Towns instead of Cities. You can spend some Gold to convert your Towns into Cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>When a Settler is selected, ideal Settlement locations are highlighted on the map. The Settler Lens also gives players an idea of which places are ideal sources of water for a Settlement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Remember that each Town you upgrade to a City beyond your Capital will increase non-Warehouse Building costs by 10% each.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CITY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_6">
			<Text>Tip: Cities should be constructed in locations with plenty of Food, Production, and access to various resources. Building Cities on a River or coastal hex is a good idea, as water is vital for a growing Population.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Towns</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Towns are founded by Settlers and require less management than Cities but serve an important supporting role in any Civ. When a Town is in Growth mode, it receives a +50% growth bonus. Towns do not have a Production Queue. Instead, 100% of the Town's Production is converted to Gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_FOCUS_TITLE">
			<Text>Focus Queue</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_FOCUS_PARA_1">
			<Text>When a Town reaches 7 population, the Focus Queue unlocks, allowing that Town to specialize in one of the following options:[BLIST][LI]Farming Town/Fishing Town: +1/2/3 Food on Farms, Pastures, Plantations, and Fishing Boats. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities.[LI]Mining Town: +2/3/4 Production on Camps, Woodcutters, Clay Pits, Mines, and Quarries. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities.[LI]Trade Outpost: +2 Happiness on Resource tiles and +5 trade range. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities. In the Exploration Age, Trade Outposts must be in Distant Lands, and Trade Outposts are not available in the Modern Age.[LI]Fort Town: +5 healing to units and +25 health to Walls in this Town. Barracks can be purchased in Fort Towns.[LI]Religious Site: +1 Happiness on all buildings and +1 Relic Slot on Temples in this Town. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities. Religious Sites are only available during the Exploration Age.[LI]Hub Town: +1 Influence for every connected Settlement. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities. Hub Towns are only available in the Exploration and Modern Ages.[LI]Resort Town: +1 Happiness and Gold per Age on Rural tiles in this Town that have at least 1 Happiness. +50% tile yields from Natural Wonders. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities.[LI]Urban Center: Buildings in this Town cost no Maintenance. You can buy tier 1 buildings (Library, Bath, Monuments) in this Town. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities.[LI]Factory Town: +100% Gold towards purchasing a Factory in this Town and +1 Resource Slot. +5 Trade Range. This prevents the Town from growing, sending its Food to Connected Cities. Factory Towns must contain an improved Factory resource.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_CONNECTIVITY_TITLE">
			<Text>Connectivity</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_CONNECTIVITY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Settlements are considered connected if they are linked with a direct road (intermediate roads that run through other Settlements do not count) or if they are both coastal Settlements on the same continent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_RESTRICTION_TITLE">
			<Text>Restrictions</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_RESTRICTION_PARA_1">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Unrest: Towns cannot start a project while in Unrest. After capturing a settlement, Civs must wait until the unrest period is over before assigning a Town a specialization.[LI]Permanent Specialization: Once a Town’s Focus is selected, it is locked in permanently. Choose wisely![/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_BUILDINGS_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings and Specialists</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_BUILDINGS_PARA_1">
			<Text>Towns can only purchase Buildings that cannot slot Specialists.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_UPGRADING_TITLE">
			<Text>Upgrading to a City</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_UPGRADING_PARA_1">
			<Text>Towns can be converted into Cities but this costs Gold. The more population a Town has, the cheaper it is to upgrade to a City.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_UPGRADING_PARA_2">
			<Text>However, the more Cities you already own, the more expensive your next upgrade will be. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_UPGRADING_PARA_3">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Cost Limits: The upgrade cost has a maximum cap of 1000 Gold and a minimum of 200 Gold after any modifiers. However, Certain Unique Abilities (UA) and other factors can reduce the cost below 200 Gold.[LI]Captured Settlements: Captured Settlements costs double to upgrade, but this charge cannot exceed the 1000 Gold cap.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_1_CHAPTER_UPGRADING_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Instead of converting all Towns into Cities, aim to keep at least a 1 to 1 Town to City ratio.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PRODUCTION_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Production: Yield</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PRODUCTION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Production is one of the main resources in Civilization VII. It is the measure by which Cities build units, buildings, Wonders, and complete projects. As such, Production is as important for City growth as Food, since it determines the speed with which any City erects new structures. However, unlike Food, Production cannot be transported from Towns to Cities, making Production arguably more important; even Cities with large populations cannot produce anything without Production.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PRODUCTION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Since Towns do not have a production queue, their production is converted to Gold.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FOOD_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Food: Yield</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FOOD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Settlements require food to grow their population. After Citizens are born, they no longer consume food, but the threshold for the next growth event increases. However, Citizens who become Specialists have a 2 Food maintenance cost.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FOOD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: When a Settlement runs out of space to grow, the excess food is used to spawn Migrants.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GROWTH_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Growth Moment</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GROWTH_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Settlements gain control of new tiles by accumulating Food until they reach a threshold. After crossing this threshold, the Settlement gains a Population that can allocate to a tile for growth. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GROWTH_1_CHAPTER_BORDER_TITLE">
			<Text>Border Growth</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GROWTH_1_CHAPTER_BORDER_PARA_1">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Expansion: Borders expand when a population is placed on a new tile near a Settlement’s border.[LI]Construction: Borders also grow when a building on the border is completed (repairs do not expand the border).[LI]Limitations: A border’s maximum reach is three tiles from its City Center, not counting the center tile itself. Borders cannot overlap with those of other settlements.[LI]Tile Acquisition: When placing a new population or completing a building, the settlement acquires all adjacent tiles, provided this does not conflict with the rule that borders cannot overlap.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GROWTH_1_CHAPTER_POP_TITLE">
			<Text>Adding Population</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GROWTH_1_CHAPTER_POP_PARA_1">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Food Accumulation: Food from each Settlement is added to a bucket each turn. Upon crossing the growth threshold, the Settlement gains a Population.[LI]Population Allocation: Players can choose between placing a new Population on an empty tile for an Improvement, adding it to an Urban tile to gain a Specialist, or using it on a pillaged Improvement to Repair the space.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_GROWTH_1_CHAPTER_POP_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Food is the primary driver of population growth. Increase a City’s food supply by setting a connected Town's focus to send additional food to the City.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CONSTRUCTIBLES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Constructibles: Placement</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CONSTRUCTIBLES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>New to Civilization VII, players can now place Constructibles on owned Rural tiles, provided they are connected to an Urban tile or City Center. This action automatically converts the tile into an Urban tile. Two Buildings can typically fit onto a single tile, while Wonders occupy the entire space. However, some buildings, such as Aerodromes, also consume a full tile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CONSTRUCTIBLES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: If a tile is full but contains buildings from a previous Age, you can overbuild the outdated buildings.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FORTIFICATION_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Fortifications</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FORTIFICATION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Fortification is any type of structure that increases the defense of the tile. The most common type of Fortification is Walls, but certain Wonders and Improvements can also be Fortifications.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_FORTIFICATION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Military Units can also create temporary Fortifications, which can help a Unit defend the tile more effectively. Build temporary Fortifications where you know combat will take place, or to protect a critical area. Be warned: once temporary Fortifications are abandoned, they will disappear.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WALLS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Walls</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WALLS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Players can build Walls in Cities or purchase them in both Cities or Towns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WALLS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Wall defenses increase a District's health by 100. Walls from the previous Age provide only half the defense bonus and half the District health, while Walls older than one age provide no benefit. However, Walls from the previous Age can be upgraded by overbuilding them with the current age defenses. Walls are not repaired through the City production queue; they automatically repair over time as long as they are not under attack and have no adjacent enemy Units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WALLS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Wall defenses cannot be purchased with Gold, except in the City Center. Instead, Walls in Districts can be constructed one tile at a time from the City build queue, using Production. Walls cannot be constructed on Navigable River hexes and must be built adjacent to other Walls from the same Settlement, starting with the City Center. Walls cannot be built adjacent to Walls owned by a different Settlement, except in the City Center, which is always allowed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WALLS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>When a Unit attacks a defensible District, combat is resolved by taking the attacking Unit's strength and comparing it to the defense strength of the District, which is calculated based on the strongest melee unit trained by the District owner minus a set value (10). Walls and all City or Town Centers deal reciprocal damage to melee attackers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_WALLS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: To capture a Settlement, attackers must gain control of the City/Town Center and any Districts with walled defenses.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SETTLERS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Settlers</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SETTLERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Settlers are essential for expanding an empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SETTLERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Settlers can be produced or purchased in any Settlement with at least 5 population. You begin with a Founder that is able to found your Capital City, all subsequent Settlers found Towns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SETTLERS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Settlers are civilian units and therefore defenseless. It is wise to escort them with a military unit to ensure their safety.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AGES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Ages</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>History is built in layers. No empire has stood the entire test of time. Instead, successor kingdoms build on the glories of their predecessors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Civilization VII presents each Age as a distinct chapter in human history. Players begin each Age by selecting one of the empires that shone during that period and then earn bonuses that can be applied to future Ages. At the beginning of the next Age, players keep the best features of their previous empire as they prepare to explore an enlarged map. The past shapes each Civ, but opportunities to refashion cities and empires means Players are never locked into a specific gameplay path.	</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Ages harken back to specific times in world history. Cities only contain buildings and wonders that led to the prosperity and civic advancement of the Age. Game systems, such as government, diplomacy, and trade are tailored for each era.	</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Finally, each Age concludes with a race to put your empire on a pedestal as the greatest kingdom of the era. Players race to build the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World or to fill their Great Library with all the knowledge of Antiquity and advances toward these objectives provide bonuses for the next Age.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Buildings can be constructed through the Production Menu in much the same way units are produced. Some buildings have prerequisites, such as technology or location requirements, and are not visible in the Production Menu until those conditions are met. Additionally, buildings can be purchased in Towns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>When a Building is placed down on a Rural tile, the tile will be converted to an [B]Urban Tile[/B]. The tile's natural yield will be lost, retaining only the Building's yields. If the tile is occupied by a point of population, that point of population will be refunded, so you can growth again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>[B]It's important to remember that an Urban Tile has to be placed next to another Urban Tile.[/B]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Non-Warehouse Buildings have scaling costs throughout the game. Their cost increases by 5% for each other non-Warehouse Building in the Settlement, as well as by 10% for each City you have beyond your Capital.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: Some buildings are Ageless, meaning they continue to offer effects regardless of the current Age. Additionally, some buildings have adjacency bonuses, providing extra yields when placed next to specific structures or features.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Warehouses</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Warehouse building provides bonuses based on the number of Improvements of the same type within a Settlement. For example, a Granary grants +1 Food for each Farm, Plantation, or Pasture in the settlement. Each of these Improvements provides the same type of bonus: Food. If you have 2 Farms, 1 Plantation, and 1 Pasture, you’d gain +4 Food from building a Granary.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Warehouse buildings are Ageless and Buildable in all Ages, which means they survive across Age transitions and can be built in any Age. Warehouses tend to provide huge bonuses to Settlements with a lot of Rural Districts, but as Urban Districts encroach on Rural Districts, their effectiveness decreases.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Standard Buildings</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Standard Buildings are the foundational structures available to all civilizations, providing essential yields such as Science, Culture, Production, and more. Unlike Unique Buildings, which are tied to specific civilizations and often come with special bonuses, Standard Buildings are more universally accessible and form the backbone of your infrastructure.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>However, as your civilization progresses through different Ages, Standard Buildings undergo changes. During an Age Transition, these buildings lose their adjacency bonuses, retaining only their base yields. This reduction can significantly impact your city's productivity if not addressed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Despite the loss of adjacency bonuses, Standard Buildings continue to incur maintenance costs. This means they can become economic burdens if not updated or replaced, as they offer diminished returns while still consuming resources.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>To mitigate these issues, the game introduces the Overbuilding mechanic. Overbuilding allows you to construct new, more advanced buildings over existing ones, effectively replacing outdated structures with ones that are better suited to the current Age. This process helps restore or even enhance the adjacency bonuses and yields that were lost during the Age Transition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Regularly assess your cities after each Age Transition. Identify Standard Buildings that have lost their adjacency bonuses and consider overbuilding them with newer structures to maximize efficiency and maintain a strong economy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Unique Buildings</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Civilization VII, some Civs have access to exclusive structures known as Unique Buildings. These Buildings typically offer stronger effects than standard Buildings. When two Unique Buildings from the same Civ are placed on the same tile, they form a Unique Quarter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: While a Unique Quarter provides substantial benefits, it is not mandatory to place both Unique Buildings on the same tile. Spreading Buildings out can sometimes produce higher yields.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Quarters</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Quarter is formed when two non-Wall buildings from the same Age, two Civ Unique Buildings, or a full-tile building occupies a tile. Quarters benefit from various gameplay buffs provided by policies and adjacencies. During a war, all Walled Quarters must be captured for the settlement to be secured.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Place two buildings that provide adjacency bonuses into the same Quarter and assign Specialists to that tile. The Specialists will enhance both buildings.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_6_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Unique Improvements</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Unique Improvements are provided by Civ-specific improvements or City-State Suzerain rewards. These must be built through the production queue and overlaid onto regular improvements. However, some placement restrictions apply, and Unique Improvements cannot be built on all improvements. For example, Step Pyramids can only be placed on tiles with a natural Happiness yield.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Unique Improvements do not remove yield bonuses from basic improvements, so building them over existing basic improvements is beneficial. However, a Unique Improvement does replace other Unique Improvements on the same tile.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_7_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Unique Quarter</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Players can create a "Unique Quarter" when a Civ has two unique buildings on the same tile. This configuration grants the city a special gameplay bonus, which varies depending on the Civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Not only do Unique Quarters provide additional bonuses, they also feature unique art, making them visually stunning!</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_8_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Adjacency</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Adjacency buildings offer bonuses to surrounding tiles, which typically start with a base bonus of 1 but can be enhanced by Specialists. To unlock this bonus, surrounding tiles must meet specific conditions outlined in the production tooltip. These conditions may include placing buildings near or in certain biomes, terrains, quarters, vegetation, wonders, improvements, or constructs with specific yields.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Place buildings next to tiles that meet the adjacency requirements then add Specialists to further boost their yield. This strategy effectively maximizes the yield on a single tile.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_9_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Ageless</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ageless Buildings will continue to be useful in later Ages. They cannot be overbuilt in later Ages, but their yields, effects, tags, and adjacencies will be retained. Typical Ageless Constructibles include Warehouses, Wonders, Unique Buildings, and Unique Improvements. For example, the Mississippian Potkop is Ageless, so it will always give you its base yield of +1 Gold and +1 Food to Adjacent Resources.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Despite being permanent, Ageless Buildings are still useful to build. Be considerate of where you place them, and they will help you keep your competitive edge for future Ages.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_10_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Overbuilding</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most buildings from previous Ages can be overbuilt unless they are tagged as Ageless. This means Players can place a current Age building onto a fully utilized tile as long as that tile contains a qualifying previous Age building. This action removes the lowest yield building on the tile and replaces it with the new building.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Improvements can always be overbuilt with a building.	</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Yield bonuses on Quarters and Adjacencies reset with each Age transition. Overbuilding is a valuable strategy to maximize your tile's potential and reintroduce bonus yields back into Quarters and Adjacencies.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_11_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Maintenance</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most buildings, aside from Warehouse buildings and Wonders, incur maintenance costs in the form of Gold and Happiness. In the Antiquity Age, buildings typically start with a maintenance cost of -2 Gold and -2 Happiness. This cost increases in later Ages, such as -3 Gold and -3 Happiness in the Exploration Age. However, Gold buildings do not have a Gold maintenance cost, and Happiness buildings do not have a Happiness maintenance cost.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: When constructing a lot of buildings, keep a close eye on your Gold and Happiness levels. Building Happiness structures is often essential for maintaining a healthy and expanding empire.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_12_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Full Tile</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most Buildings only take up half of a District; however, some Buildings need a full District to be built. These full-tile Buildings typically perform critical tasks, like launching rockets or transporting Units via Rail.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_13_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Water Building</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Water Building is any structure that requires water to be placed. Examples include the Fishing Quay and Wharf. However, buildings that can be placed on water features but don’t actually depend on it, such as a Granary on a minor river, are not considered Water Buildings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: A general rule of thumb is that if a Building can be placed on Coastal or Navigable River tiles, it’s a Water Building.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_14_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Military Building</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military Buildings act as spawn points for newly trained Units. For example, once the Barracks has been constructed, newly trained land Units will appear there instead of the City Center. Some bonuses only affect Military Buildings.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_15_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Built in Line</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_15_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some Constructibles, like the Ming Great Wall, can link adjacent copies together to create a line. This line cannot fork or intersect with itself. Constructibles that link together will often give bonuses to adjacent copies.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_16_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Mill</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_16_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mills are Buildings that must be placed on a Minor or Navigable River, such as the Gristmill.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_17_TITLE">
			<Text>Buildings: Bridge</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BUILDINGS_17_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Land Units may use Bridges to cross a Navigable River on this tile without embarking. Consider building them in convenient locations to keep your Civilization moving.</Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Policies: Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Social Policies are a key element of the Culture system in Civilization VII, providing various gameplay effects (buffs) to enhance your civilization. Each Civ has unique versions of these policies, known as "Traditions," which are a special subtype within the Social Policy category.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Key Features of Social Policies:[BLIST][LI]Gameplay Effects: Each Social Policy offers one or more gameplay benefits that can significantly impact your civilization’s performance.[LI]Unlocking: Social Policies are unlocked through the Civics of the Culture Progression tree.[LI]Slotting: These policies are slotted into available Social Policy slots within the Government screen. When new slots are added, Social Policies (and Crisis Policies) can be swapped to optimize your strategy.[LI]Traditions: Traditions, which are the unique Social Policies of each Civ, can be carried forward into the next Age, providing continuity and ongoing benefits as your civilization evolves.[LI]Crisis Policies: During times of Crisis, negative policies may appear, which players are forced to slot, accepting the associated negative consequences.[/LIST] </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Common Social Policy effects apply only in the current Age for current Age constructibles and units. Traditions can be slotted and their effect applied in any Age. By strategically managing Social Policies and Traditions, players can tailor their civilization's cultural and political strengths to achieve their desired goals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Policies must be slotted to be effective. Therefore, increasing your Happiness yield to gain more slots from Celebrations is crucial. A strong Culture strategy relies on robust Happiness management.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Policies: Traditions</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Traditions, the unique Social Policies of each Civ, can be carried forward into the next Age, ensuring continuity and ongoing benefits as your Civ evolves. These special policies are marked with a unique icon. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_POLICIES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Invest in Traditions, as they often align with your civilization’s strengths. All of your Traditions will survive into the next Age.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Changing Relationship</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civs have many ways to change their relationship with another Leader. They can initiate or support endeavors with other leaders, which boosts the relationship between both parties.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Alternatively, Players can intentionally lower a relationship by denouncing another Civ. If the relationship worsens sufficiently, Players can declare formal war without using Influence. Conversely, Players can form alliances with leaders if that relationship significantly improves.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Relationships can be influenced in less obvious ways. For example, settling close to another Leader might anger them. Additionally, leaders have Agendas, which can impact their relationships. For instance, having more wonders than Hatshepsut will upset her. You can select a leader's portrait and navigate to the Player info tab to learn about their agenda.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Relationships, positive or negative, will decay over time towards neutral (specifically to a score of 0). The further from neutral the relationship is, the stronger the decay over time will be. This decay is halved with players you are allied or at war with. If you want to keep a specific relationship with a player going, you will need to invest in it!</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- Below used to be LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4 -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: If you care about managing relationships, invest in acquiring Influence. Certain buildings, wonders, policies, and towns grant extra Influence. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Befriending Independents</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In addition to befriending major Civ leaders, Players can also befriend Independent Powers using a diplomatic action called "Befriend Independent." Once the befriending process is complete, the independent power becomes a suzerain City-State, which grants powerful benefits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Spending more Influence can speed up the Befriend Independent action. Outpace other players or someone else might claim an Independent Power’s suzerain status first. The Suzerain status is exclusive to one player!</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Incite Raid</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Incite Raid is a diplomatic action that allows you to direct Independent Powers to launch a raid against another civilization of your choosing. This tactic can be a strategic tool to divert aggression away from your own settlements or to weaken a rival.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To initiate an Incite Raid, locate an Independent Power on the map. Upon interacting with them, you'll have the option to spend Influence to incite a raid. After selecting this option, choose the leader you wish to target. The Independent Power will then prepare to launch a raid against the chosen civilization.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>If the targeted Independent Power lacks sufficient military units to conduct the raid, additional units will be spawned to ensure the raid proceeds. This mechanism ensures that the raid can be executed even if the Independent Power is initially under-resourced.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Use Incite Raid to strategically redirect potential threats away from your empire. By influencing Independent Powers to target rival civilizations, you can create opportunities to strengthen your position or exploit weaknesses in your opponents' defenses.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Trade</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Trading requires foreign Settlements to work at least one resource. In the Antiquity Age and the Exploration Age, your Merchant must physically move to a Settlement before being able to establish a Trade Route. Upon establishing a Trade route, you gain a copy of all the resources in that Settlement, while the other party gains Gold per copy of resource. Multiple copies of a single resource stack additively, increasing benefits like purchase discounts. Settlements must be part of your trade network to share resources, the range of which is expandable by having a Naval building, properly placed Settlements, and a Town Focus. Reassigning resources is only possible when acquiring new ones or expanding resource slots.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Accumulate multiple copies of essential resources, such as Gold, to build stacking bonuses that significantly enhance your Gold power.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Trade Range</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Land-based trade has a default range of 10 tiles in Antiquity, 15 tiles in Exploration, and 20 tiles in Modern, although impassable terrain such as Mountains or Natural Wonders may block routes if no alternate path exists, which makes the route requirement higher. Sea-based trade extends further, covering 30 tiles in Antiquity, 45 tiles in Exploration, and 60 tiles in Modern.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DIPLO_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: You can boost this trade range via Town Focus, Policies, or planting down more in-between Settlements.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Biomes and Features</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civilization VII features five biomes: Grassland, Plains, Desert, Tropical, and Tundra. Each biome has various features, including Floodplain, Forest, Marsh, Savannah Woodland, Watering Hole, Sagebrush Steppe, Oasis, Rainforest, Mangrove Swamp, Taiga, Tundra Bog, Volcano, Ice, Natural Wonder, Aquatic, and Reef. Meanwhile, terrain types include Flat, Rough, River, Mountainous, Coast, and Ocean.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: While terrain and biomes provide some natural yields, more significant yields come from tile improvements that are unlocked and boosted by researching technology.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Rivers</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Civilization VII, rivers are drawn through the middle of hexes and come in two sizes: Navigable Rivers and Minor Rivers. All rivers affect land movement, but Navigable Rivers also support naval movement and specialized city buildings, such as Dockyards and Shipyards. Navigable Rivers are a new terrain type, joining Flat, Rough, Mountain, Coast, and Ocean.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Navigable Rivers represent major real-world rivers like the Nile, Amazon, and Mississippi, which support significant shipping traffic. Land units can cross these rivers without the Embarkation technology, and they support buildings with powerful bonuses, such as those requiring fresh water or water power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Navigable Rivers allow for the construction of Bridges, allowing faster movement across them. They can flood, which damages tiles but also enhances their yields. Navigable Rivers can house both land and naval units, making them strategic arenas for both movement and combat. However, naval units fight at full strength on river tiles, so maintaining a strong naval presence can be crucial.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BIOME_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Navigable Rivers can boost an Empire by providing enhanced yields and supporting crucial buildings. Plan your settlements to maximize these benefits.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Unit Types</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_CHAPTER_MILITARY_TITLE">
			<Text>Military Units</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_CHAPTER_MILITARY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military units can initiate combat and defend against attacks. These include infantry, ranged, Cavalry units, and more. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_CHAPTER_SUPPORT_TITLE">
			<Text>Support Units</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_CHAPTER_SUPPORT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Support units have no combat strength and can be attacked by military units without recourse. Support units offer exploration gameplay and other valuable interactions such as trade. Examples of support units include Settlers, Commanders, and Treasure Convoys.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_CHAPTER_CIVILIAN_TITLE">
			<Text>Civilian Units</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_CHAPTER_CIVILIAN_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civilian units cannot attack, and they cannot explore. They often have other specialized roles. Examples of Civilian Units include Merchants, Religious Units, Explorers, Prospectors and Migrants.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_UNITS_1_CHAPTER_CIVILIAN_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Protect your support and civilian units by keeping them close to military units. This ensures their safety and allows them to carry out their essential roles without disruption.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DEFENSE_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Stationed vs Garrisoned</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DEFENSE_1_CHAPTER_STATIONED_TITLE">
			<Text>Stationed Units</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DEFENSE_1_CHAPTER_STATIONED_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military units located on top of an Urban district without walls are considered Stationed. These units are positioned within the district but do not receive additional defensive benefits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DEFENSE_1_CHAPTER_GARRISONED_TITLE">
			<Text>Garrisoned Units</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DEFENSE_1_CHAPTER_GARRISONED_PARA_1">
			<Text>Military units stationed on top of a Walled Urban district are considered Garrisoned. These units benefit from enhanced defenses, as enemies must first destroy the Wall's HP defenses before they can attack the units stationed there.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_DEFENSE_1_CHAPTER_GARRISONED_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Position your military units in Walled Urban districts to garrison them. This strategic placement enhances their defensive effectiveness, protecting your valuable urban areas from enemy assaults.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Army: Assembling</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To Assemble an Army, select a Commander’s "Assemble" command, which consolidates surrounding units into a single stack. Alternatively, Units can be individually packed into a Commander. While Assembled, the Army moves as a single entity, allowing for streamlined travel across the map. If an Assembled Army is attacked, it defends as a single unit, leveraging the combined strength of all its components. Assembled Armies can initiate attacks and overrun weaker enemy units, but if an Army takes significant damage, it unpacks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Use Assembling to quickly and efficiently move your Army across the map or flank the enemy backline.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Army: Reinforcement</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Reinforcement streamlines moving units across the map. To use this operation, the unit must be a combat unit with full movement, undamaged, at least six tiles from a Commander, in player-owned territory, and their destination Army must not be full. Land units cannot reinforce an embarked Army or cross the open ocean unless they can embark.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>The selected unit travels with its base movement range while ignoring terrain modifiers. Upon arrival, the unit joins the Commander's Army.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Reinforcement is ideal for quickly bolstering your forces without micromanagement. However, remember that a reinforcement unit is unavailable during transit.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Army: Deploying</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When Assembled, the Commander and all the units under them can move as a single unit. They can also add or remove units from the Army, overrun weaker enemies (requires 5:1 combat odds), and promote units within the formation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>When Deployed, the Commander can re-Assemble the units into a stacked formation, order ranged units to focus fire on a specific target, and coordinate melee units to attack simultaneously.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Use Overrun to clear weak enemies efficiently, but make sure to Deploy before a major battle. Utilize Focus Fire and Coordinated Attack to concentrate your offensive power on key targets.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Army: Fleets</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Naval Fleets, commanded by a Fleet Commander, can Assemble into a single stack, Deploy into adjacent tiles, execute naval focus fire, and perform coastal bombardments. They can also escort packed Armies across bodies of water.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Use Fleet Commanders to escort units across the water and coordinate powerful coastal bombardments.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_6_TITLE">
			<Text>Army: Air Squadrons</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Air Squadrons, commanded by a Squadron Commander, can Establish Air Bases on flat tiles with no Urban District that are not owned by another player. They can patrol to intercept enemy aircraft, conduct reconnaissance to reveal an area, execute carpet bombs, perform air strikes, rebase to nearby air bases, and airdrop infantry units to selected hexes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ARMY_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Use Air Squadrons to gain strategic reconnaissance and provide rapid support to land operations with air strikes.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PILLAGING_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Pillaging</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PILLAGING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Both improvements and buildings can be pillaged. Once pillaged, their benefits vanish, and the unit that performed the pillaging receives a reward, or “plunder,” based on the structure it pillaged – these rewards, except for healing, increase in magnitude throughout the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PILLAGING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Pillaging exhausts a Land Unit’s movement and allows one tile to be pillaged at a time. Naval Units can pillage multiple times a turn. Urban tiles with two buildings must be pillaged one building at a time, starting with the highest-yield building. Once a building is pillaged, it cannot be pillaged again until it is repaired by its owner. Repairs can be completed through the Production Menu and require 25% of the building’s initial construction cost.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PILLAGING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: If you are locked in for a long war, use pillaging to heal your units and disrupt your opponent's economy and infrastructure to gain an advantage over time.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Ranged Combat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ranged units do not suffer reciprocal damage when attacking, making them an excellent choice to pair with melee frontline units. However, ranged units are vulnerable to melee units, especially cavalry, which gain combat strength while attacking ranged units. Ranged units have a melee strength stat, which is used to calculate the damage they take when defending against melee attacks. However, ranged units’ melee strength is typically low.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Damaged units lose some of their combat strength. The ability to attack without taking reciprocal damage is one of the greatest advantages of ranged combat.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Terrain Combat Modifier</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In battle, the type of terrain can help or hurt your units. Each natural feature adds or subtracts a bonus to a unit’s defensive combat strength. Here’s a simple guide:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Vegetated Areas: Forests, woodlands, and similar features give your units a +2 bonus in combat when defending.[LI]Wet Areas: Bogs, oasis, and other wet features lower your defensive combat strength by 2.[LI]Hills: If a tile is a hill, it provides extra defense—currently a bonus of +3.[LI]Navigable Rivers: Naval units can sail on these without trouble. However, land units must embark (board a boat) to cross safely.[LI]Minor Rivers: These slow you down in combat. Attacking from a minor river tile gives your unit a penalty, and defending from one also makes your unit less effective.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Generally speaking, you would not want to defend on water tiles, while you’d get increased protection from standing on vegetated tiles and hills. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Air Combat</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Air units fall into one of three categories: Fighters, Ground Attackers and Bombers. Fighters are strongest against other air units, Ground Attackers are strongest against Land and Sea units and Bombers are strongest against Fortifications.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Fighters have the unique ability to Intercept. When an enemy air unit attempts an action near a tile where Fighters are present one Fighter will automatically Intercept and attack the enemy unit and will receive a combat bonus for each additional Fighter packed with that Fighter.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Air units are always tied to a Commander: either an Aerodrome Commander, Squadron Commander or Aircraft Carrier. Air Units can use the Rebase action to move from one Commander to another that is within range, but cannot move on their own. Instead, their Movement determines the range of their actions. Air units cannot Rebase to a Squadron Commander until that Squadron Commander has used its Establish Air Base action. Air units cannot be built or purchased unless there are available slots on a Commander in that settlement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Air units can attack while packed in a Commander by selecting them individually or all Air units of a single type can attack together by using the Commander's Focused Attack. Eligible targets for an attack will be highlighted on the map. Enemy units can only be attacked if they are visible but districts can be attacked as long as they have been explored.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_9_TITLE">
			<Text>Flanking</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once two units engage in combat, they are locked in a “front,” allowing additional attackers to strike from the sides or rear. Flanking bonuses scale by angle: front-left or front-right angles grant +2, back-left or back-right grant +3, and a direct rear attack provides +5. Certain civilizations, like the Mongols, can amplify these bonuses further (e.g., +50%).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Position multiple units to encircle foes from different angles, maximizing the flanking bonus and gaining a decisive combat edge. In Antiquity, you will need to research the Military Training technology to unlock the Flanking mechanic.</Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Intercept</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Intercept is a PASSIVE ability that allows fighter-class units to engage enemy aircraft attempting to attack locations, units, or other targets within their intercept range, which is set to 3 tiles by default. Aerodrome extends this range by 1 for Fighters stationed inside, which provides a City better air protection. When an enemy aircraft initiates an attack within this range, it first engages in combat with the interceptor. Only if the attacking aircraft survives the interception does it proceed to strike its intended target.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Interceptors continue to intercept any incoming aircraft as long as they remain alive, providing sustained air defense coverage for nearby assets. This ability makes fighter units valuable for defending high-priority targets against enemy airstrikes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Special Case for Nuclear Bombers: Bombers on nuclear missions are always successful in their drops, but if their health drops below 50, they will fail their nuke drop.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Place interceptors strategically to cover critical areas, ensuring they have overlapping ranges for maximum defense. Interceptors are essential for neutralizing enemy air threats and protecting ground forces and infrastructure from aerial assaults.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_10_TITLE">
			<Text>Fighter Sweep</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>A Fighter Sweep draws out and damages—or even destroys—enemy fighters, paving the way for a safer bombing run. By assigning your fighter units to a Squadron Commander, you can use the Sweep ability on a target location, forcing defending fighters to intercept. Once these hostile aircraft have been engaged or eliminated, your bombers can operate with far less risk.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Always perform a Fighter Sweep to reduce or eliminate enemy air defenses before sending in your bombers, especially your nuclear bombers.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_6_TITLE">
			<Text>Amphibious</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Amphibious ability allows a unit to ignore the usual Combat Strength penalty when attacking while Embarked, meaning it uses its full default strength in combat against opponents. Additionally, units with Amphibious pay no movement cost to embark or disembark, allowing them to seamlessly transition between land and water without losing mobility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Amphibious units are highly effective for coastal assaults and quick transitions between land and sea, enabling you to maintain full combat strength when attacking from water. Use them strategically to launch unexpected attacks and gain the upper hand in coastal engagements.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_TITLE">
			<Text>Embark</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When a unit embarks to traverse water tiles, it adopts a standardized combat strength that scales with the ages, rather than using its default land-based strength. Embarked units have 5 Combat Strength in the Antiquity Age, 25 Combat Strength in the Exploration Age, and 50 Combat Strength in the Modern Age. This means that while they can defend themselves, they are generally more vulnerable compared to their strength on land.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A land unit's embarked movement speed is determined by Age (plus any bonus modifiers) and is independent from their normal land movement speed. The base embarked movement speed is 2 in Antiquity, and 3 in later Ages.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Use Embark for quick water crossings, but avoid leaving units exposed on open water, as their reduced combat strength makes them susceptible to attacks. Prioritize Amphibious units for coastal operations if you need full combat strength on water.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_8_TITLE">
			<Text>Fortify</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Fortify action allows a unit to build temporary fortifications on its current tile, taking 2 turns to complete by default. Once fortifications are in place, the unit gains a +6 Combat Strength bonus when defending. This defensive bonus aligns with that of improvement fortifications like the Hillfort or Shore Battery, providing a solid defense boost against enemy attacks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Use Fortify in strategic locations, especially in vulnerable areas or chokepoints, to strengthen your defense. Units in fortified positions can withstand attacks more effectively, making them valuable for holding critical territory.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_11_TITLE">
			<Text>Splash</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When attacking with a Unit that has the Splash ability, enemy Units in tiles adjacent to the target tile will also take 50% damage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Splash damage is great for those big, stubborn groups of enemies. The 50% applied damage to enemy Units adjacent to the target make it a technique that can break up tightly-formed blockades.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_12_TITLE">
			<Text>Stealth</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Stealth Units are invisible to all enemy Units by default. Until the attack an enemy unit, end their turn adjacent to an enemy unit, or an enemy unit enters their location, the stealthed unit will be hidden from view on the map.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_COMBAT_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Keeping an eye on other Civs with Stealth Units can be useful in a number of ways outside of surprise combat. Watching foreign Wonder building progress, scouting target Military formations, and more can better inform your next move.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TECH_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Technologies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TECH_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Technologies represent new scientific advancements or inventions for your civilization. Each researched technology unlocks new buildings, units, and other advancements, enhancing the power and capabilities of an empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TECH_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Technologies are developed through a continuous research process, driven by the Science yield.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TECH_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Selecting a Tech or Civic deeper in the tree will queue up the pre-requisite nodes for you automatically.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TECH_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Focusing on technology research is an excellent way to gain a military advantage, as most military units are locked behind technologies.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CIVIC_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Civics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CIVIC_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Civics are similar to technologies in that they are also researched; however they use the Culture yield to progress. Civics can unlock wonders, units, and buildings. Unlike technologies, Civics often provide Policies and Traditions that can be slotted into a Government.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CIVIC_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Selecting a Tech or Civic deeper in the tree will queue up the pre-requisite nodes for you automatically.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CIVIC_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: While Civics unlock Policies that can be slotted, Happiness ultimately grants extra slots. Maintain a balanced focus on both!</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MASTERIES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Masteries</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MASTERIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Both Techs and Civics offer players opportunities to research Masteries. After a Tech or Civic is researched, a tier two Tech or Civic sometimes become available. These are called Masteries, and they grant additional bonuses that unlock new constructibles and codices.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MASTERIES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Masteries are often essential for Science or Culture legacies. Prioritize them to strengthen your civilization’s focus in these areas.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Towns and Economy</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Towns automatically convert their production into Gold income, making them a crucial part of your economy. Expansion leads to additional income, but this comes with increased risk as you might anger neighboring Leaders and Independents.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Expanding your towns boosts your economy, but be mindful that you don’t exceed the Settlement cap.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Fresh Water</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Establishing a Settlement on Fresh Water, identified by blue tiles in the Settler Lens, grants a permanent +5 Happiness bonus. You can toggle the Settler Lens via the icon above the minimap to spot these ideal locations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Settle on Fresh Water whenever possible to maintain higher Happiness and reduce Unhappiness in your Settlements. An Unhappy Settlement takes a penalty to all of its yields, with each point of negative Happiness causing a 2% overall reduction.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Appeal</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Similar to Civilization VI, land tiles may have an “appealing” quality that influences Happiness. Water and navigable rivers are never appealing themselves, but they can boost the appeal of adjacent tiles, as can Mountains, especially in the later Ages. If at least three of the six surrounding hexes are appealing, the tile gains +1 Happiness in Antiquity, +2 in Exploration, and +3 in Modern. Placing a population on such a tile secures its Happiness bonus for your Settlement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Look for clusters of scenic terrain when expanding, since appealing tiles provide notable long-term Happiness boosts.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Migrant Gameplay</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Migrants appear through various Narrative events, Wonder effects, and Policy cards—but most often, they show up when a Settlement has grown as much as it can. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>When a Settlement runs out of Rural tiles to improve and has no available Specialist slots, a migrant will appear during a growth event, and the growth requirement will increase as usual. You can then use a migrant in any Settlement that still has open Rural tiles, though they can only improve these tiles and cannot serve as Specialists. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: You need to walk your Migrants to a Settlement before activating them. Once activated, they cannot be taken out again.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_6_TITLE">
			<Text>Unrest</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When you capture a Settlement, it falls into unrest for several turns, causing unhappiness and stopping it from building or buying anything. Any captured Settlement also downgrades into a Town.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Placing a commander in the Settlement will help lower this unhappiness. If you conquer a Settlement that originally belonged to you, all unrest penalties disappear because the city is considered liberated.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Gaining Settlements through peace deals avoids unrest, so sometimes it's smart to mix diplomacy with your military actions.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_7_TITLE">
			<Text>Urban Population</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Urban Population counts only the citizens generated by constructing buildings—it does not include Specialists. This number matters because several bonuses depend on it. Here are a couple of examples:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Abbasid's Mamluk: +1 Combat Strength for every Urban Population.[LI]Inca Tradition: Settlements receive +0.5 Gold for every Urban Population.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Focus on constructing buildings to boost your Urban Population when playing Civs that benefit from it.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_8_TITLE">
			<Text>Starvation</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Starvation is uncommon in Civilization VII, thanks to the new approach to managing Food. Unlike previous games, only Specialists require Food upkeep—regular Rural and Urban populations do not. However, starvation can still occur under specific conditions, such as having too many Specialists or when your Settlement suffers from very low Happiness.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>If your Settlement’s net Food output turns negative, starvation may begin to set in. When starvation fully sets in, it will harm your Settlement by lowering Happiness and destroying one of its buildings or improvements. Always keep an eye on your Food supply and Settlement Happiness to avoid the consequences of starvation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: If your City is starving, consider specializing a connected Town to help feed it. If low Happiness is the issue, stationing a high-level Commander in the City can significantly reduce the Unhappiness it generates. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_9_TITLE">
			<Text>Land and Territory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Owned Tile: A tile within your Settlement’s borders.[LI]Unowned Tile: A tile that is not yet part of any Settlement’s borders.[LI]Improved Tile: A Rural tile with an improvement (worked by a population point).[LI]Unimproved Tile: A Rural tile without an improvement (no population assigned to it).[LI]Friendly Tile: A tile you own, or owned by your allied Civs and City-States.[LI]Neutral Tile: A tile not owned by any Civilization.[LI]Enemy Tile: A tile owned by a Civilization you are at war with.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TOWN_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: A lot of effects function according to these tile types. Make sure to check what type of tile a specific effect mentions when making a decision.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MERCHANTS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Merchants</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MERCHANTS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Merchants can travel to other leaders’ settlements to establish trade routes, gaining access to their resources. Merchants are also useful in building roads within an empire. Merchants go away after each Age Transition. Make sure to research the corresponding tech/civic to unlock Merchants again after every Age Transition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MERCHANTS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>In Antiquity and Exploration Age, your Merchants must first move into other Civilizations' borders, before being able to use the create trade route function. There's no such limitation in the Modern Age. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MERCHANTS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Merchants are your primary method for acquiring foreign resources. Use them strategically to strengthen your economy and complete certain legacy paths. Additionally, you can use Merchants to build roads within your Empire, which can help you connect Towns to Cities in order to feed them.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CAP_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Settlement Cap</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CAP_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>At a player level, there is a Settlement Cap. This cap is a soft cap that reduces the player's yields when the player goes over that cap. The penalty is 5 Unhappiness per settlement over the cap applied to all Settlements. This is capped at 35. The Unhappiness in turn reduces the yields via its yield reduction effects. The Settlement Cap can be increased via Tech, civic, and attribute trees. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CAP_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Razed Settlements do not count towards the cap, however, they incur other penalties.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CAP_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Staying under the cap is key to maintaining a Happy and Productive empire.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Razing</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When a Settlement is captured, the capturer can choose to raze it. Razing a Settlement requires multiple turns to accomplish, and the number of turns correlates to the size (population) of the Settlement. Tiles are razed from the farthest tiles to center. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Razing incurs a -2 influence per age penalty for rest of the age. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Once the process of Razing has started, it cannot be stopped whatsoever. Once a player starts to raze a settlement it cannot be stopped by that player, regardless of diplomatic status.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Razing is an effective way to stay under the Settlement cap if you decide to go Warmongering. However, be wary of its negative consequences.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Burning Status</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some attacks or effects inflict a Burning status on a tile, dealing a flat 15 damage per turn to any unit standing there. This damage is unaffected by either the attacker’s or defender’s combat strength, and the duration depends on the specific source. For instance, the Burning Arrow unit states a two-turn duration in its description.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAZING_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip:  Move units off burning tiles quickly to avoid taking significant damage over multiple turns.</Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SPECIALIST_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Specialist</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SPECIALIST_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Assigning a point of population to an Urban tile creates a Specialist. Specialists amplify the tile's adjacency bonuses and offer benefits like increased Science, Culture, and building adjacency yields (+2 Science, +2 Culture, +0.5 Adjacency Bonus). However, they come with a trade-off, reducing the City’s Food and Happiness by -2 each.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SPECIALIST_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>While Towns can acquire Urban tiles by purchasing buildings, only Cities have the ability to gain Specialists, making them unique centers for advancing Science, Culture, and other key yields.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_SPECIALIST_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Strategically place Specialists in high-adjacency Urban tiles to maximize yield boosts. Keep an eye on Food and Happiness, as Specialists can strain resources in rapidly growing Cities.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_OCEAN_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Ocean Exploration</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_OCEAN_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Civilization VII, ocean movement varies depending on the type of water tile. Dark blue tiles represent open ocean and function similarly to rough land tiles, consuming all movement points and ending a unit's action until Shipbuilding is researched. Light blue tiles indicate coastal waters, which act like flat land tiles. Units in coastal waters can move and heal using their full movement points.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_OCEAN_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Units ending their turn on open ocean tiles will take damage due to ocean attrition unless Shipbuilding has been researched. This mechanic adds an element of risk to early ocean exploration, making technological advancements essential for safe passage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_OCEAN_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>On higher difficulty levels, AI civilizations suffer less damage from ocean attrition, making them more resilient during early exploration.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_OCEAN_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Research Cartography early to allow your Settlers to cross the ocean. However, your Cog unit can explore the ocean as early as turn 1 of the Exploration Age.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ROAD_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Roads</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ROAD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Roads are automatically created between nearby settlements upon their establishment, allowing for efficient unit movement. Merchants can also be deployed to manually build roads. When a Town is connected to a City via roads, it can support the City by feeding it once it specializes, enhancing the City's growth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ROAD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Use Merchants strategically to establish road connections between key settlements, especially if the automatic road network is insufficient. This will enable better urban growth.</Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAILROAD_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Railroad</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAILROAD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Railroads provide fast travel between settlements in Civilization VII, enhancing logistical efficiency across your empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAILROAD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To build a railroad, ensure that two settlements are connected by roads and that each has its own Rail Station. Once both Rail Stations are built, the railroad connection is established, allowing for rapid movement between the connected settlements.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAILROAD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Units positioned adjacent to a Rail Station can travel to another Rail Station within 20 tiles in a single turn. This travel consumes all of the unit's movement points for that turn, but it allows for quick relocation across your empire, significantly boosting strategic flexibility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAILROAD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Strategically place Rail Stations in key settlements to create an efficient transportation network, allowing your units to quickly respond to threats or reinforce distant regions. Rail Station is also a requirement for the Railroad Tycoon Legacy Path.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RAILROAD_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: To connect a large empire, you will likely need to build Ports. Ports can connect Rail Stations that are split by water.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Religion Overview</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Pantheon plays the role of proto-religion the Antiquity Age, players unlock their first Pantheon by researching the Mysticism civic. Pantheons provide unique bonuses often related to natural features and lay the foundation for religious gameplay. Constructing an Altar enables players to benefit from their Pantheon.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Religion becomes available in the Exploration Age. You can start a Religion by completing the Piety Civic and building a Temple. It provides various Belief types:[BLIST][LI]Enhancer: the Enhancer Belief aids in spreading the player’s religion. Each player may have only one Enhancer Belief.[LI]Reliquary: this Belief type allows players to earn Relics, which can be displayed for bonuses. Players may have only one Reliquary Belief.[LI]Founder: awarded initially upon founding a religion, with two additional Founder Beliefs awarded later, for a maximum of three. Founder Beliefs offer yields and other benefits for converting foreign settlements, incentivizing active religious spread.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>A Holy City is the birthplace of a player's religion. This city serves as a stronghold for the player’s chosen faith.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Converting most settlements to your religion requires 2 Missionary charges. However, if the settlement has zero rural population or is being converted for the first time, only 1 charge is needed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: Focus on settlements with no existing religious influence to maximize your Missionary charges and establish a strong religious presence early.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Religious Gameplay</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Missionaries only spread their founder’s religion, and opponents’ Holy Cities CAN be converted to your religion. Independent Peoples cannot adopt a religion until they become City-States. Additional Founder Beliefs are extremely rare and often triggered by random events. There are two Religion flags on the City banner of each Settlement affected by Religion. Both flags need to match, in order for the Settlement to be considered as converted. One flag represents Urban religion, while the other flag represents Rural religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_RELIGION_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Being the first to spread Religion to a Settlement converts both flags at the same time. If a Settlement already has a Religion, you will need to convert an Urban tile and a Rural tile to accomplish the conversion.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BANKRUPTCY_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Bankruptcy</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BANKRUPTCY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>If your gold income is negative, you risk bankruptcy. When the treasury balance falls below zero while your income is negative, units with the highest maintenance costs will disband one by one until the balance is restored. This can severely impact military and economic stability, so maintaining a positive income is essential.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BANKRUPTCY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Keep an eye on maintenance costs when expanding your military or building new structures. Avoiding bankruptcy is crucial for sustained growth and security.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CONNECTED_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Connected Settlements</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CONNECTED_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Connected Settlements facilitate resource and food management between Cities and Towns. There are two types of connections:[BLIST][LI]Trade Connections: Settlements within trade range can freely move resources between them. This connection is ideal for distributing resources across the empire.[LI]Road and Sea Connections: Settlements are linked directly by roads or are both coastal and on the same continent. Towns connected to Cities this way can feed those Cities when selecting a Town Focus.[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CONNECTED_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Establish trade and road connections early to optimize resource movement and enable Towns to support City growth. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PIRATING_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Pirating</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PIRATING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Some Units have the [icon:UNIT_CAUTION] Pirate ability, or gain it from a Civilization or Leader ability. Units that have the [icon:UNIT_CAUTION] Pirate ability can attack other Naval Units and pillage tiles of Civilizations they are not at War with for a Relationship penalty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_PIRATING_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Pirating, while lucrative, still decreases Relationship with the target Civilization or Independent Power. Be careful who you push around! </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ONEMORE_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Just One More Turn</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ONEMORE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Just One More Turn mode allows you to continue your game beyond victory, giving you the freedom to keep exploring, building, and shaping the world even after your story officially concludes. Whether you want to admire your accomplishments, further develop your empire, or simply enjoy the gameplay without pressure, Just One More Turn lets you extend the experience at your leisure.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ONEMORE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>After you reach the end of the final age, you'll see the "Just One More Turn" option alongside your victory summary. Selecting it keeps your game running, allowing you to resume play right away.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ONEMORE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>In this mode, you've already won, so additional victories won't end your game, though you can still complete legacy paths and enjoy their special cinematics and achievements.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_ONEMORE_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: You'll always know you're in Just One More Turn mode thanks to a persistent reminder at the top left of your screen. When you're finally ready to conclude your adventure, simply exit to the main menu. There's always one more turn waiting for you if you want it!</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TURNEND_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Force-Ending Turns (PC-Only)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TURNEND_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>By pressing Shift + Enter on PC, you can ignore all turn-blocking notifications and immediately end your turn. Please keep in mind that this practice is mostly used when you are stuck, and it’s often controversial in multiplayer due to potential exploits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TURNEND_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Avoid using this mechanic if playing competitively.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TEAMPLAY_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Team Play</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TEAMPLAY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Multiplayer, players can form teams. To set this up, players should select the same team in the team dropdown menu when creating a multiplayer game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TEAMPLAY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>When playing on a team, teammates are locked into an Alliance that cannot be broken and are locked at the max Relationship level. Unlike a standard Alliance, teammates share map visibility. Teammates may use Diplomatic Actions with one another but are prohibited from using Espionage Actions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TEAMPLAY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Teammates share a Relationship status, and a War and Alliance status, with all other players and teams. When negotiating peace, one player from each team will manage the negotiations. Once a deal is reached, all other players on each team will make peace automatically with no further exchanges.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TEAMPLAY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>If one player on a team achieves a Victory, all teammates share in the Victory. If there is a Score Victory, the total Legacy Point count for all teammates are combined for their score.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_TEAMPLAY_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Note: Technology and Civic progress, and Legacy Path progress, is [B]not[/B] shared between teammates.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Legends System</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The [B]Legends[/B] system is Civilization VII's meta-progression framework, tracking your accomplishments across all your games. It recognizes your feats and turns your cumulative successes into lasting rewards. Through this system, each game adds to your achievements, unlocking both cosmetic customizations and gameplay-enhancing items known as [B]Mementos[/B].</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Legends consist of four interconnected parts: Legend Challenges, Legend Paths, Legend XP, and Mementos. Together, they ensure that every game matters, encouraging diverse strategies and rewarding consistent play. Whether you win, lose, or try something entirely new, you steadily build toward something bigger than any single match.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Treat Legends as a rewarding extra layer rather than a mandatory system. Play your way, experiment freely, and you'll naturally find yourself unlocking bonuses and enhancing your civilization’s long-term capabilities.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Legends XP</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Legend XP is the currency that drives progression within the Legends system, gained exclusively by completing Legend Challenges. Each completed challenge awards a certain amount of XP toward its corresponding Legend Path: Foundation Challenges reward XP for your global Foundation Path, while Leader Challenges boost specific Leader Paths.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>The amount of XP earned depends on a challenge's complexity. Crucially, this XP accumulates even if you lose the game, meaning every match contributes to your overall Legends progression, win or lose. There's no shortcut—only gameplay accomplishments earn Legend XP, making each achievement feel valuable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Don’t abandon tough matches early. Completing a few extra challenges can still provide valuable Legend XP, making your efforts worthwhile even in defeat.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Legend Challenges</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Legend Challenges are special objectives you can complete while playing Civilization VII. These tasks act like quests or achievements, offering clear goals that range from simple feats like constructing your first Wonder to ambitious achievements such as dominating a victory type. Challenges come in two forms: Foundation Challenges, which can be completed with any leader, and Leader Challenges, unique to specific leaders and their abilities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Whenever you fulfill the conditions of a challenge, you immediately earn Legend XP. This XP advances your Legend Paths, making each completed challenge meaningful—even if your current match isn’t going well. You can easily track your ongoing and completed challenges through the Challenge Log, helping you target goals aligned with your strategy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Regularly check your Challenges Log. Completing even a few objectives can turn a losing game into progress for your long-term Legend growth.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Legend Paths</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_BASICS_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1">
			<Text>Legend Paths represent your overall advancement within Civilization VII's Legends system. They function like experience tracks, leveling up as you earn Legend XP by completing Legend Challenges. There are two main types: the universal [B]Foundation Path[/B] and specialized [B]Leader Paths[/B] specific to each leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_2">
			<Text>Balance your efforts between different paths to maximize your long-term benefits. The Foundation Path offers broad rewards, while Leader Paths grant specialized advantages.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_FOUNDATION_TITLE">
			<Text>Foundation Path</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_FOUNDATION_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Foundation Path tracks your progress across all your games, regardless of leader choice. It has 50 levels, each unlocking various rewards, such as cosmetic profile upgrades (badges, banners, titles) and powerful gameplay bonuses called [B]Mementos[/B]. Importantly, leveling this path also unlocks [B]Memento Slots[/B], essential for equipping these bonuses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_FOUNDATION_PARA_2">
			<Text>Prioritize early levels in your Foundation Path to quickly unlock your first Memento Slots, significantly enhancing your gameplay options.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_LEADER_TITLE">
			<Text>Leader Path</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_LEADER_PARA_1">
			<Text>Each leader in Civilization VII has their own unique Leader Path, which levels up through Leader Challenges specific to their abilities and history. Leader Paths go up to level 10, offering leader-themed Mementos, cosmetic items, and special gameplay advantages tailored to their playstyle.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_4_CHAPTER_LEADER_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Experiment with different leaders regularly to unlock a diverse set of Leader Path rewards. Mementoes unlocked for one leader can be used with any other leaders as well. Pairing specialized mementoes with their respective leaders can often unlock powerful synergies.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Mementos</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_TITLE">
			<Text>Basics</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1_SENTENCE_1">
			<Text>Mementos are special items earned from your Legends progression, which can be equipped before each game to provide unique in-game bonuses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1_SENTENCE_2">
			<Text>They function like gear for your leader, giving effects ranging from basic stat boosts to situational advantages. Every leader can equip up to two Mementos, offering powerful strategic flexibility.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1_SENTENCE_1} {LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1_SENTENCE_2}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_2">
			<Text>Carefully choose your Mementos before starting a game, matching them to your desired victory type or compensating for your leader's weaknesses. [B]Keep in mind that Mementos can also be swapped between Ages.[/B]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_UNLOCK_TITLE">
			<Text>Unlocking and Collection</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_UNLOCK_PARA_1">
			<Text>You unlock Mementos by reaching specific milestones within your Legend Paths. Some Mementos come from higher Foundation Path levels, while many are leader-specific rewards earned by progressing through Leader Paths. Once unlocked, they permanently join your collection and can be freely equipped by any leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_UNLOCK_PARA_2">
			<Text>Unlocking a variety of Mementos by playing multiple leaders can significantly broaden your strategic options, even if you later return to your favorite leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_STRAT_TITLE">
			<Text>Strategies and Synergies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_STRAT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The variety of nearly 100 unique Mementos allows for extensive strategic combinations. Some offer straightforward bonuses, such as extra Economic or Cultural points at game start, while others trigger situationally, like spawning free units after successful espionage actions. Cleverly combining Mementos can lead to powerful or unique strategies, amplifying your strengths or mitigating weaknesses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_STRAT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Tip: Experiment with different Memento combinations to discover powerful synergies. An unexpected pairing might provide just the advantage you need for your chosen victory path.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MEMENTOS_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_TITLE}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MEMENTOS_CHAPTER_BASICS_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_TITLE}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1_SENTENCE_1_APPLE_ARCADE">
			<Text>Mementos are special items, which can be equipped before each game to provide unique in-game bonuses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MEMENTOS_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1_SENTENCE_1_APPLE_ARCADE} {LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_1_SENTENCE_2}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MEMENTOS_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_2">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_BASICS_PARA_2}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MEMENTOS_CHAPTER_STRAT_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_STRAT_TITLE}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MEMENTOS_CHAPTER_STRAT_PARA_1">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_STRAT_PARA_1}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MEMENTOS_CHAPTER_STRAT_PARA_2">
			<Text>{LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_LEGENDS_5_CHAPTER_STRAT_PARA_2}</Text>
		</Row>

	</EnglishText>
</Database>