<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- BIOMES -->
		<!-- BIOME_TUNDRA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TUNDRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Tundra” refers to the terrain extending from polar regions toward the equator (at times, downward from the peaks of tall mountains). In these places, the ground is often permanently frozen, and the landscape remains too cold for trees. Atop a bare strip of thawed soil sit plains of moss or heath, where migrating caribou or reindeer graze on lichen (and are pursued by wolves). This would seem to be a lifeless place, but a great quantity of life abounds – under the soil. Trapped in permafrost are vast stores of plant material, storing carbon that threatens to be released once the tundra warms. People who make their home in the tundra include the Sami of Scandinavia, Finland, and Russia, the Nenets of Siberia, and the Inuit and Yupik people of Alaska and Canada. These peoples have had to adapt to the harsh climate by herding reindeer (in Europe and Siberia) or by hunting sea mammals (in North America). Tundra also exists on the Antarctic Peninsula, though most of the continent is simply too cold for life.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TUNDRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Taiga </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TUNDRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The largest biome on Earth, the boreal forest (or taiga to use the Russian word), extends across the subpolar region, from Hokkaido to Canada, Finland, and all through Russia. This expanse of conifer forests is thick and tall in the south and low and hardy at the northern extreme. Despite the forest cover, taiga is a harsh environment. Not only are the temperatures a challenge, but the limited amount of nutrition hampers the fauna that make it their home. These fauna include moose, wolves, bears, and a few varieties of rodents – all mammals with thick coats and often massive bodies, where size comes with attendant warmth. The taiga’s slow processes and extensive peatland mean that it stores more carbon than temperate forests, but the taiga is changing along with the climate, as forests creep northward.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TUNDRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Bog</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TUNDRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Water seems a bit unusual when ice is the predominant feature most of the year. During the few months of summer, the tundra radically alters; lakes, streams, and bogs emerge from under the frozen land. In the cold, treeless tundra, these lakes provide shelter for migratory birds. In the warmer, vegetated taiga, peat traps rainwater and creates bogs – especially in regions such as western Siberia or the lower Yukon. Here, the black, acidic water and relative lack of nutrients foster a unique ecosystem, one with carnivorous plants and thick mats of sphagnum, often visited by large grazers, such as moose. In some parts of Europe, an odd feature of these bogs is the preservative quality of the water – bodies dumped into the bog during the Iron Age are sometimes found amazingly intact, though dyed black from long exposure to the tannin-rich water.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- BIOME_DESERT -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If water is the source of life, the desert is death; its name in English stems from “abandoned,” or “deserted.” Without water, vegetation is sparse, and without vegetation, soil is rare (soil being the accumulation of decomposing plant matter). Desert plants, as few of them as there are, learn many tricks to survive – tumbleweeds make do without soil, moving across the landscape. Cacti thrive where they can, but have long since shed their leaves for spines as adaptations to protect against water loss. Animals also adapt to survive – camels store water in their fatty humps while certain species of insects and seemingly water-dependent animals such as toads and shrimp live their lives in brief bursts during infrequent rains. Humans have had a long relationship with the desert, with groups such as the Bedouin perfecting the art of moving from shelter to shelter, treating the open desert as sailors do the sea.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Sahara is the largest desert in the world, but it is not the driest. Surprisingly, Antarctica contains some of the driest places on Earth, where rain is never known to have fallen, and even microscopic life fails to live in the permafrost. The Atacama desert in Chile (not the Sahara) is the driest place outside of the poles, acquiring all its moisture by morning fog.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Sagebrush steppe </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Certain areas in the desert hold more than nothingness and sand. In areas where some moisture is present – even foggy or dewy – plants bloom. This includes shrubs such as sagebrush (in the Intermountain West) or acacia (in the African Sahel). It is a small step from this “sagebrush steppe” to the “plains”, but this transition is perfectly exemplified in the move from the Sahel to the geographic region known as the Sudan (not to be confused with the country by the name of Sudan).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Oasis </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_DESERT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Deserts are defined by their lack of water, but what if water were present, in quantities small enough that it did not constitute a wholesale change of biome? This is an oasis, a tiny point where water from an underground aquifer or underground river emerges into the desert, creating pockets of life. These spaces become the heart of desert civilization. Oasis (and riparian, and coastal) life often existed in tandem with that of the high desert – one can imagine the mutual relationship between the roving Bedouin and the settled Arabs in the Middle East.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- BIOME_GRASSLAND -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_GRASSLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The temperate regions of the world that receive a fair degree of rain are familiar to many. This includes the region of central China, the island of Japan, the east coast of North America, nearly all of Europe, and northern and upland stretches of India. These highly seasonal areas allow for a cycle of plant growth and death, creating a buildup of fertile soil that is good for agriculture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_GRASSLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Deciduous Forest </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_GRASSLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The forests in these areas are dominated by trees that shed their leaves in winter. The eastern United States, most of Europe, New Zealand/Aotearoa, and much of East Asia are highly seasonal places, where the landscape can change dramatically throughout the year – or they have been before chainsaws and concrete covered their forests. Their seasonality affects animals as well. Each species has its own way of dealing with the climate: some mammals hibernate, some birds migrate, and some cold-blooded creatures go dormant. Likewise, humans adapt. The indigenous peoples in the American Midwest split into roving bands to hunt deer during the winter, re-congregating into agricultural communities during the warm seasons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_GRASSLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Marsh </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_GRASSLAND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Where the land is covered almost entirely by shallow water, marshes and swamps emerge – the latter has trees while the former does not. The water in a marsh may be salty, brackish, or fresh (especially in river deltas), but they serve important ecological roles, protecting young fish or crustaceans, concealing mammals, and providing shelter from storms that batter coasts with sharp edges. Examples of marshes include the Okavango Delta in Botswana, the Everglades of Florida, or the low-lying strips of land along the coastlines of the United States and Scandinavia, whereas wet forests like the Great Dismal Swamp are, clearly, swamps.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- BIOME_PLAINS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_PLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word grassland evokes images of glades and meadows: misty Irish hills, the Kanto grass sea. While a grassland is one variety of plains, there is a distinction between the more fertile grassland and the arid plain. The plains biome refers to the central Asian steppe, the African savannah, or the Argentine pampas. Plains are defined by treelessness, generally a result of a lack of rainfall (plains that are too cold for trees are classified as tundra).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_PLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In Africa, one can clearly see the progression of desert to plain to forest. Several major ecological bands exist across Africa. The Sahara, derived from the word meaning “desert” in Arabic, softens into the Sahel as one travels south, and then to the savannah regions of what is geographically termed the Sudan (not to be confused with the country of the same name). This geographic Sudan is the epitome of plains.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_PLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Savannah Woodland</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_PLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Below this belt are the savannah woodlands, a stretch of sparse forest that intensifies until one reaches the jungles in the center of the continent. This “forest-savannah mosaic” is vulnerable to alteration – human populations shape it via fire, and elephants transform forests back into savannahs given enough time. The most iconic savannah trees are the thorny acacia, at least in Africa.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_PLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Watering Hole </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_PLAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Water remains a source of life for all dwellers on the plains, be they zebra, buffalo, lion, or human. At smaller lakes – or “watering holes,” to use the nomenclature of popular nature shows – these lives come together in abundance, and often result in bloodshed. The classic watering hole is a geologic depression in the plains where water collects. As such, it is seasonal, filling during the rainy season and emptying during the dry season, when visits become more and more necessary, and the risk of conflict intensifies. Such depressions often do not empty into other bodies of water, increasing their importance in areas far from rivers as, in a particularly dry season, they may simply vanish into cracked mud.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- BIOME_TROPICAL -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TROPICAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Geographically speaking, the tropics extend between the northernmost and southernmost declinations of the sun – in other words, where the sun appears to be directly overhead at least once or twice per year. This region includes the Caribbean, Saudi Arabia, central India, and Vietnam in the north and southern Brazil, Angola, and the middle of Australia in the south.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TROPICAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The tropics are hot. For the most part, they are wetter than other zones. Tropical regions receive more focused sunlight than temperate zones and therefore experience less seasonal variation. Tropics farther from the equator experience milder winters, but prevailing winds (or special features such as the monsoon) often make a more significant impact on the climate – these regions are usually distinguished by how dry or wet they are, not how hot or cold they are.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TROPICAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Rainforest </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TROPICAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The tropical rainforest is one of the most diverse biomes on the planet. This is a zone where life reigns supreme – tropical soils are often poor because many of their nutrients are caught up in living matter. Rainforests experience little to no dry season, and the tropical forest canopy is often a dense, dark layer of trees over multiple strata, brimming with life. These forests contain reserves of (often undiscovered) medicinal plants, animals, etc. True tropical rainforests are found in the Amazon, the Congo region of Africa, and in Southeast Asia, especially Indonesia and New Guinea. Certain areas outside of the tropics can also be classified as rainforests, e.g. the Pacific Northwest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TROPICAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Mangrove </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_TROPICAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>A mangrove forest refers to a particular kind of forest – broadly it distinguishes wetter tropical swamps from forests or plains. More specifically, mangrove forests lie on the edge of the sea, where the hardy mangrove tree (and its unique spike-like shoots) works to trap sediment, thereby protecting the coastline from wave action. These forests also protect juvenile animals and offer a rich habitat for life. Perhaps the largest and most famous mangrove region is the Sundarbans in Bangladesh and India, a maze of rivers and channels opening into the Bay of Bengal, most famous for its tigers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- BIOME_MARINE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_TITLE">
			<Text>Marine (Biome)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Earth is not a pale green dot. Most of its surface, especially in the southern hemisphere, is covered by seas. The pelagic zone – the open ocean – is in constant motion. With the abyssal plain far below and the shelter of coasts and reefs far away, life in the ocean practically demands the ability to swim quickly and for long distances – pelagic fish tend to be hydrodynamic torpedoes: think tuna or billfish. On the surface, wind and water create highways for human transportation, from the outrigger canoes of the Pacific to the caravels of the Exploration age to the lines of cargo containers moving from port to port.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Atoll</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Found in tropical and subtropical waters, atolls are small, ring-shaped islands, typically composed of a coral rim surrounding a lagoon. The word “atoll” is native to the Dhivehi language, spoken in the Maldives, and popularized by Charles Darwin in his work on coral reefs. There are nearly 450 atolls on Earth, most of which are found in the Pacific Ocean. Though atolls can cover a large oceanic area, their relative landmass tends to be very small. For example, the largest atoll in the world is the Great Chagos Bank, south of the Maldives. While its structure encompasses nearly 5,000 square miles, its total land mass is only 2.2 square miles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>According to Darwin, atolls are formed when a volcanic island sinks, and the coral reef along its edges is all that remains. The coral becomes a barrier reef, and once the island has been completely submerged by the sea, it leaves the lagoon in its place. As long as the sea level does not change more quickly than the rate of coral growth, the atoll remains stable. An alternative theory to explain atolls posits that the reef develops over a sub-surface landmass and becomes exposed to the air as sea levels drop. Rainfall dissolves much of this exposed coral, transforming it into limestone karst. Due to the crevices within karst that allow rainwater to erode the stone from inside, it dissolves more quickly in the center, leaving a basin with a raised rim. As the sea level continues to drop, the center falls below the surface of the water while the rim remains exposed, resulting in the shape of the atoll.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Coast</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Where the sea meets land coasts are formed – perfect jumping-off points for expeditions to glean resources from the sea (whether they be people in boats or seals and seabirds). Coasts are gathering points for ocean detritus, but they are also places of change and conflict, where ocean-derived weather (e.g. storms) wash in over land, where the seas eat away the land, and where silt builds up, reclaiming land from the sea. Coastlines are often inhospitable places, full of sand and rough plants, but they can also be oases of civilization. Certain populations, such as the Moken of Southeast Asia, have adapted to a mostly nautical life, spending much of their lives on floating structures. Other people, such as those from the American Midwest, cannot be persuaded to eat a steamed crab covered in Old Bay, as delicious as it may be.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Lotus</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Though the lotus plant has an ancient history well-represented in the fossil record, only two species remain living today – the pink lotus native to Asia and the yellow lotus of North America. Due to their shape and habitat they are often confused with the water lily, but the two flowers come from distant families. Lotus leaves are especially well-known for both their size and their tendency to cover large ponds or lakes. While most plants have stomata, or pores, on the underside of their leaves, lotus leaves have evolved with stomata on the surface. This would normally cause the plant to drown in rainfall, but lotus leaves have hydrophobic properties. Their construction and shape is such that drops of water quickly congeal and roll off the plants at any slight disturbance of the leaf, allowing them to maintain their internal air regulation and atmospheric exchange. Despite resting on water, lotus leaves are also able to generate heat. While it has been theorized that this process plays an attractive role in pollination, the function of lotus thermogenesis remains a mystery.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Throughout Asia, the lotus serves a variety of ritual, political, and other uses. In India, it is the official plant and considered sacred, often being given as an offering to the Buddha and to several Hindu deities. It is commonly used as a political icon in India and also in Vietnam where it holds symbolism for national identity. Much of the world’s lotus plants are grown in China and exported throughout Asia for a variety of culinary uses derived from the plant’s flowers, leaves, and stems. Dating back at least to the Han Dynasty, lotus has been a key component in Chinese medicine, especially for the heart and kidneys. Other traditional medicines value the lotus for vitality and longevity due to its resilience. Though lotus seeds require specific conditions to germinate, they have been shown to remain viable in a dormant state for up to 1,300 years.</Text>
		</Row>				
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Open Ocean</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Certain areas of the sea are habitually calm or rough. Where seas meet, at the Straits of Magellan, for instance, rough water is a constant danger to travelers, a persistent threat that what is on top of the water might be suddenly sent into the deep. Pools of calm exist within the swirls of the tropical currents, such as the Sargasso Sea in the Atlantic, but this calm is just as troublesome as rough waters to ships that require wind for transportation.</Text>
		</Row>		
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Reef</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BIOME_MARINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>When we think of reefs, we often think of coral gardens, where centuries of growth (and death) of small creatures have helped create vast labyrinths underwater. These are the rainforests of the sea, with abundant diverse life and shelters for growing fish. But the term “reef” means much more – a reef is any underwater mineral buildup. It provides shelter from waves, is a habitat for smaller fish, and an obstacle for sailors (distinguished from a shoal, which is a sandy obstruction). These days, coral reefs are in severe peril as oceans acidify, leading to the mass die-off of their tiny builders and placing the future of the oceans in jeopardy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- FEATURE_ICE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_FEATURE_ICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As one approaches the extreme polar regions, life becomes more tenuous. With ground that remains frozen year-round, roots cannot dig too deeply, and plants become more and more scarce. Eventually, even the barest grasses cannot find purchase, and the landscape is one of barren rock and glaciers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_FEATURE_ICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Such ice packs may rest on the sea, as in the Arctic, or on land, as in the Antarctic. They grow and shrink with the seasons, and contribute in a meaningful way to the warming and cooling of the earth owing to the albedo effect (the reflection of light back into space). And it is in the sea that life still finds hold in icy biomes – under the ice is a living world of crustaceans, fish, and marine mammals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_FEATURE_ICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>At present, the Arctic ice pack is steadily losing more ice than re-freezes in the winter, and scientists estimate the summers may be ice-free somewhere in the middle of this century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- TERRAIN_MOUNTAINS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_MOUNTAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the plates of the Earth’s crust meet, they interact, pushing the land upwards, or causing it to buckle into folds and creases. These are mountains. Some mountain ranges are relatively old; the Appalachians, for instance, were begun over a billion years ago. Others are much newer and more dynamic, such as the Alps or Himalayas.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_MOUNTAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Mountains, too, alter the land in other ways. The Himalayas, for instance, push warm, moist air from the Indian Ocean upwards, where it cools and forms monsoon clouds. Behind them, where all the moisture has been condensed from the air, is the dry Gobi Desert and Tibetan Plateau.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_MOUNTAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>For people, mountains represent a range of possibilities and challenges – they present a barrier to movement and a challenge to agriculture. For instance, the Himalayas and their spur in Southeast Asia neatly divide regions historically influenced by Indic civilizations on one side and Chinese civilizations on the other. Elsewhere, people have proved up to the challenge that the heights provide – the Inca built their empire high atop the Andes, becoming at home in the heights.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_MOUNTAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Volcano</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_MOUNTAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Where mountains are being formed, there is always the risk of the earth’s magma bubbling upwards and breaching the surface – this is a volcano. Thus, we see volcanoes peppered across seismically active fault lines – Asia’s Ring of Fire, for instance, or the Great Rift Valley in Africa, or, notably, the great undersea mountain chains at the middle of the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_MOUNTAINS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Volcanoes have been the source of fear (recall Pompeii’s fate), or veneration (as in the Hawai’ian goddess Pele) or both. They are sites of both creation and destruction, where the fundamental powers of the earth are laid bare, and humans can witness their awesome power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- TERRAIN_RIVERS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_RIVERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Water seeks its level. As snow melts in high elevations, and as rain-soaked ground slowly releases its moisture, it collects into small tributaries, which in turn run downhill, cutting channels and carving paths to the sea. Somewhere along the way, a stream becomes a river.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_TERRAIN_RIVERS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Rivers were the core of most ancient civilizations – we cannot dissociate Egypt from the Nile, or Mesopotamia from the Tigris and Euphrates (though the Maya relied upon an aquifer, not a particular river). They provided drinking water, irrigation, and transport. This latter is often disrupted along the way as the descending water cuts across a particularly insoluble escarpment of rock – a fall line, where the water becomes impassible to ships. We can see such fall lines in most major rivers – the Rheinfall of the Rhine, the Khone Falls of the Mekong, et cetera. Here, too, are where industrial cities such as Philadelphia or Trenton thrived – the power of the falls could be harnessed by mills, while at the same time trade from up the river could be collected.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>