<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- LEADER_AMINA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_AMINA_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Modern-day Nigeria is built on the foundations of multiple layers of history, ethnic groups, and configurations of city-states in the pre-colonial period. Of these, the Hausa are dominant in the northern region, and Zazzau was one of their pre-eminent states. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>To understand the politics of West Africa, one should examine both geography and trade routes. The most notable overland routes ran through the cold Siberian steppe and the Sahara Desert, both highways linking the resources of West Africa to the wealth of Asia (with their nexus in Arabia). As with the Silk Road, Islam was the predominant religion of these networks.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the 1500s, this configuration began to change with the arrival of large oceangoing ships from Portugal (and soon after, other European powers). Saharan trade started moving towards sending trade down to Portuguese and other outposts on the coast, even as North African trade routes remained focused on the Middle East. In both cases, major trade goods included cotton, indigo, salt, kola, leather, gold and those unfortunate enough to be captured and enslaved. Local kings and warlords made profits, but this influx of wealth from a variety of sources made for highly unstable societies, as everyone sought the latest and most lucrative sources of wealth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Zazzau was one such city-state in northern Nigeria, a home to the Hausa people of the Sahel. Amina was the daughter of its king. In popular tradition, Amina was preternaturally gifted at combat, holding a knife as a child in the exact way a warrior would hold a sword. When her father and brother died, she took over the reign of Zazzau.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The idea of a Muslim warrior queen might at first seem unusual. It shouldn’t. Hausa Islam was highly syncretic, meaning that it incorporated a lot of other influences under the umbrella of “Islam” – indeed, this was a reason why war plagued the area, as reformers sought to bring religion in closer dialogue with Arabia, and others leaned on alternative, more traditional sources of authority.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Amina went on a series of conquests starting in 1576; her first command to her soldiers was “sharpen your weapons.” She fought for decades, so often that her warriors quickly became accomplished veterans, and she united much of the Hausa territory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>With conquest comes stability and trade. The union of land under Zazzau allowed Sahara-bound routes to remain open and viable, even as the more coastal settlements turned towards expanding European presences. However, those trade routes were to prove Amina’s undoing, at least in terms of her legacy. As Hausaland became increasingly linked with conservative Islam, the concept of warrior queens faded, and official roles for women were diminished, a trend that persisted after British colonization. But today, in a postcolonial Nigeria and especially in Hausaland, Amina’s legend continues, and she has become a national hero.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AMINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Amina’s conquests involved the militarization of much of the Nigerian Sahel and the fortification of Hausa cities and towns. The most colorful legend stemming from her conquests claims that she took a lover in every city she conquered, and then killed the man the morning after – a sure way to preserve one’s independence and legacy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_ASHOKA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ASHOKA_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_ASHOKA_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ASHOKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the immediate aftermath of Alexander the Great’s failed conquest of India, the Mauryan Empire rose to become the largest single polity to emerge in India in antiquity. After Alexander’s retreat, Chandragupta Maurya seized the chaos that followed and conquered the vassals that Greece had left behind. Though less unified than later Indian empires, Maurya was a beacon for learning and culture, even sending emissaries and Buddhist missionaries westward, in Alexander’s footsteps. Domestically, the empire continued the maintenance of trade routes across the subcontinent, from east to west, forming a key link in the Silk Road, a route that was to become central to their fame. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ASHOKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Religion played a vital role in Maurya. India is home to many of the world’s religions – Hinduism, Jainism, and Buddhism, as well as a few more exotic strands of belief, such as Greek Hellenism. The early Mauryans were Jain, whose focus on non-violence and the cultivation of personal purity seems an odd choice for an emperor – until one realizes that purity in turn leads to personal power and charisma. It should be noted that the Mauryans regularly had both Chinese and Greek visitors rubbing shoulders in its cities, resulting in significant heterogeneity and cosmopolitanism. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ASHOKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Ashoka (Asoka) – the name means “without sorrow” – started life as the unfavored last-born son. Apparently, his father simply did not like his complexion, which was not smooth like his brothers, and repeatedly ignored the signs that this child was going to become a conqueror. When his brother, the crown prince, headed off to war, Ashoka declared that the gods wished him to be the king. Few stood in the way of this claim: when Ashoka’s father protested, the old man promptly died; and when Ashoka’s brother returned to seize the throne, he was promptly dumped into a charcoal fire. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ASHOKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Once established, Ashoka continued his rather bloody rise to power. He immediately placed his sights on the Kalinga Empire to the east and launched a war of brazen conquest. Eager for victory, Ashoka rode out to battle with his troops – and was disgusted. The bloodshed and brutality he witnessed there led him to renounce violence and embrace Buddhism and the effort to spread the truth of the dharma (Buddhist teachings) across the kingdom, which he did by erecting stelae extolling the dharma across Mauryan lands.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ASHOKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>On his stelae, Ashoka issued his Edicts. In addition to listing those responsible for inscribing them, the Edicts define prohibitions on immorality – violence towards animals (i.e. meat-eating), violence towards people, and overly licentious festivals. They also describe institutions (of medical care, for instance) that the emperor set up in the region, making a lasting claim towards global goodwill.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ASHOKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Ashoka’s story is one of transformation. A visiting Chinese diplomat speculated that the early Ashoka had personally gone to hell to learn new methods of torture, while the later Ashoka denounces all violence, to human and animal alike. It is a story of repentance that has made Ashoka a hero across Buddhist Asia, and he is seen by many Sri Lankans and Southeast Asians as the person who brought Buddhism to their parts of the world. While this impact is perhaps his most lasting legacy worldwide, Ashoka remains compelling to Indians as well, and was the subject of a big-budget Bollywood feature and, now, a popular TV series. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_AUGUSTUS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Where to begin with Caesar Augustus, about whom massive volumes of text have been written, and to whom nearly every subsequent “great leader” west of the Indus River has aspired to be? He was Caesar from 27 BCE until 14 CE, and epitomized Rome at its height. Conceivably, he was less bold and more methodical than his great-uncle and adoptive father, Julius Caesar. However, Augustus arguably accomplished more.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Octavian, Augustus’ non-imperial name, was born into a knight’s family (eques). However, he had links to royalty, related to Julius Caesar by blood; his mother was Caesar’s niece (though Julius Caesar himself was not from the highest ranks of Roman nobility). When Octavian was a child, his father died and his mother remarried a man who was less than attentive. Octavian grew into a quiet, thoughtful, pragmatic young man. Still, he sought power and made several attempts to get closer to his famous uncle. He tried to sail to the front lines of a war that Julius Caesar was waging in Spain and was shipwrecked, yet managed to make his way through hostile territory to the front. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>This adventure greatly impressed the emperor. Caesar took a liking to the young man and quickly named him as his successor and adoptive son. Precisely why Caesar did this is open for speculation. Caesar's contemporaries, and many modern scholars, have suggested the boy was Caesar’s lover, something common in Rome, but a detail that may have opened Caesar to criticism and accusations of irrational decisions based upon lust. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The rest of the story is famous. Julius Caesar, returning in triumph from a war in Europe, was commanded to stop before he marched the army to Rome. Fed up with the arrogance and incompetence in the senate (and their formal inquiries into his finances), Caesar made no secret about his own imperial ambitions. Jokes and rumors about Caesar as an emperor abounded in Rome, and when Caesar appeared to be coming back in triumph, the senate demanded he disband his army. Fearing his imprisonment, he refused and a war ensued. Upon Caesar’s victory, he was eventually declared dictator and embarked on a series of reforms. In the end, his enemies (and friends) in the senate murdered him.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>What followed was a massive civil war. The common people were outraged, and Caesar’s assassins fled to Greece. Caesar’s heirs and friends sought to avenge him: Marc Antony, Caesar’s cavalry commander Lepidus…and Octavian. Octavian proved a more appealing figure than Antony to the common people, as Antony initially granted amnesty to Caesar’s assassins. Furthermore, Octavian had allies in the senate who remembered and rejected Antony’s pretenses to power as well as his dismissal of Octavian’s familial ties and special relationship with Caesar.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Even after Caesar's assassins were murdered, the political situation remained fraught. Octavian had married Antony’s wife’s daughter, but now he spurned her, so she fled to Antony seeking revenge. The three heirs split the Empire between them – Antony in the East, Octavian in the West, and Lepidus in Africa. While Antony retained supporters, his affair with, and idolization of, Cleopatra cost him allies in Rome. When Octavian opened Antony’s sealed will, revealing that he planned to divide the empire amongst his children, Antony’s fate was sealed. After a defeat, Antony and Cleopatra committed suicide. In the wake of their deaths, Octavian remained the sole ruler of Rome.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Nevertheless, Octavian was cautious and ensured that his power plays were legitimated by a senate that was slowly falling under his sway. In 27 BCE, Octavian changed his name to Augustus. Another name he chose for himself was “victorious commander”: Imperator. With this title came victories: solidified control over Hispania, the Balkans, and Judea, though he also suffered a major defeat in Germany. Much of Augustus’ power as an individual came from taking personal control over the most lucrative territories – for instance, Egypt belonged to him, not Rome. The profits from that immensely wealthy area flowed into his accounts, as they would for his successors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Augustus died in 14 CE, possibly succumbing to his constant ill-health, or possibly murdered by Livia, his wife. The latter is a popular theory, but most historians believe her to be innocent. His last words were “Have I played the part well? Then applaud as I exit.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_AUGUSTUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Plato writes that democracies always degenerate into tyranny. The legacy of Augustus and Julius Caesar might confirm this. While Augustus was not the bold adventurer his great-uncle was, he manipulated the reins of power in Rome. He was intelligent, patient, and built the foundations of a civilization that became an inspiration to nearly all others in Europe. While Julius Caesar – hero of the army and spurner of the senate – might inspire coup leaders worldwide, Augustus inspired emperors… and game designers. In his wake, Rome entered centuries of peace, the Pax Romana.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The conception of the United States of America has taken many contradictory forms over the years, including a haven for religious dissidents, a plantation-based economy focused on enslavement, an experiment in Enlightenment ideals, an expansionist republic intent on dominating the continent, and even the world’s center of capitalism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Benjamin Franklin’s vision of America was a blend of secularized Protestantism, capitalism, and notions of liberty. According to the writings of sociologist Max Weber, Franklin was emblematic of the transformation from Calvinism to an austere productive ethos where labor was considered good and diligent people were seen as good people. Therefore labor was a path to salvation – for the more secular-minded American founding fathers, thrift and labor become ends in and of themselves. This perspective creates an exponential rationalization of labor that focuses on efficiency, which Weber famously called “the iron cage.” As Franklin wrote, “He that murders a crown (i.e. wastes a coin on something unproductive), destroys all that it might have produced, even scores of pounds.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Franklin’s ideas about liberty were also practical. To him, it seemed irrational for Americans to ship their manufactured goods back to England to be re-sold by English middlemen when they could be directly sold to Spanish colonies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>He was also science-minded. His kite experiment is famous and led to his invention of the lightning rod. Famously, he invented bifocal glasses, swim fins, a more efficient fireplace, a catheter, and the armonica (a musical instrument involving glasses of water). These innovations showcase Franklin's curiosity and interest in creating practical things (with the exception of the armonica).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Franklin may lean heavily upon the ideas of thrift and industry because he came from relatively modest means, unlike many other “founding fathers.” Born in Boston in 1706 and lacking formal education, Franklin made his fortune after moving to Philadelphia in 1723 to begin a printing business. Despite his lack of education, Franklin was an adept writer, publishing essays in his brother’s newspaper in Boston before continuing the tradition in Philadelphia, where he published the Pennsylvania Gazette. In Philadelphia, he also published the most famous work of his early life, Poor Richard’s Almanack, which carried his trademark clever prose alongside sound advice.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Franklin's personal life was tireless as he also founded Philadelphia’s volunteer fire company, police patrols, philosophical society, and the University of Pennsylvania. He became postmaster for Philadelphia in 1737 and postmaster general for all colonies in 1753. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>The British eventually became suspicious of Franklin's rebellious nature, and for good reason. As early as 1734, Franklin formed the Albany Plan, a proposal for a unified government between the Thirteen Colonies, which was similar to the later Articles of Confederation. Franklin eventually represented Pennsylvania in London and rallied against infamous economic laws (such as the Stamp Act) that had given the colonies reason for revolution.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Franklin could be pedantic and needling, but he always impressed his listeners. Famously, he fought with John Adams over whether to keep a window open at night, a long and contentious battle that lasted hours. At other times, Franklin’s comedic skills were apparent; when the British debated sending convicts as settlers to America, Franklin laconically proposed that American convicts be sent to England in exchange.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Among Franklin’s greatest contributions was his role in helping draft the Declaration of Independence. During the Revolutionary War, he represented the United States in France, lobbying for France’s participation in the conflict, something that likely had more to do with Anglo-French rivalry than Franklin’s diplomacy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_BENJAMIN_FRANKLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Ultimately, Franklin is noted as an architect of the governing philosophy of the United States, a task he performed with tireless devotion and no small amount of humor. Allegedly, he characterized the United States' new form of government as “a republic, if you can keep it.” It remains to be seen if that republic will keep.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_CATHERINE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_CATHERINE_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Russian history is one of rises and falls, and a high or low point always anticipates its opposite. When the Romanovs took power in the 17th century from the Rurikid dynasty, the dynasty that traced its lineage back to the semi-mythical Rurik the Viking, it was a move out of a period of chaos and into a European world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Romanovs played two distinct parties against each other. The “Slavophiles” emphasized Russia’s distinction from the West, whereas the “Europhiles” believed Russia was a part of the West. The early Romanovs – especially Catherine and Peter – were decidedly the latter. They embraced European engineering and art, German nobility, and the French language. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In previous centuries many European powers were absolute monarchies: bureaucratic states centered on a particular individual. In Russia, this was intensely personalized, and the whims of the tsar (or tsarina) dictated policy. This could reach bizarre heights – while Peter the Great is lauded for his progressiveness in European (especially British) circles, his reign was intensely driven by personality and a commitment to autocracy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>In a way, Catherine's story starts with Peter the Great, who ruled from 1682-1725 and reshaped Russia. He expanded its borders and built a capital at St. Petersburg, formerly a Finnic-speaking frontier. Under Peter, Russia became an iron mining and timber powerhouse and gained a naval port on the Baltic. Peter also cultivated marriage alliances with other European powers and implemented Western dress and French language at court.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Militarily, Peter’s reign was marked by victories against the Ottomans, and a massive war over control of the Baltic – Russia was concerned with Europe, pushing westward militarily and diplomatically. Culturally, Peter is depicted as an enlightened despot, a devotee of industry and science, but this ambition was tempered by his profligacy at home. He engaged in late-night drinking bouts, brutal parties centered around abusing less-liked courtiers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Under Peter, Russia was catapulted onto the world stage – becoming a great power with a navy and a claim to the Baltic and Black seas. The country was a player in European dynastic politics, though its religious orthodoxy set it slightly apart. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Here enters Catherine.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Peter the Great’s campaign to make marriage alliances became a common practice in Russia, and his descendant Peter III chose (or had chosen for him) a Prussian princess named Sophie of Anhalt-Zerbst. Upon her conversion to Orthodoxy, Princess Sophie became Tsarina Catherine. The marriage was not happy. Peter III was stuck in permanent adolescence, playing with toy soldiers and drinking in court rather than governing – or procreating.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>When Peter III ascended to the throne in 1762, he continued his legacy of bad choices. Moreover, he lacked a global strategy. The year before, Russia had been at war with Prussia, but Peter admired the Prussian leader Friedrich II and signed an extremely conciliatory treaty. Peter also alienated powerful allies. He had inherited a claim on a duchy in Denmark and decided to wage war against that country despite long-running Russian-Danish alliances.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>In short, Peter III looked like a disaster for Russia. Several people could have deposed him – rival nobles, the military, a foreign power – but Catherine was the one who successfully organized the coup. Peter was deposed in 1762, and Catherine took the crown herself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Catherine was a classic “enlightened despot,” an absolute ruler without the impulse for liberalism or the rights of the people, and a leader who wielded power via engagement with arts and philosophy. Her internal rule was a strange series of sexual politics. She would often appoint her lovers to high-status positions, holding to Russia’s personality-based political ladder. Potemkin was one of the most famous examples – an extremely competent advisor who governed Russia’s outlying provinces, worked to modernize the state, and conducted a great deal of other reforms (although his use of fake villages built to impress the visiting tsarina, known as “Potemkin Villages,” are now understood to be a myth). When Catherine and Potemkin's affair was over, Potemkin allegedly named his successor to Catherine’s bedchambers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Culturally, Catherine’s rule during the Russian Enlightenment brought Chinese trade goods and European artistic sensibilities into Russia. Indeed, the massive Hermitage Museum is largely taken from her personal collection. Like Friedrich II, she was a friend and confidant of the French satirist Voltaire. Internally, she also oversaw growth in higher education for women and other educational reforms.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>Abroad, Catherine expanded the boundaries of Russia, chipping away at Poland and the Ottomans along the way. However, she saw Russia as a mediator more than as an expansive empire. Catherine’s shrewd instincts were displayed during the American Revolution – she did not see the war as a fundamental shift in world politics, and therefore a threat, but as a failure of King George III, and thus an opportunity. She lobbied to preserve trade and end blockades, exploiting the conflict for Russia’s profit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CATHERINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>Catherine died at the age of 67, having helped define the heights of Imperial Russia. She combined canny foreign policy, an enlightened cultural approach, and sound attention to local leaders and notables. She was not a liberal, but she presented a model of enlightened autocracy that few could emulate.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “Fall of Rome” is a bit disingenuous – in the East, the Byzantines continued using the name Rome centuries after the fall of the western empire. However, the Byzantines were eventually challenged for that title by a smaller upstart. The Franks were a Germanic tribe that conquered much of the land that we know today as France, blending the already-blended Gallo-Roman culture with their own. Over time, these Frankish kings laid the groundwork for the Middle Ages and shaped modern-day France and Germany.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 768 CE, Charlemagne inherited a relatively stable Frankish kingdom and decided to expand it. He aggressively pushed against the pagan Europeans to his east, conquering large stretches of Bavaria and parts of northern Germany and Italy, including lands belonging to the Avars, horse nomads from Central Asia that had moved into Europe. In Spain, Charlemagne also clashed with the rising Umayyad Caliphate. While these Muslims sought to consolidate control over Iberia and wrest it from the Gothic and Basque presence, Charlemagne wished to incorporate the region into his larger empire. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Rome was nervous about Charlemagne's Frankish expansion and sought to make allies. Meanwhile, the new Pope Leo III had become politically isolated and faced familial reprisal in Rome. He fled to Charlemagne’s court and offered a deal: if Charlemagne backed Leo’s position as Pope, then Leo would crown him Emperor of Rome.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>This was no mere title. The Byzantines already saw themselves as heirs of Rome – suddenly the Franks were a new western empire (at least in claim), and they were a challenge for the holy mantle of a pre-emptive Christian kingdom (this tension would later lead to the schism between Eastern and Western Christianity.) The conflict between the Byzantines and the Franks may have been rooted in sexism – at the time the Byzantines were ruled by a woman, Irene of Athens, so Pope Leo’s claim that he saw no Roman emperor before anointing Charlemagne could be seen as an attack on Irene’s right to rule. Leo’s actions were the first steps towards establishing the pope as the one who decided the pre-eminent ruler in Europe, a status that would dominate the Holy Roman Empire until Napoleon seized the crown a millennium later.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>By the time of his crowning, Charlemagne’s works were largely complete. He fought a few more campaigns against the Danes as the Viking Age kicked off, but died in 814.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>In spirit, Charlemagne was known to be both jolly and fierce. Reconstructing his personality is difficult because, in the tradition of medieval Germanic rulers attempting to build their eternal legacy, he often spread stories of his own greatness, crafting narratives that were not always firmly grounded in fact. For instance, he described his campaigns against the Muslims in Spain as a crusade to retake the holy land – it certainly was not, as Spain is quite far from Jerusalem, but the claim sold the idea and would feed into the later Crusades. When Charlemagne cited his status as a Catholic, he claimed to be the only true Christian king (a snub at the other branches of Christianity active in the world at the time), and he “naturally” felt his reign included Jerusalem, though the Abbasid rulers of that city at the time would not have recognized this.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CHARLEMAGNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Charlemagne’s Holy Roman Empire would be a political force until Napoleon’s arrival, and came to define the formation of both the German Federation and Austria (in short, most of Germany and Austria were part of the Empire, a configuration that was later torn apart by rivalries between Vienna and Berlin). </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_CONFUCIUS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Kongzi, Master Kong, is better known by his Hellenized name of “Confucius.” He was a government official and philosopher from an early period in Chinese history, the 500s BCE, slightly before the Han Dynasty and the very dawn of China. His writings emphasized rational, benevolent behavior, devotion to one’s duty, and respect for tradition. Importantly, Confucius trusted the system – if individuals strove to educate themselves and adopted a sense of good faith and loyalty to others (especially their families), they would serve as a check on greedy and power-hungry leaders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Confucius had plenty of examples of terrible leaders. As the Shang Dynasty fell apart, a new, loosely-assembled dynasty arose: the Zhou (1046-256 BCE). Under this dynasty, individual states led by particular generals held sway over a smaller, more centralized state ruled by the emperor. Imagine a popular person at school surrounded by a crowd of bullies constantly fighting for the claim to be their absolute best friend and protector. Oddly enough, fractured and contentious political situations are often fertile ground for writers and philosophers – just ask Machiavelli. Confucius lived on the eastern edge of China at some point during this war-torn period. As his political world broke down around him, Confucius spent his life advocating for sensible order and good governance. Confucian influence calls on would-be charismatic or forceful rulers to curb their power and work for the common good.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Born to a slightly upper (but not aristocratic) caste in the duchy of Lu, Confucius slowly rose through the ranks of local administration. He saw the problems inherent in the era and sought to appeal to central authority over the chaos. For instance, when he attained mayorship of a small town, he sought to dismantle its walls. Walls intended to defend against attacks from rival families; with the walls removed, Confucius thought the local duke would have to take a more direct role in defending the town.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>But rulers often disappoint. Confucius was regularly stymied by those he sought to advise – those he counseled in moderation were led astray by his opponent's flattery and lavish gifts, while others fell victim to personal vices. Eventually, Confucius’ enemies engineered to have him exiled for a time. Upon his return to Lu, he settled down and spent most of his time writing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>His works include the Five Classics of Confucian philosophy. These texts contain poems, political speeches, historical records, and catalogs of rituals, rites, and magic. The latter discusses the divination system I Ching, still popular today. Confucius’ teachings have been distilled into collections by his disciples, including the Analects, his most famous work. The other Four Books of Confucianism include Great Learning, Doctrine of the Mean (a morality lesson for all, not just rulers), and a series of conversations with the scholar Mencius.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>“Know your place, and do it well” might be one way to summarize Confucian philosophy, as well as “respect tradition,” and “act always with kindness.” Confucianism exists somewhere in between philosophy, religion, and moralism. It is a principle that is humanist at its core, emphasizing heaven's presence (tian) in interpersonal interaction, good government, and good ethics. Being loyal to one’s family and friends, being mindful of one’s duties, and being harmonious is the natural tendency of humankind.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_CONFUCIUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>In its early days, Confucianism clashed with Legalism. The latter saw top-down codes of conduct necessary to constrain human nature, which inclined towards sin. Later, Confucian codes began to synergize with Legalist codes. Confucian societies include China, Japan, Korea, and Vietnam, as well as states that are heavily influenced by Chinese thought (e.g. Singapore). Its principles now include notions of benevolence, justice, observance of proper custom and decorum, knowledge, and integrity, as well as loyalty, filial piety (i.e. loyalty to one’s family and betters), and righteousness. While Confucianism does emphasize subjection to rulers, rulers must show themselves to be subject to tian – rulers who fail to live up to heaven’s standards face the disloyalty of their populace.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_FRIEDRICH -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is Germany? The area the Romans called Germania was a region east of the Rhine where the empire's influence ceased. Linguistically and culturally, Germanic refers to a loose coalition of languages that range from extremely similar (Bavarian/Austrian, German) to slightly different (Dutch, Flemish) to quite distinct (Swedish, Icelandic, English). As a people, Germans were often divided – this is still visible today in Austria and Germany.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Eventually, two states rose to power: Prussia and Austria. The latter was a Catholic state and powerful within the Holy Roman Empire. On the other hand, Prussia was caught on the northern edge. Subject to influences (Teutonic, Hanseatic, Polish) outside of the Holy Roman Empire, Prussia needed to militarize to remain independent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Amid this rise to power enters Friedrich II.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Friedrich the Great was the longest-ruling king of Prussia, from 1740-1786. He lived in a time of art and literature as well as Prussian military dominance. Friedrich was caught between worlds. His love of the arts clashed with the militarism of the time. His homosexuality clashed with imperial demands to marry and produce an heir. His Francophilia clashed with the militant anti-French nationalism at large in Prussia. In short, he was trapped, yet he managed to stay alive and nurture both sides of Prussia: the artistic and the militant.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Friedrich was the son of Friedrich William, an infamous despot known for his relative disdain for culture, his promotion of the military, and for “Prussian virtues” of frugality and sobriety (meaning “a lack of humor” in this case). His wife, Sophia Dorothea, was quite the opposite and found the court stifling. She was far more Francophile than Friedrich William. Prussia's court language was French and both monarchs were fluent, but Friedrich William was notoriously ungrammatical in the language. Other French court customs were shunned as Prussian frugality won over. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Friedrich II was the third son; his two elder brothers died young, so much of his parents’ hope rested on the young Friedrich. Sophia Dorothea sought to instill in her son the love of high culture and court life that her husband disdained. He also learned French; in fact, he was not terribly fluent in German despite being German. But there was conflict between father and son. As much as Friedrich loved learning Latin and high culture, his father pressured him to adopt a harsh austerity. Tensions grew, and Friedrich eventually maintained a hidden library in a palace across town. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Friedrich William was concerned about his son’s sexuality – while rumors abounded about the teenager’s love affairs, their “effeminacy” bothered the king the most, and he feared that the new state of Prussia might crumble without a sober and militaristic king. Ironically, his diplomatic ineptitude was causing headaches in the empire: his loyalty to a German monarchy led him to curry favor with Austrian monarchs, who despised the austere Prussian.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Enter Lieutenant Hans Hermann von Katte. Katte was a teenage friend of the young Friedrich – though their friendship was clearly something more. Take this scene from the life of young Friedrich: Katte and Friedrich have put on luxurious dressing gowns and done their hair in the latest Parisian fashions. They practice music in Friedrich’s chambers when the king storms upstairs. Katte hides in a closet as the angry king tosses all the luxurious clothes into a fire and then forces young Friedrich back into a military uniform.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>It sounds like a scene from a farce – until the next part. The crown prince was so scandalized by his father’s conduct that he decided to run away with Katte to England. The two were caught. And while Friedrich escaped punishment, Katte was executed while Friedrich was forced to watch.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Friedrich William died in 1740, leaving the crown to Friedrich II. Under the new king, the palace saw an explosion of art, and invitations went out to French-speaking intelligentsia. Friedrich cultivated a court where he could express his sexuality – if not entirely openly, at least in private.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Still, Friedrich’s relationship with his father was more complicated. The young king desired his late father’s posthumous approval and maintained his father's aggressive military and diplomatic endeavors. He invaded Silesia in 1740 and routing the French and Austrian forces in the War of Austrian Succession.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>For all of Friedrich’s attention to art and culture, he remained an accomplished strategist. Prussia, which had been a shaky, unstable, militaristic power, was suddenly rising to become a major force, especially after seizing the wealthiest parts of Austria. Prussia’s rise also reshaped the system of alliances in Europe from an Austrian/British alliance to an Austrian/French alliance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>The interlude between wars was brief. The Seven Year’s War was another conflagration of shifting alliances, as Austria/France/Russia fought Prussia/Britain. And Friedrich started this conflict as well – again seizing Austrian territory in Saxony. In this fight, Friedrich nearly lost everything. He was bold but too bold; the only thing that saved his dwindling army was Russia's withdrawal from the war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>In short, Friedrich was a capable military leader who – despite his father – pushed Prussia ever outward. As with Napoleon, he is often credited with daring and innovative plans to pin down and outmaneuver the enemy, showing a keen understanding of supply lines and logistics. He died in 1786 in his palace.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>This was a time of absolutism. Friedrich styled himself as an enlightened despot – a philosopher-king – who was the Platonic ideal of a ruler. This is hardly democratic, but few European leaders were at the time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_16">
			<Text>Friedrich was a lifelong patron of the arts, especially French and Italian arts, and cultivated friendships with Voltaire and other luminaries. As French artists and thinkers became increasingly uncertain in France, they found a home in the Prussian court alongside other intellectuals of the day, like Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, and Classical-era composers such as Johann Sebastian Bach. Friedrich also sponsored an architectural revival, particularly in the late Baroque style, or Rococo, an elaboration upon Enlightenment forms that seek to soften (or overwhelm) the strict geometric forms of French architecture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_FRIEDRICH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_17">
			<Text>Friedrich’s legacy is twofold: the rise of Prussian militarism on one hand, and the flourishing of late Baroque arts on the other. People like Thomas Mann saw Friedrich as a ruthless expansionist seeking to chip away at Austria (which is true). Others accused Friedrich of contributing to the sparks that ignited the French Revolution by establishing a court of French philosophers and thinkers who could freely speak of sedition (also true). Ultimately, one can see Friedrich as a model for truly modern despotism, ruling by sword and pen and creating a firm break from a feudal past.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Slavery's legacy in the American South is long and complicated. As early as the 1500s, the enslavement of native people and the transport of enslaved Africans became a cornerstone of European colonies in the Caribbean and the southern region of the Thirteen Colonies. Cash crops such as tobacco, cotton, and sugar were as lucrative as the gold and silver mines in Spanish territories and existed for the same profit-oriented reasons. Colonial plantations were not farms but factories – large estates owned by one family or person that relied on a large body of replaceable labor provided with the bare minimum to keep this labor going.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Detailing the horrors of this system is beyond the scope of this article. In short, slavery sought to strip the humanity from individuals and families and reduce people to their labor. Marriage, education, free time – those things that we take to be parts of a fulfilling life were denied to people who were, contrary to earlier systems of slavery, denied their basic humanity. American slavery was entwined with racism as well, with an ideology that Africans were fundamentally not human in the same way others were, citing both pseudo-biology and Biblical passages to justify what was at its core an economic system of domination. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But in Harriet Tubman’s time, things were changing. Europeans (Denmark, at first) had begun to ban the trade of enslaved people in 1803, while the United States banned the importation of new enslaved Africans into the country soon after – though this did not prohibit the continued enslavement of African Americans already present. Around this time, Haiti erupted in revolution, marking the first successful slave revolt in the world and charting a new path forward. England banned slavery in most of its colonies in 1833, despite its extensive holdings in the Caribbean and Africa. The USA remained a holdout for an institution that had long grown unpopular worldwide, and this position was to tear the country apart. It is worth noting that the time between worldwide disgust at the institution and the end of slavery in the USA was an entire generation – someone could be born when slavery was being widely banned in Europe and die a grandparent before its abolition in the USA.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Trade in enslaved people grew more tenuous in the United States after these bans – by that time, most African Americans were two or three generations removed from Africa. But two major factors came into play during Tubman’s time – the development of the cotton gin, which allowed plantations to produce far more cotton with unskilled labor in far less time, and the Fugitive Slave Act of 1850, which stipulated a requirement to “return” escapees to their “owners.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>All these factors combined created an environment in which trade in enslaved people was limited to the USA, the productive potential of enslaved labor vastly increased, and whites could simply “claim” that any Black person they captured was an escapee. Unfortunately, these claims happened all too often –residents of New York, for instance, were subject to seeing groups of Black people in chains being “repatriated” back to the South even though some of them had never seen the South. The anger of abolitionists began to increase, and the fires of the Civil War had begun. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The Underground Railroad (UGRR) was closely associated with Harriet Tubman and this time period. It was a series of safehouses and guides – “stations” and “conductors" – used to move escapees away from the South and towards freedom in Canada. These were networks of free Black people and white abolitionists (often Quakers) operating largely independently of each other, for everyone’s safety. While the South saw this as an invasion of their property rights, the North was (largely) sympathetic. War seemed inescapable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Harriet Tubman was born “Minty” Ross on a plantation in Dorchester County, Maryland. Her early life was not happy. Tubman’s body bore the scars of a beating she underwent at the age of five, after an infant she was instructed to keep quiet cried. In another incident, she was permanently damaged when an overseer struck her in the head with a weight. Her parents, also enslaved, had to fight hard to keep the family together, hiding Tubman’s brothers when slave traders came through Dorchester.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>In 1849, fearing she would be sold and put into a dangerous and unfamiliar environment, Tubman used the UGRR to escape. She ended up in Philadelphia. The next year, she heard that one of her nieces was also likely to be sold and decided to head back to Maryland to rescue her. It was the first of 13 missions to help others.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>A prelude to the Civil War occurred in the West Virginia town of Harpers Ferry when John Brown seized an arsenal in an attempt to spark a wider abolitionist movement. Tubman helped plan this bold move, though she was not present. The United States sent marines to stop Brown, and he was killed. The raid was not popular at the time; only later would writers cast Brown as a hero.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Tubman continued her efforts as wider conflict broke out. She volunteered as a nurse for Union forces, and applied her experience as a UGRR guide to provide intelligence for the army. One of her most significant contributions was her role in the raid on Combahee Ferry in South Carolina, a dramatic attack on plantations that resulted in the rescue of over 700 people out of slavery and inspiring several similar missions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>After the war, Tubman continued the fight for civil rights in upstate New York, where she joined suffragettes seeking to expand the vote to women. She was never paid for her military service and died in near poverty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HARRIET_TUBMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Tubman herself led only a few score of enslaved people to freedom before the war, and the UGRR did not make a meaningful economic impact upon the South – yet their symbolic importance to the present-day United States is dramatic. Tubman remains a key figure in the histories of that period and the struggle for equal rights in the United States. She is a profound inspiration to those who seek to stand up for what is right, even if the job seems difficult, thankless, or downright dangerous.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_HATSHEPSUT -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_TITLE">
			<Text>Hatshesput</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hatshepsut ruled in the early part of the 15th century BCE, during Egypt’s New Kingdom. She is notable for being a queen (though many of her statues depicted her as a man – likely for religious reasons), and for embarking on an aggressive building spree around the capital of Thebes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The historical timeline is difficult to fathom. By the time Hatshepsut ascended to power, the Pyramids were already a thousand years old; it would be another 700 years until the Greek golden age, and 1,500 years before Cleopatra and the height of the Roman Empire. Elsewhere, China’s first dynasties had not yet been formed. Hatshepsut is as close to the Pyramids as we are to the Viking Age. Nonetheless, we remember her – she was the first great woman of history (with the caveat that many great people came and went without record).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The New Kingdom emerged after a period of war and decline, and was an era of international reconnection. This was a time of colossal statues (not pyramid-building, as that age had passed), of tombs in hidden canyons, of kings and other nobles hunting captive animals taken from the African wilderness. Scribes wrote on astrology and magic, medicine and science; these scholars could be male or female. Farmers depended upon the Nile, and laborers (not slaves) worked in the cities. We have an impression of Egyptian monuments and cities composed entirely of sand-colored stone, but the outsides of temples and palaces were painted bright white while their insides were brilliant yellow and green.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Hatshepsut is considered the most influential queen of Egypt, not the first or the most famous (the latter may be Cleopatra), but one with a profound legacy of construction and consolidation of power. She turned her attention away from military exploits and towards construction closer to home, ushering forth a period of artistic and architectural innovation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>She was the oldest daughter of Thutmose I and married her brother Thutmose II (as was customary amongst Egyptian royalty). When Thutmose II died, Hatshepsut remained on the throne as a regent for her infant stepson Thutmose III (the son of Thutmose and a minor wife as Hatshepsut only had a daughter). However, she swept past the bounds of a normal regent and declared herself pharaoh. Her reasons for this power grab are unknown but might be related to her ambition or an unknown political crisis.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Hatshepsut's rule was politically interesting. The infant Thutmose III was promoted to pharaoh. Afterward, Hatshepsut claimed the title of co-ruler, becoming the younger king in a partnership with her stepson – though she wielded most of the practical power. Her rule as a woman was not unusual. Kings’ mothers often ruled when their children were too young – historian Ann Macy Roth suggests that women ruled Egypt for about half of the seventy years preceding Hatshepsut. However, her claim to be a pharaoh, Horus reborn, was unusual.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Hatshepsut’s first major achievement was the expansion of trade. Her second achievement was a vast period of construction. At the time, Egypt faced the ruins of the Hyksos invasion, a movement of people from the Near East into Egypt. Hatshepsut sought to rebuild the temples the invaders had destroyed. In so doing, she commissioned an enormous amount of sculpture; sadly, much of it was later destroyed by those seeking to erase her legacy. The temple at Deir el-Bahri seems to be her crowning achievement, a vast colonnade with a sweeping entrance staircase. After the preceding period of ruin, these construction projects propped up Hatshepsut’s legitimacy. With Egypt still reeling from war and her non-standard lineage, the queen needed to double down on any claim to godly heritage. Her declarations of godhood were as politically calculated as they were religious.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The child Thutmose III would not look fondly on his mother’s actions; after her death, he sought to erase her legacy. Thus archaeologists found many of her statues in a great pile of smashed art, a waste pit of Thutmose III's design. These statues are interesting for several reasons. Kings were the embodiment of Horus, a male god, so when Hatshepsut claimed the mantle of king, she needed to become male, at least symbolically, and many of her statues were changed from female to male; at the same time, many of Hatshepsut's male relatives and contacts began to use female pronouns to better align with her.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HATSHEPSUT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Hatshepsut died at 50 and was buried in the Valley of the Kings, though her body was later removed from her sarcophagus. An extra mummy found in her nurse’s tomb has been tentatively identified as Hatshepsut and is currently on display at the Egyptian Museum in Cairo. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_HIMIKO -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_HIMIKO_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Early Japanese history is divided into three distinct periods: the Jomon, the Yayoi, and the Yamato. It is during the latter period that what we recognize as “Japan” takes shape, although it is in the subsequent Heian period that a lot of the recognizable art, literature, and dress come into being – recall that the golden age of samurai, etc., does not come about until the middle of the second millennium CE. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Jomon Japan existed prior to anything, and is titled for its style of pottery, rather than any name the people would have called themselves. The Jomon people also appear a little ethnically different from other Japanese remains. This is a legacy of Japan’s links with Pacific islands – there are cultural similarities between the indigenous inhabitants of Okinawa, Taiwan, and further south into Southeast Asia. The Jomon appear to have been replaced by the Yayoi around the last millennium BCE, although the indigenous Ainu are likely their descendants.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>It was this Yayoi culture – Japanese-speaking migrants from the mainland (meaning Korea, in this case) that Himiko ruled. The Yayoi bridged the Neolithic, Bronze and Iron Ages, and grew quite adept at crafting bronze weapons, tools, and, significantly, mirrors. The Kofun era (300-538 CE) saw this industry expand, as well as the development of a shared cultural heritage with strong Chinese influence from Honshu (the big island of Japan) to Kyushu (a smaller island) to Korea. The era ends with the rise of the Yamato clan and consolidation of Japanese power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>These islands were called Wo or Wa, by the Han Dynasty and were a cluster of scattered peoples – a group of culturally similar but politically divided tribes clinging to an often harsh ecosystem and possessing a warlike outlook on life.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Himiko herself was both a religious and political leader. From her base at Yamatai (either northern Kyushu or near present-day Kyoto), she is primarily known from Chinese records. Himiko sent gifts to the Cao Wei kingdom, the northernmost of the three states that divided China between them in the third century CE. In these records Himiko is dubbed “Queen of Wa and friend of Wei” by the Chinese emperor. Himiko’s actual position is less clear – here we are at the very beginnings of Japanese history, where sources are scattered and unreliable. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Himiko’s story gets interesting when she is accused of sorcery. Chinese sources allege that she bewitched all of the residents of Wa into submitting to her rule, and that she lived in a great castle served entirely by female attendants and guards (excepting one man, who brought her food). This mystical reputation is compounded in Japanese records, which identify Himiko with a number of divine beings: as the high shaman of the Japanese sun goddess Amaterasu, or a shamanic wife of a divine snake. In this latter story, Himiko (identified by the name Yamato-toto-hi-momo-so-bime no Mikoto) is happily married to a clearly divine being who only visits at night. She begs him to stay until morning so that she can see him in the sunlight, but he demurs. Eventually, she convinces him, and he tells her that she will see him in her toilet-case, but she must promise not to be shocked at his appearance. The next morning, when she opens the case, there is a beautiful white snake coiled inside. Himiko gasps in alarm, and the god-snake changes back to his human form. He is angry, tells her that she had been warned not to react, and that now he must leave her. Himiko, in her grief, stabs herself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Whatever the nature of her demise, upon Himiko’s death, the people of Yamatai raised a burial mound for her. According to legend, the subsequent ruler was intended to be a king, but the people, still mourning their deceased queen, refused his rule until Himiko’s relative Iyo, a girl of thirteen, was offered as the new ruler, and order was restored. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>As mentioned above, Himiko forms one of the foundations of Japanese theories of monarchy and Shinto, fusing the political with the supernatural in ways that are different from the Confucian-inspired Chinese ideals and the Indic-inspired Brahmanist ideals found elsewhere in Asia. With Himiko and Yamatai, we also see the first opening of Japan to a larger East Asian world. She is a common figure in popular culture, although often adapted to suit the needed narrative. She can be a villain or a hero, magical or mortal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>In our representation here, we have patterned Himiko off of similar spirit mediums elsewhere in the region and presented her as a person who acts as a conduit for the goddess Amaterasu. Their relationship is close, like mother and daughter inhabiting the same body, and our Himiko switches between the two voices of queen and goddess seemingly without knowing. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_HIMIKO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Amaterasu – the sun goddess of ancient Japan that, in our representation, is Himiko’s divine muse – is no reserved figure. She is vivacious and tricksy, taking part in contests, disguising herself as a man, hiding from the other gods, and the like. In one of her most famous myths, the god Susanoo, her younger brother who was famously rude and troublesome, comes to Amaterasu to say his farewell after their father exiles him. Amaterasu decides to take pity on the boy. They have a chewing contest to see who can spit out the most gods, and although Amaterasu wins, Susanoo declares that he has spat out the correct gods and falls into a rage. In one version, he is so angry that he sneaks into Amaterasu’s palace and places excrement on her throne. She sits in it. This is so upsetting that she runs into a cave and hides herself (a problem because, remember, she is the sun). The other gods hatch a plan to draw her out, and they gather outside of her cave and make a great spectacle. This makes her curious, and she peeks out to see who is there – what she sees is her own reflection. The gods have hung a mirror just outside the entrance, and Amaterasu is transfixed. Order is restored (and, incidentally, the mirror becomes a vital symbol of Shinto). </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA_TITLE">
			<Text>Ibn Battuta (Abu Abdullah Muhammad ibn Battuta)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Many representations of history treat Europe as the center of the world, implying the rest of the planet was static until the Europeans arrived. However, in the Middle Ages, the center of the world was undoubtedly the Arab states of the Middle East. At the central axis of the Silk Road and all the other attached trade routes (sea routes down the Swahili coast, Saharan caravans) the Arab caliphates were the pre-eminent force bridging Europe and Asia, until a decline precipitated by internal fragmentation and the arrival of Central Asian nomads (namely the Turks and Mongols).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Islam spread with these trade networks. The principle was simple: Muslim merchants preferred to trade with other Muslims. If a ruler or merchant wanted to get rich quickly, he would convert. If a king wanted his city-state to grow wealthy, he would convert. And if he didn’t, there were several well-funded contenders to the throne who did.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Born in 1304 to a Moroccan and Berber family, Ibn Battuta's name literally means “son of the duckling,” but his full title is Shams al-Din Abu Abdallah Muhammad ibn Abdallah ibn Muhammad ibn Ibrahim al-Lawati al-Tanji. Early on, Ibn Battuta set out to chart the scale and scope of the Muslim world, leaving on the hajj (the Muslim pilgrimage to Mecca) at the age of 21. He would not return for decades, and in that course, he would travel the known world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Ibn Battuta took a series of voyages from 1325 until 1353, beginning with a long Mediterranean trip to Mecca via Cairo, then eastward to Baghdad and through Iran. Another voyage took him down the Swahili coast to Kilwa, then through the Persian Gulf. A third trip went east across Central Asia, India, and all the way to Beijing. His final journey was a comparatively short expedition from Grenada (in present-day Spain) to Mali. He dictated his travels, musings, and poetry in the rihla genre – a term used for such travelogues – under the title “A Masterpiece to Those who Contemplate the Wonders of Cities and the Marvels of Travelling.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Ibn Battuta can be thought of as a photographer, capturing poetic snapshots of the Muslim world at its height (although some of the claims in his rihla are contested). He was a poet, adventurer, and historian, and he lived and worked for a time as an ambassador and theologian. He was also a Muslim judge, employed by various courts to serve as an interpreter of the Koran; he was strictly critical of those whom he viewed as having unorthodox practices.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_IBN_BATTUTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>In sum, Ibn Battuta’s travels were the greatest of his age, eclipsing the distance traveled by both Marco Polo and Zheng He. His work gives us a human look at the state of the world in his time – its interconnections, people, and everyday life.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_ISABELLA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_TITLE">
			<Text>Isabella I of Castile</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The medieval history of Spain is framed by the Reconquista. For most of the early Middle Ages, much of Spain was Muslim-controlled and had a sizeable Muslim minority. From nearly the beginning of the caliphates’ arrival in the eighth century CE, Christian rulers pushed back against this rule. The final movement – the conquest of the Emirate of Granada – happened in 1492, under Isabella.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>From its inception, Spain was a country fighting a war of conquest. The Spanish Reconquista was a religious holy war of expansion that sought to “restore” Christian rule to the peninsula. This purpose did not stop after the fall of Granada. Shortly thereafter, Christopher Columbus set sail across the Atlantic Ocean with the goal of securing a lucrative trade route to the Indies to fund a new Crusade. The ensuing conquest of the New World occurred alongside more forays into former Arab territory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Isabella’s Spain was also intent on colonizing minds. The populace of formerly Muslim spaces was religiously diverse, and non-Muslims were permitted to practice their religion provided they paid a special tax (the jizya). Under Christian rule, Christianity was forcibly imposed, and those who were not willing to convert were driven out – even the Moors who did convert were subsequently expelled a century later. Social anxieties assumed that forced converts were not the most pious Christians, so the Reconquista gave way to the Spanish Inquisition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Several kingdoms make up “Spain.” The key ones are Aragon and Castile. Castile often was dominant over Aragon, but Isabella united the two via her marriages, although that unity would not become official for nearly two centuries, and has a legacy of separatist movements today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Isabella took power in a complicated manner. Her half-brother inherited the throne of Castile (as Henry IV), but he clashed with the nobility who demanded that the infant Alfonso (Isabella’s younger brother) take over. The resulting war was inconclusive, but young Alfonso was unable to claim the throne; he died of plague. Isabella and the rebels made a deal wherein Isabella would become the heir instead. This arrangement also stipulated that she would not be forced into marriage, so when she did marry the king of Aragon, Ferdinand, it was likely out of love. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Henry died in 1474, and Isabella became the ruler of both Spanish lands. Her reign was long and war-torn and focused on two key themes – erasing the legacies of both Moorish Spain and her brother. She sought to improve criminal codes that had grown lax under Henry and conquer the hearts and minds of her Spanish subjects, including those in newly conquered territories. This goal extended to indigenous Americans. While Columbus was brazen in his subjugation of indigenous people, Isabella was not. She banned the enslavement of New World populations and saw them as potential Spaniards – souls to be converted, not bodies to be turned into labor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_ISABELLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>In sum, Isabella was a devout and ruthless monarch, absolutely devoted to preserving and expanding Spain’s power. This led her into conflict with the pope, although they needed each other more than they cared to admit (the pope notably granted Isabella the title of “Catholic Monarch”). She remains a crucial figure in Spanish history, having begun the wave of overseas expansion that would lead to the Spanish Empire and presiding over the Inquisition and the end of the Reconquista. Ultimately, Isabella laid the foundations of the Catholic empire that Spain would become throughout the 16th and 17th centuries, setting it on a collision course with rising Protestant powers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_TITLE">
			<Text>Jose Rizal</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Where does the Philippines belong on world maps? At times, the islands were a bridge to Oceania, an outpost of Southeast Asian maritime mandala states, or an eastern destination for Spanish treasure fleets seeking to exchange New World bullion for Chinese goods. Before the Spanish, the islands were not unified, housing Muslim sultanates in the south and a variety of linguistic and cultural groups spread over the rest of the islands. This disunity was a boon to the conquering Spanish, who declared Manila the capital of their East Indian possessions in 1571.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Spanish Philippines were organized around church lands and co-opted local leaders (caciques). This structure tied rule to religion and quelled dissent, although conflict was consistently brewing and Spanish control was often weak. Outside powers saw how flimsy Spanish rule was over the Philippines. Local caciques and priests could be petty despots in their own right, and indigenous revolts were a consistent feature of Filipino history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Into this mix came the idea of nationalism. Though this concept had not existed previously, life under the Spanish banner gave Filipinos a common experience and a common foe and encouraged Filipinos to begin identifying as Filipinos. Over time, local rebellions became national rebellions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>This tension was compounded by local wealth. Before Mexican independence, the term Filipino referred to Spaniards born in the isles, but afterward it quickly came to refer to inhabitants of the isles, especially wealthy mixed families (e.g. the children of caciques). These wealthy families sent their children to study abroad, where they picked up the ideas of social liberalism that proliferated in Europe during the 19th century. By this point, too, the role of the clergy had been indigenized to the extent that Filipino nationalists were calling for the appointment of Filipino bishops. These movements were met with harsh backlash, including executions and exile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Enter Rizal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>José Rizal’s family was mestizo, which does not mean here mixed Filipino and white ancestry, as it might in the New World; in Rizal’s case, “mestizo” includes Chinese migrants. This was not unusual as wealthy Chinese set up prosperous merchant enclaves across the region and often worked their way into local elite circles (with notably less success in Muslim regions).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>By all accounts, Rizal was a genius. From a young age, he excelled at languages and poetry, performing well in school, but took up medicine after learning his mother was going blind. As a young man, he studied abroad in Madrid, Heidelberg, and Berlin, and was fluent in Tagalog, Spanish, German, English, and other languages. He was eventually credited with speaking twenty-two languages and even made translations from Arabic, Russian, Swedish, Sanskrit, Greek, and more.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Rizal was also a playboy. His affairs with prominent mestizo and European women were well-documented. These fueled his poetry, and more than one of his lovers’ families disapproved of him and arranged for their daughters to marry other (non-Filipino and non-radical) matches.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>But Rizal’s primary love was his homeland. His writing became more strident as the Spanish cracked down on nationalism. In his “El Filibusterismo” (“Reign of Greed" in English), his hero becomes increasingly frustrated with the cynical and greedy outlook of local administrators and seeks to abandon liberal reforms for violent overthrow. This deeply concerned the Spanish, who were already worried about Rizal’s work radicalizing Filipino expatriates and exiles in Madrid. But Rizal’s mission, contrary to that of his hero, seems reasonable today – the transformation of the Philippines into a core province of Spain, the promotion of Filipinos to higher positions within the priesthood, and the granting of freedoms of speech and assembly. Such rights were granted to the Spanish, and Rizal highlighted the double standard of denying them to colonial subjects.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>The situation came to a head when revolutionary movements in the Philippines turned violent. While Rizal and his group advocated for peaceful protest, the Spanish claimed he maintained contacts with an extremist wing, and he was imprisoned in Barcelona in 1896 (likely due in part to the content of his novel). He was executed in Manila a few weeks later. His last words were “consummatum est” – “it is done" in Latin. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>A couple of years later, Spanish rule came to an end when the Americans took the Philippines from Spain. The American administration was also colonial, but it was less harsh than that of the Spanish, though independence-minded Filipinos naturally still chafed at their presence. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOSE_RIZAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>Rizal’s works, especially “Reign of Greed,” are now required reading in the Philippines. He is perhaps the best-recognized symbol of Filipino nationalism. In this light, he sits alongside Mahatma Gandhi and Sun Yat-Sen as an anti-colonial figure who sought independence through non-violent means.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_LAFAYETTE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Marquis de Lafayette is a figure associated with revolution who emerged when the world seemed in flux. What is the role of nobility? What rights inherently belong to men (and women) – and which men and women? These issues came to the fore in the mid-18th century. As empires flourished, they promoted certain well-off classes; tradesmen and businessmen grew increasingly influential and powerful – the aristocracy even more so. But these groups desire very different things from the government. This tension set the stage for the American Revolution…and France’s involvement.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>France had long been England’s rival, so we cannot read too much into the ideology behind the French crown's support of American revolutionaries. The French had warred with the English over the domination of Canada in the French and Indian War (and lost), but this was a small prelude to the larger Seven Years’ War – a massive colonial conflict between nearly all European powers. From a French perspective, the American colonies' declaration of independence was one theater of a larger Anglo-French clash.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In all of these conflicts, the Marquis de Lafayette took part.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Lafayette is not a name; it is a title. He is the Marquis (a step below a duke) of La Fayette, but his full name is Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier. His family was old and noble, dating back to Joan of Arc’s time. He had no right to be a revolutionary, and certainly no need. Yet his conscience drove him – as did revenge.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Lafayette’s father was killed by a British cannonball. As a very young man, he left for America to assist the French efforts to undermine British ambitions. In America, he was influential as a naval commander, especially in the decisive Battle of Yorktown, during which the French artillery trapped British naval divisions and captured the British commander, causing an American victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>After the end of the American Revolution, Lafayette returned to a still-simmering Paris. The French Revolution was brewing, as commoners called for reforms and, eventually, a dissolution of the monarchy – a move ironically inspired by the American Revolution that the French monarchy had supported. But the French Revolution was not a single revolution that conclusively lopped off kings’ heads to bring about the rule of the people; it was a cycle from republic to monarchy to dictatorial empire and back again. Old kings retook the throne…and generals crowned themselves new kings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Lafayette managed to keep a humanist center amidst this ideological, and very real, chaos. He epitomizes a certain kind of liberal politician – “liberal” meaning the acknowledged rights and fundamental independence of the individual. Famously driven by principles, he did not hesitate to stand against his friends if he disagreed with them. He descended from noble blood but was an advocate for (restrained) revolution. He was a close friend of American revolutionaries with large plantations (George Washington and Thomas Jefferson) but had a lifelong opposition to slavery. He managed to be in the direct center of the French Revolution and avoid being killed, even when those to his left and right were being guillotined.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Upon his return to France, he was hailed as the “Hero of Two Worlds.” In France, he was key in solidifying American and French ties, although he advocated strongly for the abolition of slavery and for negotiating peace with the Haudenosaunee. He also helped with the drafting of the American Constitution, becoming an American citizen by that process (before the concept had even come to France!).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Some years later, France was spiraling towards its crisis. The King appointed Lafayette as his representative to an assembly of nobles, but Lafayette called for more popular participation and a diminishing of royal power, creating the National Assembly. With Jefferson’s help, he wrote the Declaration of the Rights of Man, a document that has had a wide-ranging influence on the growth of democracies worldwide. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>As an aside, he designed the insignia of the National Guard with red, white, and blue colors that were to become the French flag – red and blue being the colors of Paris and white the color of the monarchy (though Lafayette himself insisted that white represented the French nation, and not the Bourbon dynasty).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Lafayette presented this Declaration to the Assembly with great success, but things rapidly moved out of his hands. The Assembly wanted a Constitution, and the King refused to provide it. The monarchy retrenched and the Third Estate (the peasants) rose up to take over particular sites, most notably the infamous prison, the Bastille. To keep order, the Assembly created the National Guard of France with the noble Lafayette in command. This offered a shaky truce, but Lafayette was capable. For example, when the National Guard marched on the palace to deliver the Declaration to the king, the people broke into the Palace of Versailles, and Lafayette ushered the royal family out to a balcony overlooking the crowd. When people cried “Shoot her,” referring to Marie Antoinette, Lafayette kissed her hand, diverting a massacre (which was still to come) into a public show of royalist piety.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>This was Lafayette’s political role in a nutshell. He was an Enlightenment advocate for liberty, and he adopted revolutionary ideas that prioritized the good of individual people, their natural rights, and the nation. However, he was also a constitutional monarchist – he wanted the king to live under those same rules, not be a god on earth. He was a consummate diplomat.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>But there was more to come. Imprisoned in the palace under Lafayette’s eye, the king tried to escape, and Lafayette took the blame. After a royalist massacre of revolutionaries, Lafayette’s reputation was fatally wounded. In a final attempt to maintain the center, he rallied against the radical Jacobins, but as these revolutionaries gained more power and influence, his reputation was further ruined. The royal family was imprisoned (and ready for the chopping block). Lafayette fled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>Time passed. Revolutionary France gave rise to Napoleon and eventually the restoration of the monarchy. And the monarchy was up to its old tricks; Charles X wanted absolute power, so Lafayette was called in to negotiate. When Charles removed the bourgeoisie's ability to vote (these were the property-owning commoners and artisans), he sparked another revolution, one that did not lead to a new Republic but placed yet another king on the throne of France – under Lafayette’s suggestion. This monarch also turned out to be an autocrat, giving rise to the failed June Rebellion (which lives on as the inspiration for “Les Misérables”). Lafayette died soon after.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>Lafayette has several legacies. In the United States, he was heralded as a hero, largely due to his charm and his young age. Washington saw the young Lafayette as a kind of foster son, and the other revolutionaries were impressed by his devotion to the cause.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_16">
			<Text>In France, his legacy is more complicated. He worked tirelessly as a moderate voice, combining constitutional monarchy with Enlightenment ideas of the rights of man. While Lafayette’s dream for France never fully took shape in his time, it did materialize in America (except for the preservation of slavery, which Lafayette opposed).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LAFAYETTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_17">
			<Text>His Declaration of the Rights of Man has also been profoundly influential, inspiring women’s suffragette movements in the US, the Latin American revolutions of the early 18th century, and even Ho Chi Minh’s Vietnamese revolution in 1945.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_MACHIAVELLI -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One approach to power is the medieval focus on idealized rulers who anticipate the kingdom of God, forever striving for perfection. Machiavelli epitomizes the opposite: brutal acquisitions of power, based not on what should happen but on what does. Machiavelli can be considered one of the first modern political philosophers. This is also why his name is synonymous with backstabbing, end-oriented, and manipulative strategies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>To understand Machiavelli’s world, one must start with the great waves that flowed over Western Europe in the late Middle Ages. In Spain, the last of the Arab caliphates had been driven out, and the country was looking for new places to push conquest. In the wake of the eastern Arab empires, new Turkish powers appeared and pressed Byzantium to the brink.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>However, the biggest world-shaking force was biological: the Black Death. The plague reshaped the world. In China, it shattered the Mongol Empire, which had ensured the Silk Road's seamless flow. In Europe, it ended the feudal system's ready supply of cheap agricultural labor. And in Italy, the devastation allowed people to rethink the role of merchant kings and noble families. These figures were already influential and intimately linked with the power struggles at the Vatican, but now they were at the central nexus of trade and power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>The “Renaissance” refers to the rediscovery of classical texts by Europeans (mainly Italians). This shift led to new, humanist ways of seeing the world that ended many notions of monarchy and encouraged people to rethink important questions such as how to rule.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Niccolò Machiavelli is often synonymous with a particular kind of realpolitik – the strategic amassing of power and influence unhindered by morality or principle. But this reputation is slightly unjustified. Machiavelli was much more than his political ideology; he was a playwright, comic, translator, and philosopher in his own right, and produced more than the text that came to define him: “The Prince.” </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>In “The Prince,” Machiavelli outlines a strategy for a new ruler. His recommendations are shocking in their cold pragmatism. Machiavelli focused on reconstructing the grounds for power as a means of keeping it. For instance, while it might be ideal for a ruler to maintain the love of his subjects, the best alternative is to be feared. A prince should strive to be honest; if this is impossible, then he should lie and keep the appearance of honesty. From a Machiavellian perspective, certain measures – such as wiping out powerful rival families or instilling fear in the population – are necessities in some situations. In short, “The Prince” is a guidebook to being a ruthless, manipulative, despicable – but successful – ruler. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Machiavelli came from a line of lawyers in the Florentine Republic. He steadily moved up in the administrative ranks and even conducted some minor diplomacy – something in high order in an era when families like the Medici and Borgias were conquering and brutalizing each other’s communities. In 1509, Machiavelli led a small force of local Florentine militia to take the city of Pisa, but he quickly faced reprisals from the pope. In disgrace, Machiavelli’s patron family resigned from the leadership of Florence and ended the Republic. Soon after, the former strongmen – the infamous Medici – returned to the city and had Machiavelli imprisoned and tortured.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>After three weeks of hanging on “the rope,” Machiavelli was released and lived out his days on a family farm in the countryside, where he completed his writing. His cynical view was informed by his exposure to ruthless politics during a time when new ideas (such as republicanism) took root as the trappings of the Middle Ages began to dissolve – and a period where pious popes raised armies and had their foes executed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Machiavelli reshaped how we think about power and control, moving away from high-minded ideals towards practical considerations. He could be considered in contrast with a person like Confucius, someone who had been in a very similar position as a court advisor (though to a far larger empire in a far earlier time). Confucius thought there should be a strict code of conduct focused on respect for tradition and goodwill towards others, and that following this code would mean that rulers would prosper. Machiavelli is the opposite – a modernist and pragmatist. His brutal (or brutally honest) stance earned him the enmity of other famous historical figures. Prussia’s Friedrich II penned the “Anti-Machiavelli,” which sought to extol the virtues of the enlightened despot over the manipulative prince, but was undercut by Prussia’s own power-hungry status.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Perhaps Machiavelli's reputation is undeserved. He addressed his book to the Medici family – his torturers and banishers. Later readers may note his more sympathetic attitude towards republics in “Discourses on Livy.” One can picture an elder Machiavelli, exiled in his country home, bearing the scars of torture, writing a cynical and bitter discourse on how to exercise power without conscience before adding his torturers’ name in the dedication, saying to the Medicis, “Here, here is who you really are."</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_MACHIAVELLI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Regardless, Machiavelli is considered one of the first modernist political philosophers who tried to think strategically and systematically about how populations function. His works could be considered satire; it is a dark statement that such a dystopic view of the world has become the foundation of much of our modern politics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_PACHACUTI -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_PACHACUTI_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_PACHACUTI_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_PACHACUTI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Pachacuti’s story starts and ends before Europeans ever arrived in the New World (discounting a few Norse adventurers half a world away). This is not a story of postcolonial resistance, it is a story of domination and hegemony in the Andes highlands. And it sets the stage for a world the Spanish would later discover.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_PACHACUTI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Kingdom of Cuzco was ruled by the Sapa Inca, the “only Inca,” a lineage supposedly descended from the sun itself and which became hereditary over time. But before this, the Sapa Inca was determined through a series of challenges and divination, or, for Pachacuti, smarts and good fortune.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_PACHACUTI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Pachacuti, whose given name was Cusi Yupanqui, was one of several sons of the preceding Inca, Viracocha Inca. Viracocha was a proud and warlike emperor who claimed he would conquer half of the world. Naturally, other people objected to this, and some of them – the Chanka, another Quechua-speaking group – decided to eclipse the would-be sun before his conquest began. Abandoning his claim, Viracocha fled the capital with his favored son, Urco Inca, who had been acknowledged as the next Inca. This left Cusi Yupanqui to fend off invaders. According to legend, Cusi Yupanqui’s defense was so brilliant that the stones rose up to fight for him – it sounds like a poetic allegory, but the Inca religion revolved around the tirakuna, earth beings who embody the mountains and rocks. The invaders fell, and Cusi Yupanqui offered the captives to his father so his father could wipe his feet. His father refused; Viracocha wanted his older son, Urco, to be the next Inca and to make the offering. The ensuing argument went poorly, and Viracocha became so offended that he plotted to assassinate Cusi Yupanqui. This plan failed and Viracocha was run out of the capital, leaving Cusi Yupanqui to become Pachacuti.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_PACHACUTI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Pachacuti means “reformer of the world,” but could also translate to “cataclysm” or “earth-shaker.” His expansion involved fortifying Cuzco into a distinct city with large stone structures, districts for each social class, elaborate road systems, and a well-defined priesthood (vital to the selection of the next Inca). Under Pachacuti, Cuzco became a proper empire. This system of rule centered on the divinity of the ruler – Inca rulers often married within their own families to preserve their divine ancestry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_PACHACUTI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Outside of Cuzco, the empire incorporated disparate groups, consuming artistic styles and cultural elements with imperial style. Notable construction under Pachacuti included Machu Pikchu (which was possibly Pachacuti’s private estate) and the Temple of the Sun in Cuzco. Settlers were aggressively dispatched to new communities, and each settlement followed a distinct caste-like system where particular groups lived in certain areas. Pachacuti also composed a series of religious hymns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_PACHACUTI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Then Pachacuti died…of old age. Leaders who pass away peacefully on their deathbed are unusual among our leaders. Pachacuti is responsible for how we think of the Inca Empire today. He became a hero and inspiration to Quechua leaders, including the ill-fated rulers who encountered the Spanish – and the rebels who fought them. Without Pachacuti, the Andes might look more diverse, but they would also lack a sense of Andean civilization’s greatness.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_TITLE">
			<Text>Trung Trac</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Look at a map of Southeast Asia and southern East Asia and take note of a few key details. Travel by water is much easier than travel by land, especially where monsoons and rainforests make moving too far into the landscape impossible. Rivers – the Irrawaddy, the Salween, the Chao Phraya, and the Mekong – become lifelines for rice-planting civilizations; other realms are built upon trade routes. Mountains are walls – in Laos and along the western borders of Vietnam, no rivers cross them, and they are thickly forested. This is why Vietnam, originating in the Red River delta and possessing a relatively open (geographically) border with China, struggled mostly with its northern neighbor, and also incorporated so much of Chinese culture; yet as one goes further south and west, Indian influence grows.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Vietnamese language belongs to the Mon-Khmer family, meaning that it is related to many of the oldest Southeast Asian languages. Vietnam also possesses a few Southeast Asian features, including a relatively high status for women. But most of its culture is adapted from northern importations – its script, style of Buddhism, and system of governance were all similar to Chinese (until the French altered written Vietnamese to the Roman alphabet).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Trung Trac’s story begins more than two centuries before her birth (around the time of the construction of the terracotta warriors) when a military commander from the collapsing Qin Empire fled south and seized lands from Hong Kong to Hanoi. He called this new kingdom Nanyue, the Southern Yue kingdom, pronounced Nam Viet in Vietnamese. He also declared it to be independent…of sorts. The newly ascendant Han Dynasty tolerated Nanyue's existence as long as it remained a Chinese vassal. The Yue people likely included a wide variety of unrelated groups: Cantonese speakers, Vietnamese people (kinh), Tai speakers, and Trung Trac’s people – the Lac Viet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Over time, the Han reconsolidated and sought expansion. In 111 BCE, they conquered Nanyue directly. During this “First Chinese Domination of Vietnam,” the Han embarked on an aggressive campaign to turn Yue “tribes” into good Chinese subjects. This involved aggressive suppression of Vietnamese customs and the imposition of Confucianism, the imperial political system, and Chinese writing. These measures were not popular.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The Trung sisters were two wealthy daughters of a Lac Viet family who grew up while Han governors were quickly trying to subvert adherence to Lac tradition and “civilize” the barbarians. This cultural conflict became a sticking point when the husband of Trung Trac was killed for opposing these efforts and plotting a rebellion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>After his execution, Trung Trac and her sister rose up and toppled Chinese rule in the region around Hanoi (then called La Thanh). The two sisters seized over 60 cities; once these were secured, Trung built lines of reinforcement and repaired infrastructure that had been languishing under Chinese rule. An independent Nanyue – Vietnam – was within reach.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>But their rule was to last only three years, after which the Han sent a massive retaliatory force to retake the region. Trung fled to a narrow canyon where she believed she could make a defensive stand, but she realized that her troops were too disorganized. What happens next varies depending on the version of the story: the Trung sisters were either killed, committed suicide, or vanished into the sky.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_TRUNG_TRAC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The Trung sisters are revered as national heroes today, and people dress as them in parades in Saigon and elsewhere. While Vietnam has its own legacy of imperialism vis-à-vis the Cham, or highland peoples, it has also been the victim of imperialist aggression for a long time from the Chinese (and French and Americans). Figures like Trung feed into this narrative, becoming powerful symbols of Vietnamese resistance to invaders – whether they come from across the seas or next door. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- LEADER_XERXES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_TITLE">
			<Text>{LOC_LEADER_XERXES_NAME}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “Persia” originates from the Greek name for the empire of Iran, the land of the Farsi people, who are referred to as “Aryan” in other texts (bearing in mind the term’s association with North India and not with the strange alterations it carried in the 19th and 20th centuries). In the Achaemenid period, Persia was the largest empire at that point in history (Alexander the Great took that title a few years later). The empire extended from Egypt and parts of Greece in the west to the Indus River Valley in the east, encompassing and surpassing what we now know as the Middle and Near East today. Despite its size, or perhaps because of it, Persia had sophisticated transportation networks and bureaucratic and communication systems; was multi-cultural and multi-religious; and established a clear lingua franca throughout its domain. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Early on, the Persians took slow control over Mesopotamia as Babylon and Assyria declined. Under Cyrus the Great, it expanded into Asia Minor and transformed into an empire. Cyrus' line was overthrown by Darius – also "the Great" – who led the Persians to another wave of conquests, this time in Egypt and the Indus Valley. But this triumph was tenuous. With revolt brewing in Egypt, Darius suddenly died and was succeeded by Xerxes – the last and arguably greatest of the Persian emperors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Xerxes became famous for his campaign against Greece, including the battles of Thermopylae and Salamis. He was a subject of Herodotus’s histories, an inspiration for Alexander the Great, and an icon for cruel tyrants – largely based on Greek perspective. However, while Xerxes was proud and occasionally cruel, he was no cartoon villain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Xerxes descended from two great emperors – his father was Darius, and his grandfather (on his mother’s side) was Cyrus. He was raised by court eunuchs, as was the custom, and taught horsemanship (the Persians were only a few generations out from being Central Asian horse nomads). His life in the palace of Babylon was one of luxury.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Xerxes' early brush with destiny came when Darius, preparing to leave for Egypt to quash its rebellion, fell ill and unexpectedly died. In the wake of this death, the question of succession loomed. Should the crown go to Darius’ eldest? Or to Xerxes, the grandson of Cyrus? A debate was arranged to solve this question, and Xerxes won, taking the throne in 486 BCE, at the age of 35. He also inherited his father’s wars and immediately took to quelling Egypt, followed by Babylon after that city rebelled. He enacted a brutal vengeance upon Babylon, melting the statues of its gods in punishment. Indeed, Xerxes was staunchly religious (likely adhering to a precursor of Zoroastrianism).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Still, Xerxes is most famous for his invasion of Greece. Darius had attempted such a campaign, which seemed logical since Persia already occupied all of Asia Minor. However, Darius was thwarted at Marathon. Following in his father’s footsteps, Xerxes pulled no punches. He amassed a gargantuan army, built a bridge over the Hellespont (the straits at modern Istanbul), and marched his troops over it. At the Battle of Thermopylae, Xerxes' massive Persian army was stalled by only around 7,000 Spartans – a battle that has become the most renowned example of Spartan bravery in history. However, the keyword here is “stalled,” not “stopped.” Xerxes eventually continued down the Greek coast, and Athens was destroyed. Many Athenians fled to the island of Salamis and bunkered down as the Persians prepared a naval assault. Unfortunately, that battle did not go in favor of the Persians. After the Athenians won, the Persians – mindful of their fragile bridge over the Hellespont – decided that they’d had enough.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Alexander the Great would enact Greece's revenge more than a century later, but this failure brought an end to Xerxes’s plans of domination. Upon returning home to Persia, he turned his gaze inward, funding a dramatic boom in construction, arts, and infrastructure. Persian roads and postal relay systems were some of the most advanced the world had ever seen, and the great capital of Persepolis continued to rise in splendor. Though these ambitious projects did irreparable damage to the royal treasury, the remains of Xerxes’ palaces and monuments are still visible today. He was assassinated in 465.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_XERXES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>In Greek texts, Xerxes often plays a foil to democratic Athens. Indeed, this Greek portrait colors our modern view of Asia and Asian antiquity. When the Greeks categorized the Persians as despotic, aggressive, fundamentally undemocratic, and weak from living in a soft climate of rich land, that says more about Greek resentment than it does about real history. This trope persists because Athens reports most of our Greek history, and they accomplished this by juxtaposing themselves with others: Athenian democracy versus Spartan militarism and Athenian freedom versus Persian despotism. They didn't necessarily chronicle things as they were; they made a political point.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>