<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Antiquity Age Resources -->
		<!-- Luxury Resources-->
		<!-- RESOURCE_COTTON -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COTTON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>From the Neolithic on, humans began creating textiles from plant fibers, and cotton was a clear candidate for manufacture. Cotton has been discovered as a cultivar in both the New World and Old, indicating that its unique properties were recognized independently, at multiple times. The boll of the cotton – the fluffy fibrous mass where its seeds are embedded – holds the real prize, but teasing out the sticky seeds is a labor-intensive problem. These fibers can be woven into cloth, or processed into prized materials such as velvet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COTTON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>India and Egypt were ideal locations for cotton cultivation, and it became a prime crop for colonial empires. In India, this became a point of contention. Before the British arrived, India had a local cotton manufacturing system. Afterward, Indian cotton was exported to textile mills in Britain, and finished textiles were re-imported at sizeable markups. In the United States, cotton is bound up with the story of slavery – enslaved people were tasked with growing, picking, and processing cotton bolls, so the introduction of the cotton gin (which automated the laborious picking) led to a crash in the price of labor, leading to even worse conditions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_DATES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_DATES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When the sun sets during the month of Ramadan, and Muslims are permitted to break their fast, they often do so with dates, in commemoration of the Prophet. Date palms have grown in the Mediterranean, the Near East, and India for millennia. When dried, their fruits make a for a snack high in fiber, vitamins, and sugar. But Islam is not the only religion that lays claim to dates – they are significant in Jewish and Roman food cultures as well. Today, dates come in an astounding variety of preparations, from drying to fermenting, that change their overall taste and sweetness. Their flavor is often likened to honey.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_DYES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_DYES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Dyes have been used since the Neolithic to enliven the human world with color. Our Paleolithic ancestors (and their Neanderthal contemporaries) painted themselves, the walls of their rock shelters, and their gravestones with red ochre. In the Neolithic, textiles entered the mix, providing a broad canvas on which people could put colors, designs, and other forms of artistic expression. Rare dyes were valuable, by virtue of being rare, and one of the most notable dyes was the Mediterranean Tyrian purple, sourced from sea snails. The manufacture of this dye was so difficult that “the purple,” in Roman times, became a euphemism for royal. In Asia, saffron dyes became similarly associated with an office: in this case, religious leaders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_FISH -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_FISH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Fishing has historically been a central part of human livelihoods. The Powhatans of North America built weirs of sticks driven into river mud to create blind mazes where fish could easily be caught. Throw-nets or gill-nets were also common around the world. Fish became a significant commodity as large seafaring ships hit the waters. Particularly rich fishing zones, such as the Grand Banks off the coast of Newfoundland, offered rich sources of cod and other fish that could be salted and transported back to Europe, or consumed by hungry sailors. In the Baltic, herring (pickled in a variety of ways) became a major product, traded by the Hanseatic League and its competitors. Indeed, the city of “merchants’ harbor,” the literal translation of Copenhagen, was built upon the herring industry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_FISH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Over time, fishing created problems. The introduction of seemingly profitable species into vulnerable ecosystems, such as the Nile perch in Lake Victoria, caused an ecological disaster, while the sheer scale of overfishing had taken its toll on ocean-going industries. Tuna, for all its popularity, is an endangered species. Plastics, hydropower in river systems, and climate change contribute to the crash of fisheries worldwide.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_GOLD -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_GOLD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Gold is the sweat of the sun, according to the Inca. This soft metal is frequently found in its bright, elemental form. It has some industrial uses, but for most of recorded history, humans found value in its uselessness – its beauty. Gold is ductile, meaning it is easily shaped, and it does not corrode, making it an ideal substance for jewelry, coinage, and the like. However, gold's softness means it is unsuitable (not to mention too rare) for tools. Some of the earliest gold artifacts, crafted over six millennia ago, were discovered around the Black Sea, at Varna. These are bracelets and plates of gold that may have emerged from a newly established patriarchal, warlike culture. This was a troubling development for the burgeoning agricultural river valleys of the Near East, which would see history repeat itself over and over again as waves of Central Asian nomads emerged to take power over soft river cities, only to become soft themselves over generations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_GOLD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Gold always held the dual role of being a source of beauty and an object of greed. Protestants and Muslims frowned on the over-use of gold. In Jewish folklore, the idolatrous calf that Moses discovered his followers worshipping was made of gold. The metal was also significant in the New World amongst Aztec and Inca societies, and especially the Muisca people of Colombia, whose sources of gold were legendary. As rumors of gold resources reached explorers such as Christopher Columbus, they sparked the rapacious expansion of colonial powers across that continent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_GYPSUM -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_GYPSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hydrated calcium sulfate, called gypsum after the Greek word for “chalk,” forms as brine but turns into a translucent crystal after being subjected to pressure and heat under the Earth's surface for hundreds of millions of years. As such, it often exists alongside other remnants of the sea floor: salt deposits or limestone. Gypsum has been known since Egyptian times as a source of plaster. The association of hard-hydrated calcium sulfate with powdery calcium sulfate hemihydrate is what makes it so useful – by heating gypsum and releasing some of its water, one can form the powder into shapes. When more water is added, it hardens again. While plaster isn’t terribly strong, it is useful as a building material. Due to gypsum's sulfur content, it also has uses in agriculture, as fertilizer.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_INCENSE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_INCENSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rituals in many religions involve the negotiation between the visible and invisible worlds. Scent and burnt offerings are key examples of this interaction, as they involve something material turning immaterial (to ancient peoples’ eyes), seemingly moving from the realm of the material into the realm of the spirit. Incense was used by very ancient societies, from the Harappans of the Indus River Valley to Egypt and Mesopotamia. It involves combining a slow-burning paste with scented oils, often bonded onto a stick or formed into a cone. Incense has been important in rituals from Catholicism to Orthodoxy, Buddhism to Hinduism, and beyond – and has even been used as a way to keep mosquitoes away.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_IVORY -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_IVORY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ivory refers to the hard, off-white enamel of teeth or tusks of large mammals, generally elephants, though people have harvested hippopotamus, whale, walrus and even mammoth. Ivory graced the eyes of Roman statues, the handles of Javanese daggers, and the masks of Beninese queens. While domesticated elephants existed in South and Southeast Asia, these materials largely came from hunting. The demand for ivory caused the disappearance of elephants across Africa and the Near East, and, in the present day, has nearly caused the wholesale disappearance of elephants en masse: accordingly, many nations ban the trade of ivory altogether.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_JADE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_JADE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Jade was always the mark of kings. In China, jade ornaments and tools were carved for royals – or those who desired to live like royals. Jade combs, drinking vessels, pipe stems, and writing implements would all increase one’s health, prosperity, and prestige. This was especially true with the Six Ritual Jades: markers of prestige that have existed since before recorded history. Jade is widely considered green, but Chinese jade was originally pale – the later Burmese jade carries a greenish luster. Jade was mined from the Kachin highlands as a part of the complicated and often antagonistic relationship between lowland and highland people. It remains a source of both jade and conflict.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_JADE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In Mesoamerica and among the Māori, jade had functions similar to that in Asia – a rare mineral associated with beauty, art, and magic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_KAOLIN -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_KAOLIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Kaolin refers to fine white clay, used today in a variety of ways: as a glaze on paper, as a whitener in cosmetics, or in paint. The word is unfamiliar to many, but its primary historical form is not: porcelain, a hard, at times translucent, pottery, fired at extremely high temperatures. Porcelain was one of the earliest trade products from Asia (especially China) to Europe, and its lightness, hardness, delicacy, and color was a marker of prestige and refinement for those who could afford it. Attempts to replicate Chinese (and later Korean and Japanese) porcelain involved a fair degree of espionage and stealth until, in 1710, production began in what is now Germany.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_MARBLE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_MARBLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When ancient sea beds were buried under layers and layers of silt and sand, the pressure of all that rock transformed mounds of shells into limestone. If that limestone is pushed deeper underground, approaching the hot mantle of the earth, the process is even more intense and the rock is transformed yet again. Marble, like limestone, is soft and good for carving, but unlike limestone it is hard enough to resist chipping and crumbling. When marble is thin, it has an almost translucent quality, making it capable of stunning, lifelike sculptures. Marble has been used in antiquity and today for its beauty, in the creation of stunning works of art and architecture. Michelangelo saw an "angel" in the marble (and carved until he set him free), and Shah Jahan saw fit to place his beloved in a marble tomb: the Taj Mahal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_PEARLS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_PEARLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Pearls are formed out of annoyance. When a bivalve mollusk, such as an oyster or river mussel, finds an irritant (often a parasite) that it cannot expel, it coats the grain with layer upon layer of calcite, attempting to make it easier to live with. Therefore these highly prized jewels are essentially parasites wrapped in mollusk excretion. Ancient pearls were found by divers, most notably in the Indian Ocean and Red Sea (though Britain had its own source in river mussels), and were sought after by nobility around the world. The Chinese associated pearls with the mythic power of dragons and hunted for them extensively in Southeast Asia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_SILK -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_SILK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Many insects, and some arachnids, produce silk: fine, hyper-strong filaments with a unique structure that causes them to shimmer in the light. This material is used to form the cocoons in which larvae transform into full-fledged adults – that is, if people let them. Silk from these cocoons has been used since nearly the Neolithic in a variety of places, from East Asia to Mesoamerica, but the silkworm saw its greatest use in China. Chinese silk production dates back to the earliest dynasties and grew in earnest during the Han. Silk was traded along the route named for the commodity and found markets (as well as new growing grounds) in Korea, Southeast Asia, India, and beyond. Indeed, silk markets grew both east and west, with silk adorning sultans’ robes, saris, European furnishings, Laotian sin, and a variety of goods in between.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_SILVER -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_SILVER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>One of the most ancient metals known to humanity, pure silver is bright and glossy, making it attractive to the earliest people. Near Eastern societies used silver to create some of the first metal art; they also used it as a currency. Silver differs a little from gold, as the latter easily retains its splendor (meaning it does not oxidize), so gathering large quantities of silver requires refining (in this case, heating to a high temperature to extract pure metal from base metals). Even before recorded history, this technique was used in places as diverse as Japan, Egypt, India, and the Mediterranean, where Phoenician traders were instrumental in moving silver from places of production to places of wealth. In the era of colonization, silver, not gold, formed the backbone of the Spanish mines in South America, where it was then traded en masse to China in exchange for Chinese luxury goods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_WINE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_WINE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Alcohol is one of the earliest human inventions. Ancient peoples from Mesoamerica, Europe, Africa, and Asia fermented maize, wheat, fruit, honey, and rice using agents as varied as natural yeast, bacteria, and even human saliva. Wine made of grapes has a special place in society. It is transformed from grape juice as naturally occurring yeast breaks down the fruit’s sugars, converting it to alcohol and changing its flavor. First identified in Georgia during the Neolithic, wine was a common drink across the Near East and Mediterranean. Homer described troubled seas as “wine-dark,” and Jesus turned water into wine. At the same time, edicts from Mohammad to Chandragupta Maurya to the Buddha forbade their followers from indulging (or over-indulging) in the intoxicating drink, thus indicating its temptation.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Strategic Resources-->
		<!-- RESOURCE_CAMELS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_CAMELS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Much like horses, camels – those two-toed, malcontented ungulates termed “ships of the desert” – are New World animals that crossed the Bering land bridge at a distant point in prehistory, only to survive in the Old World and die off in the New (their relatives, the llamas, remain). Camels present certain advantages over horses. Most obvious is their ability to survive for long periods of time without water. A camel’s hump(s) are made of fat, which is composed largely of water, allowing them to survive without drinking for over a week. Camel blood cells are specially adapted to withstand rapid influxes of water, enabling them to replenish water stores in one great draught. Additionally, horses appear to be repelled by the scent of camels, which is a surprising benefit in cavalry combat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_CAMELS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>There are two varieties of camels: the “one-humped” dromedary, domesticated in the Near East, and the “two-humped” Bactrian camel, domesticated in Central Asia around the same time. Arab, Ottoman, Mughal, and Persian forces all made extensive use of camels, as did the Mongol, Roman, and Chinese armies, to a lesser extent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_HIDES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_HIDES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Humans have thin skin. That is not a metaphor (though sometimes true) – rather, human flesh requires protection, and many creatures possess thicker hides, which we have long used to rely on for warmth, armor, or to soften the rough edges of metal and wooden tools. Our ancestors used hides for clothing long before recorded history, and leatherworking was developed by the Paleolithic, at the very least. This process involves breaking down animal skins to render them more durable and pliable and is key to making long-lasting hide-based materials. Leather mostly comes from cattle, though in pre-agricultural times a wider variety of animals might have been used. Aside from clothing, hides were used to produce parchment, rawhide, and coverings for basic houses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_HORSES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_HORSES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Of all the domesticated animals, only the dog has a closer relationship with humans. For much of history, humans shared a special link with horses. If dogs were our substitute eyes and ears, horses were our legs. Though horses evolved in the New World, they migrated to the Old World two million years ago; their cousins in North America were subsequently wiped out (along with a large number of American megafauna). Horses were familiar to nomads of the Central Asian steppe, where they were first domesticated around 5,000 years ago and used for pulling chariots (ancient horses were likely smaller than present-day horses and could more easily pull chariots than support the full weight of a mounted warrior). These chariots became effective tools of war (as the Egyptians found out) but were replaced by the ultimate Eurasian weapon: the horse archer. While the Mongols are the most famous, the Parthians of around 300 BCE were the first recorded mounted archers. Later, as horses spread across the world, other plains-based warrior societies took up the tradition. With the invention of the car, the link between human and horse has waned, though they remain close to many people’s hearts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_IRON -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_IRON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to Finnish legend, the divine smith Ilmarinen brought iron out of the bogs and fens to make tools for humanity. He sought to infuse the metal with a bee’s honey to make it gentle and kind, but he accidentally put wasp’s poison into the metal instead and forged the iron we know today – iron that makes tools as well as weapons of war. At the very end of prehistory, ironworking spread in various ways throughout the Old World. In the Near East, some five millennia ago, people began to smelt iron for basic tools and weapons, a technology that expanded across Asia and Africa, and later Europe, where the Celts spread the technology. Iron was not always superior to bronze; bronze is sharper and more durable, but iron is more pliable and cheaper to produce. Roman soldiers often noted that the swords of their Germanic foes would blunt and bend after a few rounds of fighting. But iron, refined with high heat, contains some amount of steel, and steel is harder, sharper, and more durable than bronze. Steel made all the difference in warfare – at least until gunpowder.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_SALT -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_SALT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Sodium chloride, most commonly associated with the term “salt,” has been a vital commodity in human societies since the beginning of recorded history. It exists in solution in the world’s oceans or in great deposits underground where oceans have dried and been subsumed under layers of rock. In this form, it was first mined and utilized to season and preserve food. Salt was crucial enough that it was used as a form of currency across North Africa (indeed, the term “salary” comes from the word for “salt”), and taxes on salt were vital for raising income for colonial regimes – and for instilling bitterness in those subject to them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_WOOL -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_WOOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Sheep were some of the first animals to be domesticated. Indeed, sheep and their close relatives (goats) appear in tension with the very earliest settlements. Grain agriculture lent itself to urban life – a large population of people, tied to land and relatively sedentary, working very hard for part of the year and less so the rest. Pastoralism, the nomadic cultivation of animals, operated in tandem. Grain-growing societies existed in a kind of nervous peace with herding neighbors, trading in good times…and raiding in bad ones.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_WOOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Wool is different from hair in how it crimps, allowing it to be woven into garments. The earliest wool clothing was produced in the Near East at the end of the Neolithic, hand in hand with metalworking – metal helps a great deal with shearing sheep. Sheep spread across Europe, the Middle East, and North Africa, and were especially prized in cold climates, where clothing was vital to life in the winter, and not just something that made parties less awkward. Europeans especially, lacking cotton and silk (at least at that time), made wool a regional focus, and eventually areas such as Liverpool became synonymous with the wool trade.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Exploration Age Resources -->
		<!-- Luxury Resources-->
		<!-- RESOURCE_COCOA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COCOA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The cacao tree is a New World plant. It was first cultivated in South America, but Mesoamerica adopted it nearly four thousand years ago. Bitter chocolate, without sugar or milk, and flavored with spices and vanilla, was made into a hot drink by nearly all the cultures of that region, from the Olmecs to the Aztecs. Europeans were quick to seize upon that trend. Like all luxury goods of the exploration age, cocoa was quickly exported through trade routes across the empires, especially to Africa, where the majority of the world’s cocoa is produced. Cocoa production can be brutal, with accusations of modern-day child slavery continuing to be addressed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_FURS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_FURS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Humans have few advantages over most animals; we have no claws, our teeth are weak and blunt, and we totter about on two legs when four are steadier and faster. Furthermore, our skins offer poor protection from the elements. So it seems only natural that early humans took the skins of cold-weather animals for their own – especially from creatures that live in extreme cold, or who need thick, waterproof fur (otters, beavers, and the like). Fur provides a dense layer of protection and softness against the climate. On the other hand, some humans merely desire the natural beauty of tiger or leopard pelts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_FURS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While furs have always been used for clothing, the population explosions of the early modern period triggered a vast demand for these products. The term for “money” in northern languages (such as the Finnish and Estonian term “raha”) literally means “fur.” In the New World, the Haudenosaunee fought bitter wars against their potential competitors to corner the (beaver) fur market as the Europeans began to expand. But as wild places diminish, furs become increasingly inaccessible and fur extraction becomes increasingly unsustainable – not to mention a sense of disgust at the often cruel methods used to trap and kill fur-bearing animals, which seem especially atrocious as synthetic materials provide cruelty-free ways of making warm clothes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_SPICES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_SPICES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Spice” is a broad category, referring to anything (beyond salt) added to food to improve its flavor. Pepper, chili, cinnamon, and nutmeg are examples of plant substances that can be dried, crushed or ground into powder, and transported across long distances. Spices were particularly conducive to trade, as they remain effective in small quantities, and were a way for people to show off their global connections with just a pinch of flavor. They are linked with trade in the Indian Ocean; Indian and Indonesian merchants managed the majority of the spice trade in ancient times. But these vast networks spread across the globe, and many ingredients we think of as staples of one cuisine have roots in another – chili, for instance, is thought to be synonymous with Thai food, but its origins are in Bolivia, and it came to Southeast Asia with Portuguese merchants.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_SUGAR -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_SUGAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Sugar” refers to a variety of polysaccharides that come from a variety of sources: beets, fruits, etc. Most commonly, it refers to sugarcane, a tall plant native to Southeast Asia and New Guinea. This cane was key to the spread of sugar around the globe, with world-altering (and devastating) power. Sugarcane had long been used as food for pigs or pressed to make juice by cultivators in India and Southeast Asia, but it was difficult to transport and unwieldy. Christopher Columbus had the idea of transplanting cane to the Caribbean, where it began its long history of mass cultivation; for most of its history, this cultivation involved enslaved (or near-enslaved) labor, conducted by people at the harshest level. Sugar fueled the adoption of other luxury goods, such as coffee and tea, and shaped the tastes of empires in far-off Europe – what are Victorian-era cakes or an English “cuppa” without sugar? Its rise to common use, and the exploited labor that enabled it, altered European tastes for sweets, rendering “dessert” an essential part of British meals. It also altered the class structure of the Caribbean, setting the stage for events such as the Haitian Revolution.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_TEA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TEA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before tea was the signature drink of the British Empire, it was a staple of East Asian leisure for thousands of years. It likely originated in northern Burma or southern China. In these regions, tea leaves are still used in salads (in Burma) or are salted and fermented as a kind of chewed stimulant (in Northern Thailand). But the stimulating drink made by boiling the leaves has become the iconic version of the plant. In India, where the British used their colonial occupation to mass-cultivate leaves, tea is often boiled in milk to make a rich, warming drink. In Japan, concentrated and powdered tea is whipped into strong and frothy matcha, and in Russia, it is often mixed with a spoonful of fruit preserves. Interestingly, one can trace the origin of tea through language – tea brought to market by ship is called “tea” in France, England, or Indonesia, whereas tea brought overland by Silk Road caravans was often called something closer to “chai,” and tea that did not have to be transported, such as in Burma or Northern Thailand, is referred to using words unrelated to Chinese (e.g. laphet in Burmese, or miang in Northern Thai).</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_TRUFFLES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TRUFFLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As agriculture spread, so did a divide in which foods were considered common and which were luxuries. The latter might include imported goods, select parts of meat, or those remaining animals, plants, and fungi that had eluded domestication. Such is the case with the subterranean fungus, the truffle. A component of European food since the Roman era, truffles are hunted carefully with a specially trained pig. These uncommon fungi are used now as an element of fine cooking, and their rarity is only compounded as wild spaces and artisanal knowledge shrink.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- Strategic Resources-->
		<!-- RESOURCE_WHALES -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_WHALES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The largest animals ever to exist, whales are a constant source of wonder...and meat and oil. Whaling may seem daunting, but whale hunting, especially in the Pacific, has been traditionally practiced via small boats by determined hunters armed with harpoons. Early evidence for whaling has been seen in Korea, and whaling societies developed across Indonesia, indigenous North America, and Oceania. In the industrial age, whaling became a vast industry as fleets of ships, mostly from Europe, exploited the great beasts' oil for heat and lighting, using other whale parts for clothing and food. Not only did whaling become fuel for industrial and urban expansion in colonial centers, but it was also a vehicle for further colonial expansion – many island communities were targets for whaling depots as much as they were strategic military sites. Over time, overhunting and the growth of petroleum destroyed whaling’s viability. Today, whaling is practiced by Iceland, Norway, Japan, and indigenous communities across the Pacific.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_NITER -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_NITER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Niter, or saltpeter, is potassium nitrate, a widely abundant salt found in caves, especially in arid places. Its nitrogen content makes it valuable as fertilizer. But it has another popular use: when mixed with sulfur and charcoal, it makes gunpowder. Song Dynasty China (960-1279 CE) was the first place to make use of black powder, constructing powerful bombs, fire arrows, and incendiary devices (as well as fireworks). The process soon caught on and spread elsewhere. By the late 1200s, early cannons were being used against (and later by) the Mongols in the Middle East. By the 1300s, the Turks were experimenting with “fire-lances”: guns. The rest is history; as Mao Zedong wrote, political power comes from the barrel of a gun.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Modern Age Resources-->
		<!-- Luxury Resources-->
		<!-- RESOURCE_COFFEE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COFFEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Coffee is native to the northern part of the Rift Valley, in present-day Ethiopia. It remained a local curiosity until its discovery by Arab merchants during the Middle Ages, when it was exported to Yemen; it got its present-day name from Arabic (via Turkish). To this day, “Turkish” coffee – ground into a fine powder – remains a hallmark of the country, and like tea in East Asia, coffee’s stimulating properties were used by religious mystics to increase concentration during long periods of repetitive action. Others found it stimulating as well – coffee was introduced to Europe during the Ottoman Empire’s expansion. While the British grew tea in bulk in their Indian lands, the Dutch focused on coffee cultivation in Indonesia, and the Spanish in Colombia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COFFEE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Coffee houses, in Europe and its colonies, became sites of conversation and academic debate, earning the name “penny universities” for their mass-marketed lectures and semi-academic environments – even providing an alternative to beer (Friedrich the Great famously derided coffee salons as degenerate, and lauded beer as the only beverage of choice for his men). Over time, coffee and capitalism went hand-in-hand – it only made sense that a beverage allowing people to work harder and longer would be made readily available for employees at offices, or game studios.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_TOBACCO -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TOBACCO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Sid Meier does not want you to smoke. But tobacco was once an influential commodity, currency, and medicine that spanned the world. Originally domesticated in North America, tobacco found various uses as it began to travel. For the Aztecs, it was a ritual incense, and played a role in the religious connections with the divine; the snake goddess and guardian of fallen warriors, Cihuacoahuatl, had a body made of the herb. Tobacco was an early international export, making inroads into a number of societies. In the Middle East, hookahs helped cut the harshness of smoke, and the pipe was ubiquitous in Europe at various levels of society.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TOBACCO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>It was not until the late 20th century that the dangers of tobacco were made clear, and its use has dropped precipitously in many places.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- Strategic Resources-->
		<!-- RESOURCE_CITRUS -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_CITRUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Citrus fruits, such as oranges and lemons as well as the less familiar (but no less delicious) yuzu and pomelo, are a variety of fruit native to Southeast Asia. Quickly adopted as an early cultivar, citrus fruits expanded in human hands to East Asia and westward along trade routes through Islamic lands to the Mediterranean in the 900s and to Europe in the 1400s, where they were freely cultivated in the warmer regions of the continent. Beyond being a popular food, citrus fruits were discovered to be a necessary staple for sea travel. Vitamin C deficiency – scurvy – plagued many in the premodern world but was especially rampant among sailors. Subsisting on a diet of salted meat over long voyages, sailors lacked the vitamin C intake they normally received from a more varied, land-based diet (e.g. eating animal organs, green plants, etc.). Citrus fruits (especially limes) are an excellent source of the nutrient, and proved to be a quick fix for the disease, preventing the worst of the losses from scurvy, which could wipe out a sizeable percentage of any long-distance crew.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_COAL -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Coal is the result of plant matter from hundreds of millions of years ago that was compressed into peat and then buried deep in the earth. Once excavated, this compressed carbon burns hot and relatively long, making it useful for smelting. Because it was difficult to find (compared to wood), coal did not become a fuel of choice for many until the Industrial Revolution, when forests had fallen across England and populations were more concentrated. Coal fueled the “dark Satanic mills” of Blake’s imagination – the halls of English industry. It drove the steam engines that ran factory equipment, heated the homes of those who maintained those machines, and powered the railroads that took their products to market. And coal smoke blotted out the skies, producing the pollution euphemistically termed “London fog." Coal, the most polluting fossil fuel, is still a popular power source in many parts of the world, and continues to leave an imprint on our atmosphere.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_OIL -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_OIL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Millions (and millions) of years ago, plankton died, sank to the ocean floor, and were buried under mud. As these deposits of organic matter descended deeper underground, they were subjected to intense heat and pressure, turning the bodies of these tiny creatures into a carbon slurry: petroleum. Oil – bitumen, pitch, tar (the latter two denoting wood-based resin as well as fossil fuel) – was occasionally used in ancient times as a waterproofer, road surfacing agent, medicine, or source of heat and light. Only through the development of refining technology, and the rise of the industrial age, did oil become the lifeblood of the great epoch of consumption and intensification. Its lubricating properties help machines run smoothly and for a long time. When burned – in a massive power station, an internal combustion engine, or a lamp – oil and its by-products (gasoline, kerosene, etc.) provide a ready source of power, one we have become reliant upon. Control over oil has been vital in nearly all 20th-century conflicts, from World War II (where resource-starved Japan sought to expand into oil-rich parts of Asia) to the Gulf War (where Iraq and the United States fought over Kuwaiti oil reserves). The consumption of oil has constructed our modern world and – with the carbon released into the atmosphere – heralded its end.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_QUININE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_QUININE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Medicines are largely products of plants and fungi. For instance, aspirin is made from willow bark, penicillin is produced from mold – and the malaria-combatting quinine comes from the bark of the chinchona tree. Chinchona is native to the Andes, and was widely used as a treatment for muscle aches and fevers there. Malaria was one of the diseases brought by Europeans during the colonization of the New World as it had been endemic to the Mediterranean for years. Surprisingly the New World plant had a profound effect in stopping the Old World disease – something it only took the Spanish two hundred years to discover (indigenous people, who knew quinine was effective to treat fevers, were likely using it early on). Upon its identification by Western science, quinine was mass-produced and used in tonic water drinks as a preventative for malaria and a treatment for advanced cases. Today, malaria has more effective treatments (and more resistant pathogens), but the drug remains an early weapon in the ongoing battle between humans and pathogens.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- RESOURCE_RUBBER -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_RUBBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rubber is indigenous to the New World, where it was used to make the balls for the famous Mesoamerican ball game. It was not until the 1700s that rubber joined sugar, coffee, and tea as one of the crops to be collected and intensified for colonial industrial production. It is worth noting that London’s Kew Gardens and Singapore’s Botanic Gardens are separated in their construction by just a few years – trial crops (especially, in this case, rubber) were often sent to colonial outposts to see how they might fare in different environments. As a result, rubber plantations in colonies acquired a dark reputation, especially in the Belgian Congo, as sites of horrific violence against workers by colonial administrations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_RUBBER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Rubber became vital for use in automotive parts, footwear, flooring, and a thousand other applications that demand water-resistant, flexible materials.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Add-on Resources-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_MANGOS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Environmental anthropologists refer to species who have symbiotically adapted to a now-extinct ecosystem as ‘ghosts.’ So it is with wild mangoes – their heavy seeds are adapted to be eaten and passed on by large animals: rhinoceroses, elephants, hornbills, and the like, most of which are now vanished from much of the areas of South and Southeast Asia from where mango trees originate. But since ancient times, people, too, have been a key way that mangoes spread. In these regions, mangoes form a part of local diets: unripened mango chips dipped in spicy paste, chopped into rojak, or mashed with garlic and chili; or the ripened sweet orange fruit eaten with sweetened sticky rice, refined down into chunda, or eaten on its own.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_CLAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In clay, the human hand plays at creation, forming shapes for utility or artistry alike, made permanent in fire. Clay bricks make sturdy buildings where stone is scarce, and clay pots allow for cooking, brewing, fermentation, and, importantly, the transportation of water. Because of the changes that it signified in ways of life, pottery is one of the key signifiers of the Neolithic age (though, in places, it predates the Neolithic) and pottery production begins thousands of years ago: over 20,000 in Europe, nearly that in China, and approaching 10,000 years of age in Mesoamerica, the Middle East, Africa, and Southeast Asia. The quality of clay and the ability to intensify heat all have an impact upon the pottery produced, from low-heat and porous earthenware to mid- and high-heat stoneware (achieved early in China and only until the later Middle Ages in Europe), and delicate, glasslike porcelain. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_FLAX_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The long, supple and strong fibers from the flax or linseed plant have been used to make clothing since the Paleolithic. In antiquity, the crop was grown from the Mediterranean to India, and refined into a light, strong cloth – linen, and its seeds crushed to produce linseed oil. As such, it was one of the first crops to be intensively domesticated (in Mesopotamia), and it was the flax plant’s fibers that wrapped Egyptian mummies and its oil that anointed them. Roman soldiers mixed linseed oil into their food, and Charlemagne decreed that his subjects should consume it for their health. The linen trade was present in ancient Greece, and intensified in the early modern period, especially in western Europe. It remains a popular material today, especially in summer.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_RUBIES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>As the demon Vala fell to the Hindu gods, his blood collected, hardened, and turned into rubies. So the legend goes, and rubies were in ancient Sanskrit texts called ratanaraj, the king of gemstones, valued beyond diamonds for their color. The Siamese considered them one of the sacred “nine gems” of rule, and Burmese warriors might place a ruby in their own body to achieve invincibility. Surely, thinking of them as simply hardened aluminum oxide is less romantic. Today, they are mined in East Africa and especially in Southeast Asia, principally Myanmar, and they remain one of the hardest and most prized gemstones. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_RICE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rice is by far the most important cereal crop in the world. It was first domesticated in China, around 10,000 years ago, in areas that were at that time home to Hmong and Austronesian populations. “Wet” rice cultivation, practiced for thousands of years, has an unusual method of cultivation, requiring first growing seedlings in a dry field, and then transplanting them in a flooded one, often by hand. Rice cultivation made its mark on ritual culture as well, with emperors scattering the first seeds, plowing the first furrow, or investing in the great hydroengineering projects such as Angkor’s baray or Balinese water temples. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_LIMESTONE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>On the beds of prehistoric seas, the calcium carbonate shells of mollusks and corals fell, were ground to powder, and compressed over millions of years. This process forms limestone, a sedimentary rock that has been important for construction since antiquity. Because of the ease in which limestone can be cut, and its impressive white luster, limestone was used in construction of ancient buildings such as the Great Pyramid of Egypt, or when burned and made into plaster, the wonders of the Maya world. Subjected to intense heat and pressure, limestone will eventually produce yet another important and wonderous stone – marble. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>We may think of tin – a brittle, bright elemental metal – as a relatively flimsy material, but when combined with copper, tin produces bronze, one of the most important metals of the ancient world. Ancient smelters may have discovered tin alloys by accident when making copper tools, but once they understood that adding tin oxide into the mix could make harder, sharper, more durable tools and weapons, the Bronze Age had begun. But relying upon two different sources runs a risk should one of these fall to an enemy, and securing sources of tin was a vital part of ancient realpolitik.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_LLAMAS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The New World differed perhaps the most from the Old in having few beasts of burden – there were no horses, camels or elephants to carry loads from one city to the next. But in the Andes, there were llamas, and they were well-suited to traversing the high paths. Long before the Inca Empire rose, Andean peoples used llamas (and their cousins, the alpacas) for wool, fertilizer, meat, and, of course, transportation. These appear to have been extremely important for the consolidation and growth of empire in the region but also limiting – where llamas did not do well (in the jungle lowlands, for instance), empire also did not expand. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_HARDWOOD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In tropical forests, the sheer abundance of life allows a variety of strategies. Some plants grow quickly, fruit, and die. Others take their time – the hardwoods. Teak (from Southeast Asia), mahogany (from the Americas), and ebony (from Africa) are three examples of tropical hardwoods, and have been used since antiquity not only for their luster, but also because the fine-grained wood resists encroachment by fungi or insects, meaning that one can build a structure even in the most humid climate, and have it last. Palaces in the Southeast Asian highlands were often made of teak, and indigenous canoes in the Caribbean of mahogany. In the age of colonialism, though, these resources became sources of great desire and wealth – and fell under threat, with many protected now by law.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_WILD_GAME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “hunter-gatherer” is most often associated with small-scale societies, but hunting was, at times, productive enough to support cities: many New World cities, for instance, relied upon hunting for meat, and even where domestication of animals was underway, hunting remained an important source of protein and resources. Game could vary – antelopes (e.g. deer, moose, gazelles) are important nearly everywhere, but also wild cattle, birds (such as pheasants and turkeys), rabbits, and the like are hunted. As agriculture became more and more prevalent, these sources of food turned from a staple of the diet to a delicacy. </Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- 1.3.0 Resources -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_CRABS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The popularity of crabs is not only due to their delicate and delicious flesh. Crabs have a body structure that results in its unique sideways walk (also called a “crabwise” walk), and behaviors that seem individual and emotional to a human observer. Male crabs participate in mating behaviors that involve waving limbs in what appear to be a dance, while their protruded eyes seem to make humorous expressions. In truth, we know little of crabs' internal lives, though they have recently been categorized as sentient by the United Kingdom and are believed to be capable of feeling pain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_CRABS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Crabs are found throughout the world in both the oceans and freshwater, and some species are also specific to land primarily in the tropics. There are hundreds of species of crabs, varying in size from a few millimeters up to four meters. They have long been a part of the diet of peoples around the world, being prepared whole, pulverized into bisque, or served only as legs. Shells of a variety of crab have been used as fertilizer due to the presence of chitin, a compound that stimulates beneficial microorganisms in soil.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_CRABS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In popular culture, the crab is commonly associated with the astrological sign of Cancer, the Latin word for crab, one of the twelve signs of the zodiac. So named in the second century CE, it is one of the faintest constellations, its four primary stars vaguely forming the shape of a crab's pincer. In Greek mythology, the crab features in the myth of Heracles. When the hero was fighting the Hydra, a crab came to her defense and bit Heracles on the foot. The unfortunate creature died when Heracles stomped on it in revenge, so Hera placed the crab among the stars to honor its sacrifice.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COWRIE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The cowrie is a ubiquitous sea snail found throughout the Indian Ocean and the tropical regions of the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans. Their shells are oval-shaped and have a vertical opening on one side lined with what look like teeth. They tend to be shiny, looking as if already polished, and range in size from 5 mm all the way up to 19 cm for the largest. Cowries come in a variety of colors and patterns, and scientists have enumerated hundreds of different species.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COWRIE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Currency has been the primary human use of cowries throughout history. They were used for thousands of years by Africans, Indians, and the Chinese, with evidence stretching back to the Bronze Age in Egypt. In the 16th century and following, Europeans used cowries to enter African markets and proliferate the slave trade. The uniform shape and weight of a cowrie shell combined with its resistance to forgery as a natural object helped cement its importance in trade until the 20th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_COWRIE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Other uses of cowries include as jewelry, in divination, and in games. Indians have used them as a kind of dice for a variety of board games, tossing a handful of cowries and counting those that land aperture up. In the Yoruba religion of West Africa and other related practices, cowries are an important spiritual symbol, playing a role as talismans and in divination. The seer will pose questions to the spirits or Orishas, and then cast a set of cowries, typically 16, reading the pattern in the way they fall. Cowries have represented fertility, wealth, and health throughout their history, and still today, they feature in fashion and art, particularly that of the African diaspora.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TURTLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Sea turtles are a group of seven species of reptiles found throughout the world's oceans, six of them in danger of extinction. They tend to have a more elongated body than land-based turtles. Though this limits their ability to retract head and limbs into their shells, it serves to reduce friction in the water and makes them swift swimmers. Despite being aquatic animals, sea turtles must surface occasionally to breathe. While active, they are able to stay up to 40 minutes underwater without surfacing; while sleeping, they can remain underwater for up to seven hours.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TURTLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Ancient Chinese texts from as far back as the fifth century BCE mention sea turtles as a delicacy for dining, while the Greeks and Romans used sea turtle shells for various implements and jewelry. Still today, sea turtles are a source of protein for many communities while their shells and skin are used for jewelry and apparel. This desire for sea turtles has led to a crisis for many species, and the creatures are now illegal to hunt in many countries. The tourism industry has worked to address its own role in sea turtle hunting by transitioning from selling meat and shells to encouraging tourist visits to observe turtles in their natural habitat, building awareness and generating revenue for conservation efforts.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_TURTLES_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Sea turtles play a key role in the ocean's ecosystem, grazing on sea grass and thus allowing it to supply a healthy habitat for numerous other marine animals. Their nesting areas on beaches and dunes help sustain the vegetation, ensuring their own future and that of other native wildlife. Sea turtles are known to migrate sometimes thousands of miles to reach their breeding sites. Once the eggs are laid, they incubate for up to two months, their eventual sex determined by the temperature in which they develop: cooler temperatures leading to male turtles and warmer leading to females. Adult turtles can live up to 80 years, revisiting their breeding grounds every few years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_PITCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Pitch is a versatile, naturally-occurring substance that has been used in shipbuilding since at least 2500 BCE. Across the Mediterranean, shipbuilders would fasten together wooden planks with dowel and then fill the seams with pitch to caulk them against any leakage. The Egyptians and Phoenicians were early users of this technique, but we see evidence of similar use beyond the Mediterranean as early as the first millennium BCE. Austronesians and China had a vast maritime trade network across Oceania, South Asia, and the Middle East during this period and into the first millennium CE made possible by the shipbuilding innovations of pitch. In the colonial period, pitch was one of the most valuable exports from the forested areas of North America.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_RESOURCE_PITCH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the natural world, pitch is most often found as deposits of tar; a famous example is the Pitch Lake in Trinidad, covering over 100 acres and reaching a depth of 250 feet. Pitch also results as a byproduct from coal production and can be farmed and harvested from plants or trees. Aside from its use in shipbuilding, pitch was used by the Byzantines to make resin for waterproofing their ceramics. Throughout the Middle Ages, it was used as an adhesive to bind together blades and their handles along with many other tools and weapons. Today, pitch is used primarily in construction as a binder for roofing and pavement materials.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>