<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_1_TITLE">
			<Text>Ages and Age Transition</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Ages and Age Transition are new to Civilization VII and represent large segments of human history, culture, and conflict. A full game in Civilization VII spans multiple Ages, as players play from one Age to the next. A game ends when any player wins a Victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each Age has a set of challenges and rewards called Legacy Paths. Players can complete Milestones on a Legacy path to unlock powerful bonuses that can carry into the next Age (called Legacies). Players can also unlock additional playable Civilizations for the next age depending what they do in the current age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>When an Age ends, all players transition to the next age at the same time. An Age ends when the Age Progress Meter is filled. Age Progress is added slowly every turn but also advances more quickly when a player accomplishes a Milestone for the first time, researches a Future Tech or Civic, or when a player is eliminated. Once the meter is at 95% (on Standard Speed), Age Progress cannot be added through normal means and a 10 turn countdown will begin. Each turn will add 1 Age Progress until the meter is full and the Age ends.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>During Age transition, Players choose a new Civilization to play as and gain powerful bonuses from any Legacies unlocked in the previous Age. Players gain more Legacy points to spend on Legacies as well as unique Legacies by completing all Milestones on a Legacy Path. During this time, Mementos can also be changed. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_1_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>If an Age is not the last Age of a Campaign, a Crisis can trigger when the Age Progress Meter is almost full. Crises are major events that usher in the end of an Age and are not intended to be solved or stopped.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_2_TITLE">
			<Text>Carry over between Ages: Overview</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The following things carry over to the next Age after an Age Transition:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]Leaders and attribute points [LI]Legacy points (total number and type) [LI]Unlocked Traditions (i.e. the unique Social Policies specific to a Civilization)[LI]Golden Age and Dark Age Legacies from the previous age[LI]All of your units upgraded to the new age version of those units by default, or a number of units to defend your settlements (6 at the start of the Exploration Age, and 9 at the start of the Modern Age) if playing with the Regroup Age Transition Impact option [LI]Commanders, with their Promotions and level by default, and with units to fill them if you have enough units if playing with the Regroup Age Transition Impact option. Defeated Commanders will respawn.[LI]Wonders and Unique Quarters (and their Yields and bonuses)[LI]Buildings, but only with their base yields[LI]Settlements (including those that were conquered, exchanged in peace deals, or incorporated from a City-State)[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>The following things change after an Age Transition:</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_2_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>[BLIST][LI]All Players select new Civilizations[LI]All Cities revert to Towns (except Player capitals)[LI]All non-Ageless Building adjacency bonuses will be removed and they can be overbuilt. Buildings from the previous Age will lose their tags (Ex. a Library will not count as a Science Building in Exploration).[LI]New Independent Powers and City-States emerge[LI]The map is populated with new Discoveries. In Modern, they must be discovered by Explorers in order to gain Artifacts for that Age.[LI]Any uncompleted Quests are lost[/LIST]</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_39_TITLE">
			<Text>Carry over between Ages: Military</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_39_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When playing with the Regroup Age Transition Impact option, Military units partially reset at the end of each Age. Naval units are lost after Antiquity, although you gain a free Cog upon starting the Exploration Age if you have spent your Legacy Points. Keeping naval units beyond the Exploration Age requires Fleet Commanders. Land units are capped at six after the Antiquity Age and nine after the Exploration Age, plus any assigned to an Army Commander. Surplus units above those limits are disbanded, and if you have fewer than the minimum, you receive free Infantry to make up the difference.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_39_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>All units you receive after the transition are automatically upgraded to the new Age's tier 1 units. Defeated Commanders will respawn after Age transition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_39_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: When playing with the Regroup Age Transition Impact option, plan your army composition carefully before each Age transition to avoid losing valuable units or facing unexpected deficits.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_40_TITLE">
			<Text>Carry over between Ages: Others</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_40_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When an Age ends, Independent Peoples and City-States disappear, reappearing as new Independents. You retain improvements and resources but lose suzerainty benefits. Gold and Influence carry over Age Transition in limited amounts with all values scaled by game speed. With the Continuity Age Transition Impact setting, you carry over up to 3000 Gold and 400 Influence per Age (e.g. 6000 Gold after progressing into the Exploration Age from Antiquity). In contrast, the Regroup setting grants a flat carryover of 3000 Gold and 500 Influence, no matter the Age. Buildings from older Ages become less effective, losing adjacency while retaining only base yields. Only the Capital remains a City; all others revert to Towns, though you can relocate your Capital to spawn a second City immediately. Most Techs and Civics reset, as do civilian units, while old Civ abilities expire (unique buildings and improvements remain). Legacy Points not used at the Age start are lost.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_40_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>When a new Age beings, settlements conquered in the previous Age will be regarded as Founded by the player who possesses them after Age Transition.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_40_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Spend excess Gold and Influence before an Age transition so you do not waste resources that exceed the carryover limit.</Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_3_TITLE">
			<Text>Advanced Start</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Players can start a new game from any Age - not just Antiquity. Players can customize their Advanced start by selecting bonuses from different Legacies. These bonuses range from additional settlements, automatically completed Techs/Civics, or a free army. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Players also start the Age with the Social policies of a Civilization of the previous age. This Civilization will be one of the recommended Civilizations of a Player’s chosen Leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_3_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>For example, a Player who starts in the Exploration age as Hatshepsut begins the Age with the Social Policies of either Aksum or Egypt (the recommended Civilizations for Hatshepsut from Antiquity).</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_4_TITLE">
			<Text>Single Age Games</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>During setup, Players can decide to play through only a single Age. This is known as a Single Age Game. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_4_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Single Age games do not have a Crisis and do not end with an Age Transition. Single Age games still have the Domination and Points Victories. If playing a Single age Game in Modern, Players can still unlock unique Victories in the Modern age by completing all of the Milestones of any Modern age Legacy Path.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_5_TITLE">
			<Text>Legacy Paths and Legacy Points</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>New to Civilization VII, Legacy Paths are challenges that offer rewards and give Players a chance to leave their mark on history. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Each Player has four Legacy Paths they may pursue during an Age: Military, Scientific, Cultural, and Economic. Players do not need to complete a Legacy Path to end an Age or achieve a Victory (though they are very helpful). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_5_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>At the start of a new Age, each Player receives a new set of Legacy Paths specific to that age.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_6_TITLE">
			<Text>Milestones</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_6_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Legacy Paths are divided into Milestones. When a Player completes a Milestone, they receive Legacy Points, Leader attribute points, or another bonus. Each Legacy Path contains one Golden Age Legacy and one Dark Age Legacy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_7_TITLE">
			<Text>Golden Age and Dark Age Legacies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>When a Player completes the final Milestone of a Legacy Path, they unlock a Golden Age Legacy. Golden Age Legacies allow Players to keep more of their Civilization intact after an Age transition. For example, some Golden Age Legacies allow a player to keep a specific type of Building into the next Age with its Yields and bonuses. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>In contrast, Dark Age Legacies are unlocked by default. If a Player choses a Dark Age Legacy, they will receive powerful bonuses in the next age at the cost of also applying negative effects. For example, a Dark Age Legacy may make it easier to research specific Techs, but at the cost of increasing how long it takes to produce a specific Unit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_7_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Players can only activate one Golden Age or Dark Age Legacy at the start of a new Age (even if they have unlocked more than one).</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_8_TITLE">
			<Text>Legacy Points</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Legacy Points are awarded after the completion of Milestones. Players spend Legacy points to purchase Legacies after an Age Transition. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>In games where none of the Players achieve a Victory, the Player with the most Legacy Points at the end of the Modern Age (or the current Age if playing a Single Age game) wins the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_8_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Legacy points also apply bonuses to their corresponding unique Victories in the Modern age, making these unique Victories easier to accomplish.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_9_TITLE">
			<Text>Legacies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Legacies are bonuses that players can purchase at the start of a new Age. The bonuses provided by Legacies include lump sums of Gold, completed Techs/Civics, full armies, or new unit abilities. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Players purchase Legacies using the matching Legacy Point (Military, Cultural, Scientific, Economic, or Wildcard). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_9_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Players can also unlock additional Legacies by completing Milestones on Legacy Paths. Completing all of the Milestones in a Legacy Path will unlock a very powerful Golden Age Legacy to use in the next Age. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_10_TITLE">
			<Text>Victories</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_10_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Civilization VII, Players can achieve victory in different ways. When any player achieves a Victory, the game immediately ends.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_11_TITLE">
			<Text>Domination Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To win a Domination victory, a Player must capture all Settlements that belong to other Civilizations. This does not include Settlements owned by Independent Powers or City-States.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_11_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A Domination Victory is possible at any time during the Exploration and Modern Ages. In the Antiquity Age, a Domination Victory is only possible when playing a Single Age Game. (This is because players cannot cross the ocean to claim the settlements of Civilizations in the Distant Lands continent during Antiquity).</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_12_TITLE">
			<Text>Unique Legacy Path Victories</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Unique victories are also unlocked by completing the last Milestone of any Legacy Path in the final age. The first Player to complete any of these unique Victories immediately wins the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_12_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Matching Legacy points earned from previous ages make these victories easier to achieve.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_13_TITLE">
			<Text>Points Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_13_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>If none of the other Victories are achieved by the end of the final Age, the Player with the most Legacy Points wins.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_14_TITLE">
			<Text>Crisis</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>New to Civilization VII, Crises are negative events and effects that force Players to make difficult choices towards the end of an Age. These emergencies cannot be solved or stopped – they can only be managed until the Age ends.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Crises push Players to deal with escalating negative events, ranging from hostile invaders, spreading plagues, or open rebellion from settlements. During a Crisis, Players must slot Crisis Social Policies. These policies reflect how your civilization is choosing to manage the Crisis and often have negative effects that will last until the end of this Age.	</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_14_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>A Crisis can only occur in an Age that ends in an Age transition. A Crisis cannot occur in a final Age (or during a Single Age game).  Crises can also unlock unique Legacies that reflect how the Crisis has left an enduring impact on your Civilization.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_15_TITLE">
			<Text>Invasion (Antiquity)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_15_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>During an Invasion Crisis, unsettled and migratory peoples become increasingly powerful and threaten to destroy the major civilizations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_15_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>New Hostile Independent encampments spawn which cannot be converted to City-States. Encampments spawn combat units which will raid nearby civilizations until dispersed but will respawn a few turns later in a new location as the highly mobile unsettled peoples are difficult to truly defeat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_15_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Invasion Crisis policies affect how Players engage with Independent Powers, both militarily, diplomatically and economically.	</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_16_TITLE">
			<Text>Revolution (Exploration)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_16_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In a Revolution Crisis, new ideas, technologies and the rise of the middle class destabilize and eventually overthrow the existing governments.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_16_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Successive stages of the Revolution Crisis force Players to choose from mounting negative effects associated with their current Government. Eventually, these governments will be overthrown and the player will choose a new Revolutionary Government with their own unique bonuses and drawbacks.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_17_TITLE">
			<Text>Plagues</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_17_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>Plagues are a special type of disaster associated with Crises.  Plagues can be Major Outbreaks or Minor Outbreaks.  Major Outbreaks spread and cause Minor Outbreaks in Connected settlements.  Outbreaks are more likely to occur in settlements that are densely populated, highly connected to trade routes or under siege.  Outbreaks pillage Buildings and Improvements in a settlement but also sometimes give additional science or culture to an affected tile.  Units on an infected tile take damage every turn.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_18_TITLE">
			<Text>Plague (Antiquity)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_18_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Antiquity plagues are less likely to spread but there is little that civilizations can do to avoid them. Antiquity plague Crisis policies have ways to mitigate some of the effects of plagues while suffering major economic or military downsides.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_19_TITLE">
			<Text>Plague (Exploration)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_19_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Exploration plagues are more likely to spread across whole Continents.  Exploration plague Crisis policies allow players to mitigate and eventually prevent Major Outbreaks as Civilizations eventually learn how to adapt to the constant waves of plague.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_20_TITLE">
			<Text>Revolts (Antiquity) </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_20_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Antiquity, crisis policies are tied to a Civilization’s Government. If a settlement’s people are unhappy then they can go into Unrest or even Revolt and try to defect to another civilization.  Antiquity Revolt crisis policies put pressure on the happiness of a player’s settlements so make sure to increase your local happiness in key settlements with Resources and Buildings or Stationing Commanders to suppress Unhappiness.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_21_TITLE">
			<Text>Wars of Religion (Exploration) </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_21_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Exploration, settlement revolts are tied to Happiness and Religion.  Unhappy settlements that follow another civilization’s religion can go into Unrest or even Revolt and defect to the Founder of that Religion.  Exploration crisis policies give players a choice to pursue religious tolerance and maintain a religiously diverse Civilization or to embrace religious zeal and pursue a policy of strict religious unity. You can avoid unrest and revolts either by ensuring that all of your settlements follow your religion or by keeping any settlements that don't follow your religion happy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_22_TITLE">
			<Text>WMDs/Nuclear Weapons</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_22_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>WMDs are devastating and powerful tools that Players can use in the Modern Age. When deployed from a Bomber, Players can use them to completely destroy an enemy player’s Buildings or Units. Radioactive Fallout caused by them will continue to damage units caught in its radius.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_22_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Players must construct the Manhattan Project Wonder before they can produce individual WMDs. The Manhattan Project Wonder is unlocked by completing all Milestones of the Military Legacy Path in the Modern age or by reseaching the Nuclear Fission Technology. Players can then win the unique Military Victory in Modern by completing the Operation Ivy Project in one of their Cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_22_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>In order to use a WMD offensively, Players must build a WMD and use the WMD Strike action from any Aerodrome, Squadron Commander, or Aircraft Carrier with a Bomber based there.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_22_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Additionally, all Military Legacy points make the construction of both the Manhattan Project Wonder and WMDs easier. These Military Legacy points can be gained from completing Milestones of the Military Legacy paths from any Age (not just Modern).</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_23_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern Military Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_23_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To win a military victory, players must complete three steps. First, the Modern Military Legacy Path must be completed, which will unlock the Manhattan Project Wonder to build in a City. Once a player has built the Manhattan Project, they will be able to conduct an Operation Ivy Project in one of their Cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_23_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A player who completes the Operation Ivy Project will immediately win a military victory. Military Legacy points earned across all ages will increase Production towards building the Manhattan Project and Operation Ivy.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_24_TITLE">
			<Text>Antiquity: Wonders of the Ancient World</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_24_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Wonders of the Ancient World is an Antiquity Age legacy path that challenges players to construct 7 Wonders within their empire. Each Wonder not only provides adjacency yields but also grants unique effects, enhancing your civilization's power and influence. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_24_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Failing to make progress on this legacy path will unlock the Cultural Dark Age card at the Age Transition. This card grants your Missionaries +1 Charge and +1 Movement but imposes a -3 Happiness penalty in all Settlements after founding a Religion, doubled in Settlements that do not follow your Religion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_24_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Successfully finishing this legacy path upgrades your Amphitheaters to Golden Age Amphitheaters, allowing them to retain their base yield, adjacency bonuses, and effects in the next Age, preserving their impact and influence as your civilization advances.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_24_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Most Wonders are unlocked through Tech and Civic Masteries, with a greater selection found in the Civic tree than the Tech tree. If you’re pursuing this Legacy Path, focusing on boosting your Culture output and prioritizing Civic Masteries will help you unlock these Wonders faster.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_25_TITLE">
			<Text>Antiquity: Pax Imperatoria</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_25_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Pax Imperatoria is an Antiquity Age legacy path that requires players to build a vast empire by controlling 12 Cities or Towns. Conquered Settlements count as double, making expansion through conquest a highly effective strategy for completing this path. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_25_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Failing to reach any milestones in this legacy path unlocks the Militaristic Dark Age option for the next Age. This option grants you three fully packed cavalry armies with siege capabilities, but at a steep cost: you will lose all existing armies and all Settlements except your capital.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_25_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Successfully completing the Pax Imperatoria legacy path rewards you with the Pax Imperatoria Golden Age in the next Age, granting an Infantry unit in every settlement you conquered in the previous Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_25_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Building a strong military and focusing on conquest is the most effective way to progress along this path, as peaceful expansion may be limited by Settlement caps. Remember that even razed Settlements count toward your goal, so use razing wisely to speed up your progress.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_26_TITLE">
			<Text>Antiquity: Great Library</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_26_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Great Library is an Antiquity Age legacy path that requires displaying 10 Codices within your empire. Codices are displayed by slotting them into specific buildings; you can access the slotting menu by selecting the Great Works icon. Libraries, Academies, and the Nalanda Wonder each contain slots for Codices, and your Palace (in your Capital’s city center) includes one slot by default. To succeed on this path, you’ll need multiple Cities equipped with these constructible buildings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_26_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Most Codices are awarded through Tech Masteries, though some can also be obtained from the Civic Tree, narrative events, City-State Suzerain bonuses, or by completing the Nalanda Wonder. Certain Civilizations can also gain additional Codices through specific Great People.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_26_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Failing to reach any milestones in this path triggers the Scientific Dark Age in the next Age. This Dark Age grants a random Technology boost every 5 turns but imposes a -50% Science penalty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_26_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Completing this legacy path grants you the Great Library Golden Age in the following Age. This transforms all Academies into Golden Age Academies, allowing them to retain their base yields, adjacency bonuses, and effects in the next Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_26_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>To reach milestones on this path, focus on increasing your Science yield and constructing multiple Cities with the necessary buildings for slotting Codices.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_27_TITLE">
			<Text>Antiquity: Silk Roads</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_27_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Silk Roads is an Antiquity Age legacy path that challenges players to assign 20 resources to their Settlements. Resources are acquired by improving resource tiles on the map or by sending Merchants to foreign Settlements to establish trade routes, granting access to the resources available in those Settlements. Once resources are obtained, they must be assigned to Cities and Towns to progress along this path.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_27_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Failing to reach any milestones in this path triggers the Economic Dark Age in the next Age, giving Naval Commanders a charge to create a new Settlement for every 2 levels they earn, but doubling the cost of Settlers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_27_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Completing this legacy path unlocks the Silk Roads Golden Age in the following Age. In this Golden Age, all of your Cities from the previous Age remain Cities, preserving their development and benefits.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_27_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Focus on assigning resources to Cities rather than Towns, as Cities have more resource slots. Note that empire-wide resources (those that cannot be slotted) do not count towards this Legacy Path, so plan your resource assignments carefully.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_28_TITLE">
			<Text>Exploration: Toshakhana</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_28_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Toshakhana is an Exploration Age legacy path that challenges players to display 12 Relics within their empire. To start, research the Piety Civic, which allows you to build Temples and establish a religion. Once you have founded a religion, you can train Missionary units to convert Settlements. For Settlements already following another religion, you must convert both a Rural and an Urban tile; for Settlements without an existing religion, a single conversion is sufficient.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_28_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>By studying Reformation, you can adopt the Reliquary Belief, which generates Relics. Just like Codices in Antiquity, Relics require specific buildings, such as Temples and Wonders, to be displayed within your empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_28_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Failing to achieve any milestones in this legacy path results in a Cultural Dark Age for the next Age. In this Dark Age, Explorers gain +1 movement speed and unearth Artifacts 50% faster, but your empire suffers a -50% Influence penalty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_28_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Completing the Toshakhana path unlocks the Toshakhana Golden Age in the next Age, allowing you to retain your Religious Founder Beliefs, further enhancing your cultural and religious influence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_28_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_5">
			<Text>Tip: Most Relics are earned through the Reliquary Belief, but you can also acquire them through narrative events, becoming Suzerain of a City-State, and other special events.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_29_TITLE">
			<Text>Exploration: Treasure Fleet (Convoy)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_29_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Treasure Fleet is an Exploration Age legacy path that requires players to accumulate 30 Treasure Fleet Points by returning Treasure Convoys from Distant Lands. These lands, often only accessible by crossing Deep Ocean, hold unique Treasure resources. To progress on this path, establish a Settlement near these resources, and improve the Treasure resources. After some time, a Treasure Convoy will spawn in the Settlement, which you must then escort safely back to your Homeland to unload the treasure and earn Treasure Fleet Points. A Treasure Convoy is worth 1 point for each Treasure resource improved in the Settlement that spawned it. A more valuable Treasure Convoy also gives more Gold when unloaded in the Homelands.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_29_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Failing to reach any milestones in this path results in an Economic Dark Age for the next Age. This Dark Age provides +100% Production and Gold toward Rail Stations and Ports, adds +1 resource slot in all Settlements, but imposes a -25% Culture penalty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_29_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Completing the Treasure Fleet path unlocks the Treasure Fleet Golden Age in the next Age. In this Golden Age, all of your cities from the previous Age remain cities, and cities in Distant Lands gain an additional 2 population.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_29_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: You can intercept and steal Treasure Convoys from other civilizations, but be prepared for a potential naval confrontation.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_30_TITLE">
			<Text>Exploration: Non Sufficit Orbis</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_30_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Non Sufficit Orbis is an Exploration Age legacy path that challenges players to gain 12 points from Settlements in Distant Lands. Each Settlement in these regions contributes 1 point, with points doubled for conquered Settlements or Settlements following your religion, and quadrupled if both conditions are met. To progress in this path, focus on establishing new Settlements, converting religions, and capturing territories in Distant Lands. Strengthening your religion and military will greatly aid in advancing through this path.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_30_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Failing to reach any milestones on this path triggers the Militaristic Dark Age in the next Age. In this Dark Age, all Commanders gain 2 free levels, and new Commanders start with 2 additional levels, but all military units have a 25% increase in cost.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_30_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Completing the Non Sufficit Orbis path unlocks the Non Sufficit Orbis Golden Age in the following Age. In this Golden Age, you gain an Infantry Unit and a Ranged Unit in each of your Settlements in Distant Lands.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_30_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Unlocking Cartography will allow your Settler units to traverse Deep Ocean, while Astronomy grants access to the powerful Fleet Commander, enabling better organization of your naval forces. Sailing units across the ocean as early as possible gives you a strong start on this path.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_31_TITLE">
			<Text>Exploration: Enlightenment</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_31_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Enlightenment is an Exploration Age legacy path that challenges players to develop 5 districts outside the City Center, each producing a total of 40 yield. To achieve this, research Education to increase the number of Specialists you can assign to a single location and strategically place Specialists on high-yield, high-adjacency tiles.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_31_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Failing to make progress on this path will trigger the Scientific Dark Age in the next Age. This Dark Age unlocks Flight along with Combustion, but imposes a +50% cost on all airplanes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_31_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Completing the Enlightenment path unlocks the Enlightenment Golden Age in the following Age. In this Golden Age, all Universities become Golden Age Universities, allowing them to retain their base yields, adjacency bonuses, and effects into the next Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_31_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: To progress efficiently, specialize your Towns to send food to connected Cities, ensuring steady growth for creating Specialists. Use growth events to gain additional Specialists and maximize your yield in key districts.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_32_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern: Railroad Tycoon</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_32_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Railroad Tycoon is a Modern Age legacy path that challenges players to accumulate 500 Railroad Tycoon Points by manufacturing goods in their Factories. Points are generated each turn for every Factory Resource slotted into a Settlement with a Factory that is connected to your Rail or Port Network.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_32_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To begin advancing on this path, research Industrialization to unlock Rail Stations, then progress to Mass Production to enable Factory construction. After building Factories, place Factory Resources into their slots to start accumulating points. Completing this legacy path unlocks the opportunity to pursue a Modern Victory, positioning your civilization for ultimate success in the Modern Age.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_32_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Build a robust Rail and Port Network to connect as many Settlements with Factories as possible. This setup will maximize resource production efficiency and help you reach your Railroad Tycoon Points goal more quickly.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_33_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern: Ideology</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_33_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Ideology is a Modern Age legacy path that requires players to accumulate 20 Ideology Points by conquering Settlements for the first time. You gain 1 point before adopting an Ideology, 2 points after adopting one, and 3 points when capturing a Settlement from a civilization that follows a different Ideology. First adopters of an Ideology receive two Social Policy slots, while second adopters receive one Social Policy slot.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_33_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To pursue this path, research Political Theory, which unlocks the choice of a political Ideology. By completing its associated Civic, you can adopt one of three Ideologies: Democracy, Fascism, or Communism. The highest points are earned by capturing Settlements from civilizations with opposing Ideologies. Completing this legacy path unlocks the opportunity to pursue a Modern Victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_33_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Adopting an Ideology early and targeting civilizations with different Ideologies will accelerate your progress on this path and bring you closer to a Modern Victory.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_34_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern: Space Race</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_34_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Space Race is a Modern Age legacy path that challenges players to be the first to complete all three Space Race Projects and achieve the First Crewed Space Flight. Completing this path unlocks the opportunity to pursue a Modern Victory, symbolizing your civilization’s leadership in space exploration.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_34_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To begin, research Flight, which unlocks the first Space Race Project. Construct an Aerodrome and complete the Trans-Oceanic Flight Project. Next, research Aerodynamics to unlock the Break the Sound Barrier Project. Finally, research Rocketry, build a Launch Pad, and complete the Launch Satellite Project to advance further on this path.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_34_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Tip: Prioritize the relevant technologies and infrastructure to stay ahead in the Space Race. Securing the lead in these projects can give you a decisive advantage in the Modern Victory pursuit.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_35_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern: Geographic Society</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_35_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Geographic Society is a Modern Age legacy path that requires players to house 15 Artifacts within their empire. Completing this path unlocks the opportunity to pursue a Modern Victory, showcasing your civilization’s dedication to preserving history and culture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_35_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>To get started, study the Natural History Civic, which enables you to train an Explorer. This specialized unit can research and excavate Artifacts. Your Explorer can locate Artifact sites by conducting research at any University (available from the Exploration Age) or Museum (unlocked in the Modern Age). Through these investigations, Ruins on the continent will be revealed. After locating a site, send your Explorer to excavate the Artifact, a process that takes several turns and results in an Artifact.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_35_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_3">
			<Text>Just like the Culture Legacy paths in the previous Ages, Artifacts will need to be slotted to count towards your path progression. The slots come from your Palace, Museums, and Wonders like the “Palacio of Bellas Artes” or the “Hermitage.” </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_35_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_4">
			<Text>Tip: Artifacts can be acquired through excavating Ruins, certain Narrative Events, and by Overbuilding in your Settlements. Focus on these activities to quickly accumulate Artifacts and advance along this legacy path.</Text>
		</Row>


		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_36_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern Economic Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_36_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To win an economic victory, players must first complete the Modern Economic Legacy Path, which will grant them the Great Banker in their Capital. Once a player has gained the Great Banker, they must use its Establish World Bank Office action in the Capital Cities of each other player.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_36_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Establish World Bank Office action costs both Gold and Influence each time it is used (scaled by relationship). Economic Legacy points earned across all ages will reduce the cost of the Establish World Bank Office action. A player who establishes a World Bank Office in every Capital will immediately win an economic victory.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_37_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern Cultural Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_37_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To win a cultural victory, players must first complete the Modern Culture Legacy Path, which will unlock the World's Fair Wonder to be built in any City. A player who completes the World's Fair Wonder will immediately win a cultural victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_37_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Culture Legacy points earned across all ages will increase Production towards the World's Fair Wonder.</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_38_TITLE">
			<Text>Modern Science Victory</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_38_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>To win a science victory, players must complete two steps. First, the Modern Science Legacy Path must be completed. Secondly, a player must complete the Crewed Space Flight Project in a City with a Launch Pad.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_AGES_38_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>A player who completes the Crewed Space Flight Project will immediately win a science victory. Science Legacy points earned across all ages will increase Production towards the Crewed Space Flight Project.</Text>
		</Row>

	</EnglishText>
</Database>