<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_SILLA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Three Kingdoms of Korea were a set of culturally similar states on the peninsula in the first millennium CE. Of these, Silla was both the oldest and the most distant from Chinese influence, but each of the Three Kingdoms shared a militarized society and centralized system of government with a powerful monarch and aristocracy. In the early years of the Three Kingdoms, each power sought to balance the others through selective alliances and well-timed advances. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In this early Silla period, the system of “bone rank,” wherein all members of society had a particular position owing to their lineage, led to a hierarchical aristocracy with a king or queen at the top. While Buddhism had made inroads into the Three Kingdoms, Silla was the most traditional of the realms and kept Korean shamanic traditions at its core. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But at the edges of the map, there were always other powers. Silla allied with the Tang dynasty of China and subjugated the other two kingdoms in the seventh century CE. But Tang assistance came at a cost – the Tang sought to establish Chinese colonies throughout Korea, and Silla soon found itself fighting alongside its former rivals to expel these incursions. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Having unified the peninsula, Silla faced the task of keeping it. An early step was the reinforcement of royal absolutism, extending out from the capital, now named Seorabeol (“capital,” a word shortened in later years to “Seoul,” though the present-day city is not the same as the Silla capital). The Council of Nobles had its authority dramatically cut, and land became tied to a person’s position vis-à-vis the capital, not their family; thus maintaining one’s position involved placating the center. Branches of the family tree that had become distant from the capital found their authority – and income – whittled away, building seething resentment.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Silla society was also organized around trade, especially of silk. Trade was important in Silla, both as a political tool as well as for income. The Silk Road clearly linked Silla along with its other sites – a Byzantine hairpin could travel from Constantinople to Silla in a mere six months, and Muslim scholars and even an exiled Iranian prince lived and studied in Silla. Indeed, Islam makes its first appearance in Korea during Silla, though it was to wane afterwards. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_SILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>But there were cracks forming. The suppression of local nobles could work in a truly isolated place, but when these nobles began to grow rich on trade, they gained power that they used to challenge the central state. Riven by civil war, in the 10th century CE, Silla surrendered to the state of Goryeo. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Constructibles-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_DRAGON_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Buddhism arrived in Korea around the 4th century CE, and became a significant political tool – and point of contention – for Silla. Korean animism, focused around the worship of clan deities, had been central to the cultivation of elite power. But powerful noble families are an impediment to a centralized monarchy, which seeks the supremacy of one family over all – thus, monarchs of Silla adopted Buddhist religion, and sponsored the construction of massive temples – sachal, in Korean - within the capital.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_DRAGON_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The most significant of these was the Dragon Temple, Hwangnyonsa. This was a large nine-tiered pagoda, the largest building in East Asia at the time. From Hwangnyonsa, a new, royal-directed Buddhism was administered and promulgated throughout the kingdom. Buddhism remained contentious in Korea owing to its association with royalty, most notably being suppressed during later Joseon in favor of Confucianism and its class of scholar-administrators.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LECTURE_HALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Korean temple architecture featured independent buildings with different functions – halls for monks to eat and sleep, halls for particular images, and, of course, the lecture hall, where monks would study the sutras. While lecture halls are often not the most dramatic structures within a temple, they serve a crucial purpose. The development and study of Buddhism was a hallmark of Silla – the new religion was precariously situated between the monarchies, who embraced it as a source of international legitimacy, and the nobility, who rejected it as a threat to their ancient rights.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_PAGODA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The pagoda is the central feature of most Buddhist temples. It houses the most sacred objects that the temple possesses: relics of the Buddha or famous monks, and other treasures. The pagoda of the Dragon Temple was especially outstanding. It was a wooden structure reported to be over 250 feet tall, making it the tallest structure in East Asia and the tallest wooden structure in the world at the time. Today, only the foundation stones remain, though they, too, are formidable.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civics-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_SILLA_KOLP_UM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The “bone-rank system” of Silla, kolp’um served to place each member of Silla society into a hierarchical rank. These ranks determined who was eligible for kingship and who could hold an official title, as well as who was barred from these positions. After Silla’s expansion, the system also solidified the capital’s hold upon the provinces, as provincial residents – even those of formerly noble stock – were ineligible to participate in the Silla administration.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_SILLA_SAMGUK_SAGI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Samguk Sagi is the “History of the Three Kingdoms” of Korea, an account of the tensions between Silla, Goguryeo, and Baekje. It was compiled later, in the Goryeo era, but became a basis for much of the knowledge about this time period: lists of rulers, battles, and conquests, and a description of the bureaucratic structure of the various polities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_SILLA_SEONGGOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The bone-rank system served to concretize power in Silla, making sure that centrally-connected families in their base in the capital held sway over the rest of the country. The highest of these ranks was the seonggol, the “sacred bone,” a designation that pointed to those eligible for kingship. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_SILLA_SEONGGOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But this was a feature of early Silla. After the reign of Queen Jindeok, the seonggol system fell out of use.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_SILLA_JINGOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The level in the bone-rank system under the seonggol, the “sacred bone,” the jingol (“true bone”) denoted official positions up to but not including the kingship. Here, too, families held onto their appointed place in a hierarchy. After the end of the seonggol system, the jingol system remained, and it was from these ranks that later Silla royalty came. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_NODE_CIVIC_AQ_SILLA_JINGOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As Silla declined, those without such a rank often turned towards the new religions of Buddhism and Confucianism to rise in power, marking a shift in Korean society that would pave the way for Goryeo. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_CIVILIAN-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SANGDAEDEUNG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Silla, the office of sangdaedeung was one of the highest ranks outside of the actual monarchy, and the highest of the jingol ranks (at least until the throne was opened to jingol). This official presided over the Hwabaek Council, and passed decisions on major matters affecting the kingdom.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- UNIQUE_UNIT-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HWARANG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The hwarang – a group of aristocratic youth bound together by a code of chivalry and emphasizing poetry and art as much as combat – have become a symbol of the romance and beauty of the Silla period well into the present day. A hwarang followed the sesok o-kye, the five commandments, emphasizing Confucian and Buddhist teachings, service to king and family, courage and loyalty to friends, and the wisdom of mercy. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HWARANG_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The hwarang’s martial role diminished after the unification of Silla, and they largely disappeared from the historical record after Silla’s fall. They formally disbanded during Joseon.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
				