<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!--Watch Out Moments-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_NO_CODEX_SLOT_MESSAGE">
			<Text>Our greatest minds have produced a new Codex, but what use is wisdom that none can see? I suggest building a Library or Academy and moving the Codex there, so that all can benefit from it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_NO_CODEX_SLOT_SUMMARY">
			<Text>Nowhere to Display Codex</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_SURPLUS_GOLD_MESSAGE">
			<Text>You have over 1000 Gold in your treasury. Money exists to be spent, so it can make more money. I'd suggest purchasing a building in one of our Cities or Towns. New construction means bigger cities, happier people, and more Gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_SURPLUS_GOLD_SUMMARY">
			<Text>Overflowing Treasury</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_SETTLEMENT_LOST_MESSAGE">
			<Text>Our settlement of {1_CityName} is overrun, conquered by the forces of {2_LeaderName}. Such a loss must be repaid on the battlefield. If we strengthen our armies, we can better defend the empire. The loss of all our settlements would knock us out of the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_SETTLEMENT_LOST_SUMMARY">
			<Text>Settlement Lost</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_SETTLEMENT_RAZED_MESSAGE">
			<Text>One of our settlements has been razed to the ground, and vibrant neighborhoods have been destroyed. Our defenses must be strengthened, lest more settlements follow this fate. Should we lose them all, we will forfeit the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_SETTLEMENT_RAZED_SUMMARY">
			<Text>Settlement Razed</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_AGE_TRANSITION_COMMANDERS_MESSAGE">
			<Text>Many soldiers have pledged their lives to our empire, but we lack the Commanders to lead them. In addition to the amount of Units our Army Commanders can hold, we will only be able to maintain {1_value} Land Units at the start of the next Age, and only Infantry, Ranged and Cavalry Units. Without more Army Commanders, we will lose {2_lostunits} Land {2_lostunits: plural 1?Unit; other?Units;} when the Age ends.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_AGE_TRANSITION_COMMANDERS_SUMMARY">
			<Text>Large Army</Text>
		</Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_CODEX_NEEDS_TO_BE_SLOTTED_MESSAGE">
      <Text>One of our Codices is buried in our archive and is providing no wisdom to our scholars. We have a building available where it can be put on display. Let's move it there immediately.</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_WARNING_CODEX_NEEDS_TO_BE_SLOTTED_SUMMARY">
      <Text>Codex Needs To Be Slotted</Text>
    </Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>
