<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Antiquity Constructibles -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ANGKOR_WAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Angkor Wat – the name simply means “city of temples” – is a vast complex in present-day Cambodia. Originally constructed as a dwelling for Vishnu, the complex went through multiple religious interpretations, from Hindu to Mahayana Buddhist to Theravada Buddhist. It has remained a place of worship for Cambodians (or Khmer, the two words are synonymous) even before its “discovery” by French explorers in the 19th century. The central temple is the largest religious monument in the world, built of sandstone blocks and modeled upon the Hindu-Buddhist heavens: a central mound (Meru) in the center, surrounded by four other blocks. Interestingly, while most temple complexes face east, Angkor faces west.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ANGKOR_WAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Such sites can be thought of as antennae radiating the king's power and majesty to the surrounding countryside. As such, they became powerful symbols for would-be conquerors: Angkor was used as a symbol of French Indochina during the colonial occupation, and a model of the temple was added to the Grand Palace at Bangkok during the Siamese occupation of Cambodia. The site’s profile also appears on Cambodian flags from the Khmer Rouge to the present day.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_COLOSSEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Those who are about to die salute you!” was the rallying call of the gladiators competing in the Roman Colosseum, which remains the largest standing amphitheater in the world today. On this stage, the sport of the ancient Romans was on full display. These could be gruesome affairs, often including duels to the death or battles between wild animals such as lions (Roman gladiatorial contests have been cited as the reason lions went extinct in the Mediterranean, although a shifting climate and expanding human population might have had more to do with it). But the Colosseum was an arena for more than just deadly spectacle, hosting public addresses, executions, plays, and sea battles that required the complex’s floor to be filled with water.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_COLOSSEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Gladiatorial contests were often staged between fighters armed with different weapons from around the Empire. For instance, the Samnite fighters had a long shield and a sharp Roman soldier’s sword (the gladius), Thracians held a short dagger and shield, and the Retiarii had a net and trident. Competitors were not armed in ways that made the most sense, but for whatever made the best sport.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_COLOSSEUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Colosseum was a place where the emperor and the populace could be together at the same time. As such, it was an important site in the politics of empire, especially when the senate dwindled in influence and importance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_COLOSSUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A man of bronze stands astride the harbor at Rhodes – a depiction of the sun god Helios. More likely, he stood alongside the water as the popular depiction is impractical. Regardless, the Colossus was a marker of the might and prosperity of the Greek island. It stood over a hundred feet high, about the size of the modern-day Statue of Liberty, and was made to commemorate the defense of the city against an attack by Macedonian forces descended from Alexander the Great. The victorious defenders sold equipment abandoned by their fleeing enemies and spent this windfall on the statue. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_COLOSSUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Colossus did not stand for long. In 226 BCE, just 54 years after its construction, an earthquake toppled it. When the Rhodians heard from the Oracle at Delphi that they had offended Helios, they left it in ruins, though its massive scale continued to attract tourists. In time, the ruins were taken by conquering Arab forces in 653 CE and sold to a merchant from Syria.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_DUR_SHARRUKIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Dur-Sharrukin is not a singular wonder but the capital city of Assyria under Sargon II, built sometime before 706 BCE in the far north of what is now Iraq. It was a massive feat of engineering, constructed with limited materials and requiring the cultivation of surrounding land. The city’s three square kilometers were enclosed by walls featuring over 150 towers. Inside was a collection of opulent palaces, temples, and a ziggurat, as well as elaborate lamassu and shedu (Assyrian sacred beasts) statues. Dur-Sharrukin also held a sprawling garden composed of trees from every land that Sargon conquered. These gardens became the inspiration for Sennacherib’s gardens at Nineveh, the Hanging Gardens of Babylon, and the Persian pairidaeza.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_DUR_SHARRUKIN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Dur-Sharrukin was abandoned upon Sargon’s untimely death, and the city became a thing of myth. Slowly buried across many centuries, it now lies beneath the modern town of Khorsabad. The site was rediscovered and explored by teams of archaeologists in 1843, 1928, and 1957. Unfortunately, the group ISIS claimed responsibility for destroying the area in 2015 and looting its remains.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_EMILE_BELL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The largest bell in Korea, the Bell of King Seongdeok was cast out of bronze in 771 CE during the Silla period of Korean history. It is a temple bell that was originally installed in Bongdeoksa Temple, where its sound would call monks to prayer and ring out the time of day. A tube at the top of the bell provides a unique reverberation and famously rich sound. This sound is the source of a rather sinister legend – allegedly when the smiths first sought to make a bell for Bongdeoksa, every bell they cast would fail to produce a sound. A monk dreamed that a working bell needed a sacrifice – that a child needed to be cast into the metal. When the bell is struck today, one can easily imagine its ring calls out “emile,” meaning “mother.” This story is likely a later anti-Buddhist invention or a modern ghoulish ghost story.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_EMILE_BELL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Today, the bell stands in the National Museum of Gyeongju.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GATE_OF_ALL_NATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Imagine how Alexander the Great felt upon entering Persepolis (Parsa, in Persian), the ceremonial capital of an empire that had functioned as the main antagonist during that formative period of ancient Greek history. It was his rival’s holiest site, the heart of the empire, where its gold and silver were most concentrated, and where its learning and arts were most evident. His troops entered and sacked the city, burning everything to the ground and killing everyone they found. It has been said that Alexander regretted Parsa’s destruction, but the city remained ruined.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GATE_OF_ALL_NATIONS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>By some accounts, Parsa was not a place for permanent habitation, functioning more as a palatial and ritual complex. Regardless, it was a vast place of art and wonder. The Gate of All Nations, built by Xerxes in the 5th century BCE, was an extensive entrance supported by four pillars and decorated with bulls and lamassu (sphinxes with the heads of bearded men). The space was designed to impress, to instill insignificance in its viewers as they stared up at the face of Xerxes the Great – before facing its active ruler.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GREAT_STELE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Great Stele, or Stele One, is the tallest of the many stelae found at Aksum. Dating from the early fourth century CE, it was carved from a single piece of granite and transported from the quarry several kilometers distant. Like the other large stelae at the site, it stood over tombs of the elites and seems to have signified religious beliefs and practices that predated Christianity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GREAT_STELE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Great Stele would have been 33 meters (108 feet) high when standing and the tallest obelisk in the world, but it collapsed during or soon after its placement. Lying shattered on the ground, its four sides showcase their intricate carving. Thirteen stories of a building are engraved into the stone with rows of windows extending to the tip. The base of the monument has two false doors on the front and back, possibly representing beliefs in an afterlife.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GREAT_STELE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Funerary traditions of raising monuments to mark gravesites stem from a broader regional practice in Eastern Africa and date back as far as the third millennium BCE. Within this context, the Great Stele marks both the height of Aksum ingenuity and the importance of Aksumite religious practices before the kingdom adopted Christianity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HA_AMONGA_A_MAUI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the distant past, the hero Maui loaded three massive stones onto his outrigger and sailed to Tonga, where he installed them as his throne. No one else could have lifted them – the endeavor took the strength of a man who could raise the islands of Hawai’i from under the sea. In Tonga, these stones provided later kings a safe sitting place, from which one could see (and strike) any potential assassins should they get too close.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HA_AMONGA_A_MAUI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>According to historians, the arch was built by the Tongan king Tu’itatui in the 13th century. Tonga was an early Polynesian kingdom (and remains a Polynesian kingdom), having been inhabited for nearly 2,500 years. Like many Polynesian societies, Tonga focused on sea navigation and the cultivation of the personal power (mana) of kings, often tied to the figure of Maui. Monuments like the Ha’amonga ‘a Maui are therefore significant for their remembrance of him and their maintenance of the idea of the power of kings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HANGING_GARDENS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Following a conquest, Mesopotamian rulers would bring pieces of the conquered landscape back to their palaces to serve as symbols of power. Sargon, Sennacherib, Nebuchadnezzar, and others had gardens full of these symbols attached to their palaces, but the quintessential garden was the Hanging Gardens of Babylon. Sadly, historians know little more than the name. Does it refer to a destroyed or lost garden in that city? Was it Sennacherib’s palace? Could it have been an idealized Mesopotamian garden? The details are unclear.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_HANGING_GARDENS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At Nineveh, around 700 BCE, Sennacherib raised a massive system of waterworks to feed orchards and gardens with water screws that brought irrigation to higher terraces, which is where the “hanging” name comes from. These gardens were filled with trees such as cypress and pine, dates, pears, grapes, and other fruit. In the midst of the arid Iraqi landscape, such a garden would have been a cool, refreshing oasis – as well as a record of conquest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MAUSOLEUM_OF_THEODORIC_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the chaos of the fall of the Western Roman Empire, successor states were often ruled by “barbarian” kings – Theodoric of the Ostrogoths among them. The Goths have retained significant staying power – our modern use of “Gothic” to mean “ghoulish” stems from its use by Italians to disparage the Goths in antiquity; the term was later used to disparage medieval European architecture (gargoyles and flying buttresses, etc.), a style that frequented, and gave name to, the subsequent genre of 18th-19th century horror literature. The Mausoleum of Theodoric is an example of the architecture of the ancient Goths. The structure is a simple stone circle that housed Theodoric’s remains and included a lower level for services. It remains a sign of Italy's early Middle Ages, a period of great transition for the West.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MONKS_MOUND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the ninth century CE, a vast city was constructed in what is modern-day Illinois. Called Cahokia by later residents, it was the heart of Mississippian society and a hallmark of their power, organization, and construction. The city was laid out along the cardinal directions in carefully planned districts. Various halls, temples, and homes were built upon its many man-made mounds.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MONKS_MOUND_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At the center of Cahokia, next to the large open plaza, rose the towering Monks Mound. Constructed with soil and clay carried by foot in baskets, the structure remains the largest prehistoric earthwork in the Americas. Its base is larger than that of the largest pyramid at Giza. While the original mound was built quickly – perhaps within twenty years – it expanded over the centuries to dominate the landscape. Its four terraces guided visitors to the hall at its flat peak, a wooden structure 100 feet long and almost 50 feet wide, likely a temple or chieftain’s dwelling that would have been visible from anywhere in the city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MUNDO_PERDIDO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Mundo Perdido, the “lost world,” is the central complex at the Maya city of Tikal. Built around 300 CE as a religious and astronomical site, it consists of a tall pyramid with three associated temples and sits in the middle of (what is now) the Guatemalan rainforest. Interestingly, the complex shows influence from the non-Maya Teotihuacan site in Mexico, a testament to the multicultural nature of Mesoamerican politics.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_MUNDO_PERDIDO_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The religious significance of Maya astronomy is also noteworthy. The movements of the stars were clues to the dispositions of the gods, so astronomical sites were places of sacrifice and worship, where the gods could be seen directly and given offerings. To the Maya, for instance, the bright star in the morning sky (which we call Venus) was not a ball of sulfur dioxide clouds surrounding a scorching planet. Rather, it was the eye of Kukulkan, through which direct communication was possible from the earth to the heaven – one that required a stage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_NALANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The first residential university, the Buddhist monastery at Nalanda has stood in eastern India since at least the fifth century CE, though it traces its roots back even earlier. Fittingly, the Bihar region of India is the origin point for both the Buddha and the Buddhist emperor Ashoka – according to legend, Ashoka even laid the foundations for a monastery in the region. However, Nalanda has its origins in the Gupta Empire, which built a massive teaching institution that attracted Buddhist scholars from across the world. This included the Chinese monk Xuanzang, who traveled to India in order to bring back Buddhist records and served as the inspiration for the epic “Journey to the West.” Other pilgrims came from Korea, Java, Srivijaya (Sumatra), and Tibet, each seeking to participate in Nalanda’s thriving scholarly debates. Nalanda was also the site of various theological debates within Buddhism, from the philosophical Nagarjuna to the esoteric tantric school of Vajrayana.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_NALANDA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As on the Northumberland shore, monks and their wisdom are vulnerable to the swords of raiders. Around 1200 CE, the Persian warlord Muhammad Bakhtiyar Khalji attacked and destroyed Nalanda. According to legend, when the general finally discovered the treasures of Nalanda, he was shocked to discover they were books. He sought those who could tell him the meaning of the texts, but they had all been slaughtered. In the centuries afterward, Nalanda and Buddhism survived in some form in Bihar, but those institutions were never as significant as they had once been.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ORACLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Those with the responsibility to make potentially calamitous or fortuitous decisions often treat that responsibility carefully. An outside voice – from the gods or the future – could be a good way to think through difficult choices and weigh the consequences. In Hellenistic Greece, this voice was the Pythia – the oracle of Apollo at Delphi – who was guided by the phrases inscribed on the temple: “know thyself,” “nothing to excess,” and “surety brings ruin.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ORACLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>According to legend, the earth-goddess Gaia gave birth to a dragon named Python. Jealous of Zeus’ infidelity, Hera sent Python after the infant Apollo. However, Apollo slew Python at Gaia’s shrine and took over the place.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ORACLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The secrets of how the oracle worked are lost to time. Those seeking natural explanations might rationalize the Pythia’s ramblings through the release of local volcanic gases (and their hallucinogenic effects). However, a more likely explanation could be that it was a cultural phenomenon – trances and prophetic statements are common enough in many societies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_ORACLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Advice from Delphi was often cryptic. For instance, the Pythia told Alexander’s father Philip, “with silver spears, you may conquer the world,” seemingly foreshadowing Philip’s canny use of silver mines in subverting the Greek city-states. Before the Greek navy's defeat of the Persians, the Oracle reportedly called the winds “mighty allies of Greece.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PETRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Arabia is often associated with Islam, but Arabs had a long history in the area before the rise of the Prophet. One example is the Nabataean civilization, an Aramaic-speaking population living in present-day Jordan. Their city of Raqmu, now Petra, is a marvel of stonecutting – an entire city carved from rock that earned the epithet “city of rose.” Its most notable structure is the Al-Khazneh, the so-called treasury building, which was a mausoleum to a Nabatean king.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PETRA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Nabataeans created a city where life flourished – even in the desert. They built channels where water flowed and created a hidden oasis in the middle of desolation. Today the monument remains a symbol of Jordan and one of New Seven Wonders of the World.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PYRAMIDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Pyramids (“myr” in Egyptian) are massive tombs raised for kings so ancient that their age is mind-boggling. These structures were raised around 2560 BCE, meaning that Cleopatra lived closer to us than she did the construction of the Pyramids. Traditional Egyptian tombs (mastabas) were long, low stone structures atop a deep burial shaft. Pyramids evolved as architects stacked these shapes, making larger and taller mastabas. Later architects, such as the alleged architect of the Great Pyramid, Hemiunu, covered these stacks in a sheath of reflective limestone and placed a capstone on top. Some have claimed the capstone was composed of gold, but that is unlikely as it would have been too great a temptation for thieves.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PYRAMIDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Recent discoveries at a quarry have unveiled preserved blocks, arsenic chisels, and ropes, which offer a good picture of how the Pyramids were built – archaeologists estimate that around 13,000 to 40,000 people were needed for labor, which took around 27 years. Contrary to popular cultural depictions, the Pyramids were built by hired seasonal labor, not enslaved people (and certainly not ancient aliens or Atlanteans).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PYRAMIDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>A city formed around the Pyramids during their construction, which included a temple complex where the pharaoh-as-god was worshipped. In this sense, the whole complex is a living space – a temple site of devotion oriented towards a cult of the Egyptian gods, one that reinforced centralized authority and dedication to the Nile. The Pyramids mark off the fertile “black land” at the edge of the wastes of the desert.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PYRAMID_OF_THE_SUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before the Aztecs built their empire, another civilization flourished within modern-day Mexico. Teotihuacan served as a blueprint for the majesty of the Maya (who were contemporaries) and the Aztecs (who came much later). Teotihuacan's societal influence on art and trade was so strong that some scholars speculate that its decline, rather than environmental factors, led to the decline of the Maya. Teotihuacan civilization appears to have collapsed from within, likely due to social revolt and unrest. Still, their legacy remains.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_PYRAMID_OF_THE_SUN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Aztecs gave the great Pyramid of the Sun its name – its Teotihuacan moniker has been lost to time. The space houses elaborate carvings of jaguars and serpents. But during its heyday, around 200 CE, its highest point also contained a temple, rising nearly 250 feet above the Mexican dryland. Even in ruins, it remains impressive.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_SANCHI_STUPA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When Ashoka the Great had his moment of crisis and converted to Buddhism, he commissioned a number of building projects promoting the religion across Maurya India. Built in the third century BCE, the massive complex at Sanchi is the most impressive. A stupa is a mound of stone, allegedly containing a buried relic – the most famous contain the cremated remains of the Buddha. One can think of a stupa as a radio antenna, broadcasting the truth of the Dharma to those who listen. However, a stupa is one part of a larger temple, with houses for monks and novices, and can be understood as a place for community gatherings and education.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_SANCHI_STUPA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Sanchi is also the site of one of Ashoka’s famous pillars, where he conveyed his message to all. At Sanchi, he called for the unification of the sangha, the community of Buddhist scholars, who – along with the history of the Buddha and his teachings – form the core of the Buddhist religion. Sanchi’s impressive gate is a marker of the stories of the Jātaka, the lives of the Buddha before he was reborn as Siddhartha Gautama. Over time, Buddhism declined in Madhya Pradesh, the region where Sanchi is located, as well as in much of India, though it remains an important monument to the history of the region.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_TERRACOTTA_ARMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is a king without followers? What is the value of authority if no one is present to recognize it? And what is death but the dismantling of one's glory? The terracotta soldiers buried with their ancient Chinese leaders are a testament to the human desire to cling to some degree of command even when facing the inevitability of death.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_TERRACOTTA_ARMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Qin Shi Huang is the imperial name of the warlord of Qin, one of the states that protected the Zhou Emperor – until it didn’t. Qin Shi Huang overthrew Zhou, proving that all the ritual trappings in the world were no match for a society organized around militarism. Before his death around 210 BCE, Qin Shi Huang commissioned the assembly of an army of clay, for the conquests he would undertake in the spirit world. Nearly 10,000 in number, the soldiers were assembled with lifelike faces, armor, and weapons, including chariots, terracotta horses, and support staff. They were buried along with Qin Shi Huang.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_WEIYANG_PALACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Han China was ruled through power and prestige. The Han employed a vast administration under the autocracy of the emperor, combining the traditional authority of the Zhou Dynasty with the aggressive militarism of the Qin. This administration required a place from which to operate. When we think of a palace, we often think of luxurious residences and galleries of art, but Weiyang, in the city of Chang’an, was primarily an office building. Yet it was an impressive one. The palace is the largest ever built – at nearly five square kilometers it is vastly larger than the later Forbidden City. Weiyang Palace would have housed bureaucrats in a broad hierarchy dedicated to overseeing the administration and the state, with designated entrances for vassals (the east) and workers (the north).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_WEIYANG_PALACE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the Tang Dynasty, the palace was destroyed in an invasion and now lies in ruins. Its name means something akin to “happiness that has not yet reached its middle,” a relevant title for one of the earliest administrations in a country with such a long history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GREAT_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In this age of mass-produced literature, it can be hard to appreciate a world in which an individual book was a work of art. Mesopotamian scribes carefully pressed each letter into a clay tablet with a stylus, East Asian authors painted each character on a scroll with a brush, and South and Southeast Asian writers carved out curling letters in palm-leaf with a sharp pen. One book was a treasure; a library was a fortune. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GREAT_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The libraries of the ancient and medieval world were therefore wonders in themselves, not simply because of the ability to access the wisdom of past times, but in the sheer amount of labor that went into each book. Their names stand out: Ashurbanipal’s library of clay tablets, the House of Wisdom in Baghdad, the mahavihara at Nalanda. But it is the Great Library at Alexandria that we may think of first when we think of such collections – the archive of the Mouseion, and the jewel of the Greek-speaking world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_WONDER_GREAT_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Library housed papyrus scrolls of engineering, mathematics, epic poetry, history, and philosophy. It was constructed under the Ptolemaic kings of Egypt, and shone during the last centuries BCE. But misfortune was to haunt it – under repressive regimes, scholars were ousted, and in Julius Caesar’s attack on Egypt the library burned, and hundreds of years of knowledge went up in papyrus ash. The Great Library was not to recover, especially as religiously-fueled purges derided its knowledge as pagan heresy. By the fourth century CE, the library was empty and its scholars scattered, though similar sites of learning were to reappear wherever knowledge was sought and treasured.     </Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Antiquity Buildings -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ACADEMY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While universities are massive institutions of general study, academies are places for philosophical reflection. Confucian academies were quintessential examples – places where students of Confucianism could study and debate the classics. Expertise in classical texts was necessary to advance in the bureaucracy. In Greece, the classical academy was a school originally named for a grove of trees sacred to Athena, and scholars such as Plato and Socrates taught there. These schools emphasized debate and philosophy as well as a close relationship between teachers and students – a tradition exported to Persia under Alexander’s conquests. Academies merged naturally into larger universities in Africa (specifically Mali, Morocco, and Egypt) as interests and knowledge expanded, and as society realized it could no longer expect students to be masters of astronomy, philosophy, religion, and mathematics all at once!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ALTAR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The division between the sacred and profane refers to the split between things of this world and things of the next (in this case, “profane” refers to “earthly,” not “impolite"). An altar is the meeting point between these two worlds, where offerings or other signs of respect are given. These were often sites of immolation, where food or other earthly goods were set as burnt offerings and transformed into divine smoke and ash. Catholic altars are the sites where bread and wine become divine flesh and blood, and Buddhist altars carry burnt incense before images of the Enlightened One. Not all religions have altars. For example, mosques do not, which is unsurprising for a religion that privileges the written word over the material. Also, many animist faiths do not separate the sacred and profane, at least not in the confines of a house of worship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_AMPHITHEATER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word “amphitheater” references a semicircular or circular ring of seats surrounding a stage where performances, speeches, gladiatorial contests, poetry, and the like could be staged. The term is specific to Greek and Roman contexts, where it performed a key role in public entertainment. However, if "amphitheater" is used to reference any gathering point for performances, we find examples across several societies, from Balinese dance to Chinese village opera to the singing of Malinese griots. Stories are crafted to be shared, whether that be a politician’s speech, a mythological tale projected in shadow on a screen in a Malay market, or a story writ in bronze and blood upon gladiatorial ground.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ANCIENT_BRIDGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Travel and innovation go hand in hand. Since ancient times, the development of bridges demonstrates the wide variety of technological and stylistic advances that have transformed these structures over the centuries. The earliest bridges drew from the immediate natural world – stepping stones and fallen trees. But people also experimented with materials to create unique solutions to natural barriers. The Obersee in Switzerland bears evidence of prehistoric log pilings that supported a wooden footbridge across the lake. In Greece, the Arkadiko Bridge features stones forming a slim arch over a ditch. The Andes and the Himalayas both saw the independent development of suspension bridges made of vines, allowing navigation of steep mountain valleys. In a more creative endeavor, Herodotus tells us that Xerxes constructed a bridge out of ships to move his army across the Hellespont strait; when a storm destroyed his first attempt, he had the sea whipped and branded with hot irons out of fury.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ANCIENT_BRIDGE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Relatively few bridges from the ancient period remain intact because many were temporary or required constant upkeep that ceased over time. Rome was the first society to develop permanent bridges, allowing them to move armies quickly across the empire’s vast territory. While their wooden predecessors do not survive, Roman stone bridges are still found across Europe, their round arches and cemented blocks supporting pedestrians even today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ANCIENT_WALLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Evidence of walled cities dates back to the eighth millennium BCE when Neolithic inhabitants of Jericho constructed stone fortifications around their settlement. In the ensuing centuries, city walls developed across the globe as both a protective measure and a means of regulating trade. As architecture grew more advanced, these structures took on additional purposes – for instance, the Assyrians and Babylonians erected walls to intimidate as well as defend, boasting of their strength in dedicatory inscriptions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ANCIENT_WALLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Walls were used to both expand and defend borders. The Great Wall of China, a network of rammed earth and stone structures, is the most famous example of this process. Sprawling across mountains and deserts, it was designed to both claim new territory and protect the fertile lands of the south from northern invaders. The Persians raised walls in the Caucasus Mountains to defend their territories from nomadic tribes. And the Romans marked their northernmost provinces in Britain with the Hadrian and Antonine Walls.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ARENA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Romans loved the art of war. Gladiatorial contests included bloody duels fought between trained (and at times untrained) warriors, chariot races, and even naval battles. These events were a central feature of entertainment in the Republic and Empire. Stages developed from simple fights in an amphitheater to the massive spectacles of the Colosseum. But similar contests existed elsewhere. The Aztecs – another famous warlike society – staged battles between two opponents on raised platforms, and the Egyptians delighted in water jousting atop papyrus rafts. Here, arenas indicate places of physical contest, whether between warriors with swords or rival chunkey teams on a Mississippian ball court.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BARRACKS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term "barracks" evolved from a 17th-century Catalan word and refers to housing for a professional army. In many ancient and medieval armies, soldiers would be called to fight from their homes and had to camp as they saw fit, but professional armies featured soldiers who lived in the military. Elite units, or guards stationed in fortifications far from home, might be housed in special buildings from which they could easily muster for combat or training. Barracks also allowed commanders to keep an eye on their forces, ensuring discipline and readiness for the battles to come.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BATH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Humans are creatures of the earth and muck – at the end of each day, our bodies are covered with sweat, dirt, oil, cooking grease, or worse. Those with children understand the level of humanity's filth, intimately. But societies idealize the perfect body, one fresh and clean. As a result, baths become important as sites for ritual, recreational, or daily purification. The Great Bath at Mohenjo-Daro is one such site: a massive well-fed pool in modern-day Pakistan. We have yet to decipher this society's script, so the details are lost, but this was evidently a pool for washing human bodies (whether common or noble). Likewise, Roman baths were places for relaxation and conversation, and Japanese onsen were key destinations for a relaxing weekend, especially during industrial times. Baths required detailed knowledge of plumbing, pumping, and people skilled in evaluating different geothermal sources of water – not to mention all the materials needed to purge the human body of its dirt, physical, mental, or spiritual.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BLACKSMITH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Smithies are a fundamental part of ironworking. Early metals were gold, silver, and copper, though none of these are ideal for forging durable tools or weapons (unless one is fighting werewolves). Copper can be made into an alloy (bronze) that is hard, sharp, and corrosion-resistant. Still, bronze does not require a smithy. Smithies existed across the Old World, from West and East Africa to Europe to China – though the New World had yet to master iron at the time the Europeans arrived.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BLACKSMITH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With smelted iron (i.e. not meteoric iron), one must constantly heat and pound the metal to render it pliable, allowing it to properly harden when cooled. Iron weapons were not generally superior to bronze (at least at temperatures too low to produce steel); iron swords had to be straightened after just a few strikes in combat because they easily warped. However, iron was more economical. Efficient forges, as in Rome or Song Dynasty China, could produce iron with a greater steel content.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BLACKSMITH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In a smithy, charcoal or coal is used to power a forge, and the blacksmith heats the metal until it glows, while a striker repeatedly pounds the metal into shape. An efficient forge could produce weapons as well as tools for a variety of purposes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BLACKSMITH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Due to their necessary function in societies, smiths often had a role in mythology – consider Vulcan, or Ilmarinen, or Ogun, or the blacksmith caste of Maasai culture who gained a reputation for magic and lived under rules of enforced celibacy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BRICKYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Bricks are some of the first building materials used by cities. Early brick structures – especially in the Middle East, which feature buildings nearly ten thousand years old – were rectangles of clay mud, and sometimes straw, that were dried in the sun. The most impressive of these is Jericho, which had the oldest known protective wall in the world. However, making bricks in the sun is difficult in moist or cool climates. Instead, one needs to fire a brick to preserve it – a technique used extensively everywhere from India to Rome to China, where they form part of the tomb of Qin Shi Huang. Bricks, in this way, are essentially a crude form of pottery.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BRICKYARD_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>For most of antiquity and the Middle Ages, brickmaking involved treading over clay by foot in a muddy pit to remove impurities and make it malleable and consistent. The clay was then poured into a mold and left to dry in the sun for a summer. At the end of the season, the bricks would be stacked into a structure – a kiln – that was loaded with wood and set ablaze. At the end of several days of firing, the bricks would be ready for construction.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_FISHING_QUAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Humans have fished with hooks and harpoons since nearly the origin of our species. Fishing became essential for many early settlements along coasts and rivers. As we developed larger and more capable boats – a feature of societies from Mesopotamia to aboriginal Australia to the New World – fishermen could leave the shoreline and pursue larger catches. Such technologies necessitated centers, places where boats could dock and unload their harvests, as well as repair and store watercraft. These wharves – or “quay” (pronounced to rhyme with “key”) – allowed for the distribution of fish beyond individual consumption, provided increased productive specialization, and furthered the development of early cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GARDEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A garden can be many things: a collection of exotic plants, a place of serene relaxation, or a location to cultivate food. Indeed, it could be all of the above. The terraced gardens of Ashurbanipal, often considered the “Hanging Gardens of Babylon,” were irrigated structures built to model the lands he conquered. Ashurbanipal could "tour" his conquests by walking through these foreign landscapes. Groves of trees around Buddhist temples evoke the forest of Lumbini where the Buddha was allegedly born, and function as places of quiet contemplation. Persian gardens were masterpieces of irrigation, channeling small flows of water through cultivated, geometrically styled plots, which formed the inspiration for both Roman and Muslim gardens.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_GRANARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The origin of cereal agriculture was a key point in the development of urban life. Cereal grains such as wheat, maize, rice, and the like require a great deal of coordinated agricultural labor, intense at times and passive during others. Some scholars, like James Scott, cite the cultivation of grain as a key point for inequality, as a gateway for slavery and serfdom (though this is contested by others, such as David Graeber). When grain is harvested en masse, it needs to be stored to last until the seasons when there is no harvest. Furthermore, it needs to be protected against mice and other pests, and be kept high and dry so it does not spoil. Hence, the granary: a storehouse to keep grain safe and secure. Early granaries date back to the Neolithic, well before the scope of this game, and are found worldwide. Examples include wooden rice storage in Southeast Asia, stone structures amongst the Pueblo people of North America, ceramic structures in the Middle East, and simple pits in Egypt.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_HARBOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Dating at least as far back as 2500 BCE, harbors have been important components of the workings of empire. Within these sheltered bodies of water, ships used for trade and transport are able to moor and transfer goods safe from the winds and storms of the open sea. Though harbors are the bodies of water themselves, whether natural or manmade, the word is used synonymously with “dock” and “port,” coming to mean the general location and structures where ships dock and cargo is handled.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_HARBOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The earliest known harbor used for shipping is the Egyptian site Wadi al-Jarf, located on the Red Sea, that dates to the reign of King Khufu (c. 2585-2555 BCE though dates vary). A papyrus logbook found at the site details some of what transpired at this early dock. Limestone from the quarries at Tura was transported by boat through this harbor to eventually make its way to the pyramids at Giza. Though it is unclear what purpose this stone had, it was likely used as a layer of cladding on the outside of the pyramids. Other entries in the logbook record the transport of food and other items, the trajectories of vessels across the kingdom, and the titles of various officials working to keep goods and materials flowing.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Most understand the concept of a library – it is a collection of books. But what books? For what purpose? Who curated this collection? Who can access them? Our concept of a public library that is available to all is a modern invention. Early libraries were primarily for kings, nobles, priests, and other specialists.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In antiquity, the library of Ashurbanipal of Assyria stands out. This was a collection of tens of thousands of clay tablets, wax cylinders, papyrus scrolls, and other items collected by trade or conquest, and the space contained everything from texts on divination to religious epics (including the Epic of Gilgamesh) to legal records. These were not simply read for entertainment but for knowledge about how the world, its people, and its gods all worked.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LIBRARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The names of other famous libraries echo through the centuries: Alexandria (in Egypt), Nalanda (in India), the Wen Yuan Pavilion (in China), the House of Wisdom (in the Abbasid Caliphate), the library at Timbuktu (in Mali), and others. These structures rose and fell along with writing and knowledge – as empires fall, libraries burn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_LIGHTHOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Before the 1800s, the world was only lit by fire. Torches, rushlights, gaslights, and kerosene lanterns were how people made their way through homes, cities, and the roads between. Those used to streetlights on the road, headlights on cars, and the ambient glow of cities reflected off the clouds will struggle to imagine sailing through a sea on a moonless night, the sky lit solely by stars and the occasional flash of sea phosphorescence. Knowing one's location, especially at night, was a matter of literal life or death for sailors, so lighthouses lit by massive bonfires were one way early societies marked dangerous (or popular) places. While Alexandria likely has the most famous lighthouse of the ancient world, the Romans built beacons across Europe at places such as the Tower of Hercules in Spain, and other societies lit beacons on the shores. Surprisingly, ancient China had a limited lighthouse tradition, using pagodas on the shore to navigate (and forgoing sailing on moonless nights).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MARKET_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Early models of urban development posit that early cities were built out of a series of necessities. Prosperity allowed some people to specialize in tasks – a weaver could make cloth all day and not have to worry about tilling a field. However, exchanging these goods, especially over long distances, required a central location: a market (i.e. agora, souk, bazaar). Still, markets alone were insufficient as they required protection and the development of systems to control violence. In a word, soldiers. The market thus acts as a catalyst for increasing social complexity, building upon the need for specialization and systems of control.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MONUMENT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A monument is a place of memory. It is a site – often without another function – built to frame a collective memory of the past, usually to celebrate it (but not always). Monuments provide a template for the public's reading of the past, normally created by those in power. For instance, Trajan’s Column, completed in 113 CE, depicts a benevolent Roman army moving towards a hostile foreign power and the subsequent rebuilding of the conquered lands; the message is that the army acted with goodwill, an important message for a public wary of a Roman military constantly set to seize power. Monuments erected in the 1920s across the American South purported to mourn the loss of the Civil War, but they contained a subtext about the continuing influence of white supremacy in the region. Monuments can also be read against the grain: Bangkok’s Democracy Monument was built by a fascist architect to celebrate a military regime, but these days it is a focal point for pro-democratic rallies. Like narrative, memory alters and changes, and the meanings of monuments today are rarely those the builders intended.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_SAW_PIT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Boats are not shaped from whole trees. Even dugout canoes require a deal of processing. The construction of a ship, or building, requires that trees be transported to a site and carved into various planks. This is the function of a saw pit – a place where logs can be hauled (by horse, ox, or elephant) to be carved into manageable shapes. Early on, saw pits relied upon massive two-person saws; later medieval builders operated water-driven saws. Two skilled workers could produce a dozen boards a day, whereas a water-driven sawmill could increase that number by a factor of ten or more.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_VILLA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Many ancient societies had strictly guarded systems of social class. The ruler governed from the central palace, but oligarchies required a body of powerful nobles. In ancient times, productivity often translated to power. Estates, large or small, acted like near-states in themselves, and could house plantations, industries, labor staff, and even personal guards. In Rome, these estates were villas, palatial residences surrounded by a variety of productions. Villas could become threats to centralized power, as production led to wealth, wealth led to influence, and influence could lay claim to power. Roman villas were divided into country and suburban residences and could reach the size of the latifundia, large estates with masses of working enslaved people. But villas could also be simple country estates separated from the omnipresent politics (and pestilence) of urban life.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Unique Buildings -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_BASILICA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the Roman Republic, cities began constructing basilicas, spaces in which the populace could conduct business transactions and legal processes. These rectangular buildings typically featured a central hall bordered by aisles. One or both ends of the structure were raised to accommodate a magistrate tribunal or a statue of the emperor. By the first century BC, basilicas had grown into immense, elaborate monuments and became a hallmark of Roman urbanism. The Forum in Rome held no less than seven. As a core element of the forum model, basilicas were built in settlements as far away as Britain. They became so ingrained in Roman life that small versions were attached to the houses of aristocrats, who used them to host guests and manage private business.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DHARAMSHALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When we think of travel in the ancient world, we think of great caravans moving down the Silk Road, or galleys filled with amphorae. But pilgrimage also played a key part in travel. The Hindu worlds of South Asia were no exception, with pilgrims traveling to shrines and temples that were particularly important to a trade group or caste or were well-suited to a certain crisis for which the pilgrim sought assistance. Dharamshalas were shelters for these pilgrims and were places where people with similar concerns or professions could meet after crossing wide distances, creating a sense of public.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_DHARAMSHALA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In later years, dharamshalas would prove influential in forming particular spiritual groups, especially Sikh communities. But these developments took place over a thousand years after the end of the Maurya dynasty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_JALAW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ballcourt – jalaw – was a vital part of Maya society as a space that linked athletics and religion. Players would strike a heavy rubber ball in an attempt to pass it through a stone hoop while the opposing team tried to overturn control of the ball. The relatively simple custom was amplified by a clear deterrent to losing: sometimes the losers were ritually sacrificed (how often is a matter of archaeological speculation). The game also figures in Maya myth: the Hero Twins make their names as ball-players, playing as far and wide as the underworld, and in so doing they arrange the death and defeat of its malevolent gods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_JALAW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The ball game extended across Mesoamerica, from Maya lands to the later Aztec Empire, and as far north as the present-day state of Arizona. As with the Hero Twins story, the game may have been a substitute for larger violent conflicts, allowing a ritualized form of competition when direct conflict would have cost too much, in both lives and infrastructure.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_KUH_NAH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>While the uwaybil k’uh was the inner resting place of the gods, a deity’s entire house was called the k’uh nah. This interior space was devoted solely to the god's interactions with the community, and many social functions could occur here. But even the temple complex was part of a larger ceremonial complex, where the dwelling and activity places of particular gods were mapped onto physical terrain, presided over by a literate priestly class.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_KUH_NAH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Much has been made of sacrifice in Maya religious practice, but the k’uh nah extends beyond the ritualized human sacrifice that many imagine. On an everyday level, the sprinkling of blood, most often from animals, was a key part of rituals aimed at currying favor with the gods. This spilled red blood recalls the red of Maya structures – blood’s brightness, its vitality, its essence, were the currency to be traded to the gods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MASTABA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The mastaba was a common type of tomb constructed by the ancient Egyptians throughout their long history. These structures were rectangular, with sides that sloped up to a flat roof. Inside the mastaba was a chapel where priests and family members could leave offerings for the deceased. The chapel had a false door, an artistic rendition of an entrance via which the dead were thought to cross the barrier between life and death.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MASTABA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Beneath the mastaba was the tomb itself. The shaft leading down to the burial chamber was filled with rubble to stymie grave robbers, and a second underground chamber sometimes stored additional goods for the deceased to take into the afterlife. Mastabas were constructed by individuals during the Old and Middle Kingdoms until they were phased out in favor of alternative burial methods. These “eternal houses” continue to live up to their name, forming an iconic part of Egyptian necropolises today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MORTUARY_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A key duty of ancient Egypt’s rulers was to prepare for their inevitable death. In addition to their tombs, they built mortuary temples to ensure that their royal ka, or spirit, would be cared for after departing for the afterlife. These structures featured shrines to the gods; a chapel with a false door, allowing the dead to access the realm of the living; an offering table for visitors’ dedications; and storerooms for goods devoted to the deceased. Mortuary temples were staffed by priests who performed daily rites, allowing the ruler to perpetually maintain their cult.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_MORTUARY_TEMPLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the Old, Middle, and early New Kingdoms, temples were typically attached to the pyramid or burial chamber where the royal was interred. The most famous of these is the Temple of Hatshepsut, a monumental structure commemorating her achievements, built to overshadow the Temple of Mentuhotep II next door. Although the rise of rock-cut tombs later prevented the construction of mortuary temples adjacent to the tombs themselves, they continued to be built a short distance away, carrying on centuries of tradition and reverence for those long gone.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_ODEON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Vocal arts were highly valued in ancient Greece, and the right venue was crucial for the demonstration of a performer’s skills. Large productions took place in the open-air theater, but the size and acoustics of these structures were not always ideal for more modest shows. In 435 BC, Pericles built a smaller stage as a rehearsal space next to the Theater of Dionysus in Athens. This odeon, covered by a roof and decorated with the remains of Persian ships destroyed in the recent war, began a movement toward cozier spaces for more intellectually driven performances of poets, musicians, and orators. The separation of odeons from theaters created a distinction between levels of entertainment, offering a space for these art forms to thrive for the enjoyment of educated audiences.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_PARTHENON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the fifth century BC, Athens reached a new zenith. Following the Persian War, it became the leader of the Delian League, a military alliance of Greek city-states organized to defend members from mutual enemies. With this power came the responsibility of the League’s treasury – and an opportunity for Pericles, the first citizen of Athens, to enhance his city’s profile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_PARTHENON_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Dipping into these mutual funds, Pericles began construction of several prominent buildings atop the Acropolis. The Parthenon was the crown jewel. This temple was devoted to Athena, goddess of wisdom and war. Immense columns surrounded the inner sanctuary, which contained two rooms – the naos, where worshippers could pray before a large statue of Athena, and the smaller opisthodomos, where the wealth of the Delian League was stored. Although heavily damaged by an explosion in the 17th century AD, the Parthenon still dominates the Athenian skyline today and remains one of the most iconic symbols of the ancient world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TEMPLE_OF_JUPITER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Of the many gods in the Roman pantheon, the most important was Jupiter, also called Jove – the king of the gods. A deity of the sky, he was associated with thunderbolts and eagles, and his worship permeated the Roman state throughout history until the arrival of Christianity in the fourth century AD. Oaths were sworn in his name, sacrifices were made for his favors, and victorious soldiers placed spoils of war before his statues.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_TEMPLE_OF_JUPITER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Temples built to Jupiter were major sites of religious worship. They were centrally located in settlements across the Roman world, most prominently in Rome, where the Temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus dominated the Capitoline Hill. Inside each temple was a statue of Jupiter. Priests and priestesses maintained the space, which was used for rites, festivals, and quiet prayer.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_VIHARA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The rainy season poses a special problem for Buddhist monks. Prohibited from taking life, monks had to exercise special caution navigating paths and avoid stepping on the insects that proliferated during this time of year. With this in mind, many Theravada Buddhist monks retreated to a special hall – a vihara – during the rains. At least, this is the theological interpretation. Practically, rain retreats and special quarters for monks allowed the monastic community to persist, cultivate discipline (or reinforce orthodoxy), and focus on the individual education of monks and novices. Even in the dry season, viharas are places of communal gathering for Buddhist monks, where a lot of the business of the monastery takes place.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_BUILDING_VIHARA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>During the Maurya period, viharas could be rest stops for travelers, even those of non-religious orientations. But under Ashoka, these more pleasure-oriented centers gave way to explicitly religious sites, often carved directly into the rock, as at Ellora. Ashoka even heavily promoted the gifts of goods and land to such religious viharas over the years.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!-- Unique Improvements -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_BARAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Angkorean civilization revolved around the control of water, specifically the great backflow of the Mekong River during the monsoon. Royal religious rites often named the monarch as the mediator between the heavens and the populations. As divinity made flesh, the king was responsible for ensuring that his people prospered – and prosperity in Southeast Asia depended on water. Baray were massive reservoirs (the West Baray could hold 14 million gallons of water) and were proof of the king’s ability to care for his people. Baray evoke the Sea of Creation in Hindu/Buddhist myth, combining both religious meaning and practical engineering in a single structure.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_HAN_GREAT_WALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Though its name suggests otherwise, the Great Wall of China is not a single wall. Its earliest sections were built between the seventh and third centuries BCE by warring kingdoms hoping to defend themselves against each other. The victorious Qin dynasty unified these states and destroyed the walls between them, but kept the structures along the northern borders. These segments were connected to defend against northern enemies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_HAN_GREAT_WALL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>With the rise of the Han dynasty in 202 BCE, diplomatic negotiations with the nomadic Xiongnu in the north soon erupted into war. In response, the Han strengthened and expanded the Qin walls, leveraging them as offensive structures to great success. Dotted with towers and forts, these walls created positions of strength in contested territories, claiming land and providing a defended route for supplies, communication, and trade. The walls were supplied by civilian and military farms and built largely using the rammed earth technique, in which soil is tightly compacted layer by layer between two vertical boards.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_HAWELT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Aksum, kingship was linked with religion, as kings were seen as the descendants of Astar, the principal god of the region. Before Aksum’s conversion to Christianity in the fourth century CE, royal tombs were marked by hawilt, large obelisks. These were decorated with false windows and doors, a type of vertical palatial skyscraper for the dead king. The obelisks were a source of ire for Aksum’s first Christian king, Ezana, who ended the practice, even though his own grave was marked with a hawilt. As a result, much of the original religious or social functions of these objects has been lost. Remaining hawilt number in the hundreds, including the Great Stele and King Ezana’s Stele.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_PAIRIDAEZA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>What is paradise? In the dry Iranian plateau, a walled garden with cool streams and groves of shady trees would have been a welcome respite from the heat. Mesopotamian rulers often built gardens in their palaces as otherworldly landscapes, at times re-creating the flora of the lands they had conquered. This tradition was taken into Persia, and the pairidaeza, or paradise, became a marker of luxury. These were not simply horticultural exhibitions. In addition to the exotic plants in the pairidaeza, hydroengineering technology moved water into artificial streams, fountains, waterfalls, and canals – irrigation for more than agriculture, for a re-creation of Eden (or its Zoroastrian equivalent).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_POTKOP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Potkop” is a Natchez term for “mountain” or “mound.” Here it refers to the mounds raised by the Mississippian people, although they would have called it something else (they were likely Siouan speakers, and the Natchez language is an isolate). Nonetheless, the Natchez were building mounds they called potkop when they encountered Europeans in the 17th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_POTKOP_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Mississippian potkop was a flat-topped structure made of packed earth, topped by a temple, storage buildings, or important homes and other central buildings. They were often used over successive generations, though Mississippian cities regularly went through cycles of growth and dissolution. The mounds are the most significant architectural aspect of their society that survives to the present.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--City-State Improvements-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FESTIVAL_GROUNDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Across the world, festivals are ubiquitous and play an important role in affirming societal bonds. Most occur at the local level and are too numerous and diverse to count or categorize, though some rise to become a global practice and center around common holidays. Regardless of size or purpose, festivals tend to include food, whether as a remnant of their agricultural origins or simply as a means to foster community and culture. Entertainment, whether in music, dance, or theater, is also a hallmark of modern festivals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FESTIVAL_GROUNDS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Many festivals throughout the world serve to mark the passage of the year and celebrate the natural cycle of rebirth and renewal. In temperate regions, the evergreen often serves to symbolize the annual cycle of death and rebirth, whereas in an arid, river basin like the Nile, the floods mark the passage of time and offer cause for celebration. In Ancient Rome, some people celebrated the Saturnalia by decorating trees, similar to the modern Christian practice of the Christmas tree. In parts of Asia, trees mark the passage of the New Year, such as in Hong Kong, where the Lam Tsuen festival is an important component of Chinese New Year celebrations. Tourists and locals alike celebrate by making wishes on trees, lighting lanterns with hopes for the new year, and delighting in the food carnival.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_HILLFORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Hillforts were Bronze and Iron Age fortifications found primarily in Europe. They used earthworks and ditches to reinforce a hill's natural defenses, sometimes enhancing dirt barriers with wooden stockades and other tactical barriers. They were often composed of multiple concentric walls, within which lay villages with populations far exceeding those of the smaller settlements that dotted the rural landscape.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_HILLFORT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Although initially developed by the Celtic peoples of Central Europe, the most famous hillforts are found in the British Isles and largely date to the Iron Age. The reason for their abundance is still debated – were they built in response to warfare or as permanent settlements to support growing trade networks? Either way, the scale of the earthworks makes them highly visible in the landscape – remnants of the ancient world living side by side with the modern.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ICE_HOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the low humidity of the Persian deserts, the yakhchāl stands as a cone of cool relief. These engineering marvels harnessed the desert air and underground water to create structures so well insulated from the heat that they could store ice even in the desert temperatures. Dating as far back as 400 BCE, yakchāls were constructed of a special mortar and featured walls at least two meters thick at their base – all designed to resist heat transfer and keep the interior cool. A shade wall was often constructed nearby to assist with the production and transfer of the ice.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ICE_HOUSE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The conical structure was designed to create air currents that would guide warm air out through the chimney-like spout, while openings at the base allowed cooler air in. Some yakchāls were built over a qanat, an underground aqueduct, that served as a water source and cooling system for air flowing into the structure. While most yakchāls were used to store ice, some also contained shallow pools of water that could produce ice through evaporation and radiative cooling. In modern times, mechanical refrigeration has reduced reliance on traditional yakchāls. Even so, some still stand and remain functional even after hundreds of years, offering inspiration for sustainable architecture.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_MEGALITH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A megalith, from the Greek “megas” (large) and “lithos” (stone), is a prehistoric structure made from one or more huge boulders. Common types of megaliths include a single standing stone such as the menhir or monolith, dolmens made of two upright stones supporting a third horizontal stone to look like a table, or more complex formations such as stone circles and cyclopean walls. These creations are found across the world. In ages of limited technology, they would have required significant communal cooperation to move and configure. Some megaliths contain burials, while others likely hosted religious or social rituals. Nevertheless, the exact purpose of many megaliths remains unknown, lost to the passage of millennia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_SOUQ_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The emporium was a trading center in the ancient and early medieval world. Many of these sites were permanent markets in settlements along the coast or near major trade routes. Others were seasonal, overlapping with significant regional events: political, social, or religious. Emporia were largely defined by local exports but were also created to attract and centralize imported goods from various origins. For instance, Hatshepsut established Elat as a gateway center of trade to attract materials from the Levant and Arabia that could then be funneled into Egypt. Due to the international flavor of emporia, they were centers of significant cultural exchange, where ideas as well as goods spread to new lands and minds.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_ZIGGURAT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Pyramid structures frequently appeared across the ancient world, and while their functions varied from civilization to civilization, many central themes remained the same. Pyramids are structurally stable and could be built to monumental proportions more easily than other architectural designs. Their upward reach speaks to the near-universal human association of the heavens with the divine. Building step pyramids is particularly straightforward. In Egypt, step pyramids predated the more famous straight-sided structures, and they were built as tombs for pharaohs and influential people. Chinese pyramids in the Henan and Shaanxi provinces were also used as tombs for early rulers during the Han Dynasty and beyond. The ziggurats of Mesopotamia acted as religious sites topped with temples and shrines; considered dwelling places of the gods, they were accessible only to priests. Mesoamerican pyramids were also sites of worship and sacrifice; their positions were often dictated by celestial bodies. In all cases, constructing pyramids required immense wealth and labor, and they were designed as symbols of power, inspiring awe among peoples both ancient and modern.</Text>
		</Row>

		<!--Unique Quarters-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_ACROPOLIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Acropolis, “upper city,” was the core district of a Greek settlement. Built atop a steep hill, it was designed as a citadel and provided a safe haven to the populace in the event of war. Due to its strong defenses, the acropolis often housed the city’s treasury, as well as the residence of its leader. In peacetime, it was a center for religion and society. Temples were raised to the gods, rituals and festivals were held within its walls, and cultural events such as theatrical and musical performances attracted locals and tourists alike.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_ACROPOLIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>While each major city featured an acropolis, the most famous remains that of Athens. Around its base lay the Odeon and the Theater of Dionysus; at its summit, amid temples and shrines, sat the Parthenon and an immense statue of the goddess Athena, surveying her namesake city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_FORUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The forum was the heart of Roman life, providing a communal center for the populace and drawing a settlement’s most important services – social, religious, economic, and cultural – into a single location. These public spaces began as commercial hubs, marketplaces that served multiple towns and drew them into a single political entity. They were also social centers for locals to gather and meet. Over time, these fora grew to incorporate additional functions. They housed the Temple of Jupiter and additional religious complexes and shrines. Political speeches and debates often took place on the steps of these buildings, while nearby basilicas bustled with legal matters and business transactions. During the Republic, the forum in Rome expanded in both scope and monumental architecture and became one of the city’s major tourist attractions, as well as the model for fora throughout the Roman world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_MATHA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A temple is often more than simply a temple. As Hindu and Jain temples grow larger, they fulfill more social functions and integrate into the community, becoming not only places of worship, but ones that offer services to all branches of society. Here, religious scholars are provided texts, technologies (e.g. medicine, sculpture, dance) are taught and studied, and the indigent or impoverished can receive help; temples may also function as communally-run spaces for agriculture and production. In the past, such places operated as a safety net in times of need, adding a human face to a world that, with wars and epidemics, disasters and uncertainty, could be harsh. These activities speak to the importance of working for the public good, and they occupy areas often managed by the state in the modern era. For example, universities, hospitals, and social welfare have become secularized today but were seen as a duty of religion in the past.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_MATHA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In Maurya India, mathas were sites where Hinduism was unified…and also elaborated upon by what we consider to be other religions today (e.g. Jainism, Buddhism), or branches of Hinduism (Shaivism, Vaishnavism).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_NECROPOLIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>According to ancient Egyptians, true immortality was found in death, but significant preparation was required to achieve the best outcome in the afterlife. The necropolis (“city of the dead”) developed to support and serve the extensive funerary practices that prepared body and soul for their final journey. Upon death, Egyptians believed the soul departed the body, which needed to be preserved until the spirit’s return allowed for rebirth. This process was accomplished through mummification, during which the organs were removed and the corpse was dried out, treated, and wrapped in linen before being interred in a sarcophagus. The dead were buried with spells to guide them to the afterlife, as well as food, tools, treasures, and other supplies they would need for the journey.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_NECROPOLIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Numerous dangerous paths traversed the Duat, or underworld, and the passage taken by the deceased was determined by their status in life. If the soul succeeded in this voyage, it faced judgment and was weighed against the feather of Ma’at to determine if it was pure enough to enter Sekhet-Aaru, the paradisial Field of Reeds. Those who passed the test would find new life…those who failed were consumed by the goddess Ammit, never to be reborn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_QUARTER_UWAYBIL_KUH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Maya godhouse – the uwaybil k’uh – was a place of veneration for the Maya deities. Temples were houses for the gods, places where the deities could rest and be at home. As such, they were often covered by a cloth, at once enhancing the familiarity of the place (i.e. its appearance as a place of rest and relaxation) as well as its otherworldliness (i.e. this place of rest was intended for a divine being). These coverings were located in the innermost sanctum of a Maya temple, a place closed off to all but the most high-ranking priests. As such they emphasized the temples as places of religious veneration, not communal activity. In other words, the idea that religious rites are moments that bring a community together (a theory of Émile Durkheim) is contradicted here. These were places where individuals could perform the necessary duties that ensure the cooperation and placation of the vital forces underpinning the universe in seclusion.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>