<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- Antiquity Civilizations -->
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_AKSUM -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AKSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ancient Mediterranean world featured arteries of trade extending from Rome to China (in later years, and through different routes, this would become the Silk Road). On the southern end of this route was the kingdom of Aksum, cited by the prophet Mani as one of the great powers of the world, alongside Rome, China, and Persia. Aksum believed it was the inheritor of Kush, or Nubia, which was called Ethiopia by the Greeks. This was the upper part of the Nile River (now known as the southern part, which is confusing if you’re looking at a map but makes sense if you’re sailing the river). This kingdom had its own language, culture, and identity that was linked deeply with Egypt. Kush traded with Egypt and was subjugated by them, but at times ruled over the entire Nile. Aksum bridged the Red Sea and controlled trade routes linking Africa to India, leaving the Mediterranean proper to Greek and Roman powers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AKSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Life at either end of this trade route had its advantages. If Aksum and Rome kept their frontiers fortified, they could profit from trade without being trampled by the armies that crossed over Persia and India. The list of goods Aksum traded is impressive: rhino horn, ivory, and all manner of products  from the African interior. Given its position at the mouth of the Red Sea, Aksum was well poised to capitalize on trade between India and Roman-controlled Egypt, especially when merchants wanted to bypass Syria and other potential Achaemenid Persian possessions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AKSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>This kingdom also anticipated later Christian Ethiopian realms. While the Aksumites originally practiced their own polytheistic religion, one king captured a Christian boy from Tyre called Frumentius. Frumentius remained in Aksum to educate the imperial heir, Ezana, whom he later converted to Christianity. Ezana’s conversion was likely motivated by the promise of stronger trading ties with the Mediterranean, particularly the Roman Empire, through shared religion. In addition to Christianity, modern-day Ethiopians trace their script, Ge’ez, back to Aksum, although it is debated how much of Aksumite culture was Arabic in origin and how much was from sub-Saharan Africa.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AKSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Aksum’s days were numbered as Muslim caliphates rose in the seventh century CE. The expanding Arab powers not only threatened Aksumite possessions in Yemen, but the Muslim conquest of Egypt and the establishment of trade empires based on religious connections meant that Aksum’s culture-defining trade routes went nowhere under Ethiopian rule. Unwilling to convert this time, the Aksumite kings faded into the introverted Ethiopian dynasties of the medieval period.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AKSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>While Aksum laid the foundations for modern-day Ethiopia, one wonders about an Ethiopia that could have been. If Aksum had maintained an open link with Byzantium, the fortunes of the eastern Mediterranean and general Orthodoxy might be different. One could imagine an Orthodox sphere of power extending south to the Swahili coast, stretching from Constantinople to present-day Kenya. But that was not to be, and once Aksum was cut off, it faded.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_AKSUM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>But “faded” might not be the best term as historical records cite a 10th century invasion of Aksum, either by a Jewish queen named Gudit or by a queen from southern lands (i.e. Kenya). Some kind of military action occurred in the region, but allegations pointing to non-Christians should be taken a grain of salt, given the prejudices of that era. Other sources suggest that a brief centuries-long rainy period ended, reverting Ethiopia to its drier roots and hurting the Aksumite food base. As a power in the Horn of Africa, Ethiopia would rise again, but this time as the master of the highlands and not the Red Sea. Still, this is a story of another time, a time of the Battle of Adwa, the rock-hewn churches of the hills, of resistance to colonialism (and internal colonization).</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_EGYPT -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Any text on early civilization is likely to evoke Egypt. The notion of time regarding Egyptian history is astounding. For instance, the Great Pyramid of Giza was already 2,600 years old by the time of the Roman Empire – meaning Cleopatra and Caesar were closer to our own time than those who laid the Pyramids' stones. Even two millennia after the Pyramids’ construction, the Egyptian kingdom still flourished, and the names of its gods Horus and Amun-Ra were still spoken. Will we say the same for our civilization two thousand years hence?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>To its inhabitants, Egypt was Kemet, the Black Land. Its modern name (Egypt) comes from the Greek “Aegyptos.” The link between the kingdom and the “black land” points to Egypt’s dependence on the Nile River. During the yearly flood, waters rise to a certain level, carrying rich silt and moisture onto the desolate Saharan ground. The line between black alluvial soil and unfertile, red soil underlines how the Egyptians viewed themselves – the rich, black land as opposed to the red desolation. Indeed, this dependence on the Nile resounds throughout Egyptian mythology; Ra, the god of the sun, shines upon the gifts of Hapi, the god/dess of the Nile’s flood, and Horus, the god of kings, rules over that. Life, death, and rebirth exist in an endless cycle that is both ever-changing and timeless.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The ethnic origins of the Egyptians has been a politically fraught question for some time. Colonizers had a vested interest in asserting Egypt's split from the local population in a strategy to assert authority over the land. However, the Egyptians were clearly “from” Egypt, and genetic analysis links ancient Egyptians most strongly to peoples of the Middle Eastern Mediterranean coast.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>To cover Egypt's history, we have to speak of very different times, nearly 7000 years ago. Egypt changed a lot during that period. Petroglyphs across the Sahara region reveal a different climate – one that is lusher than the present, where parts of the desert functioned more like a savannah. The Neolithic peoples who settled Egypt were master farmers and traders, importing obsidian micro-blades from Ethiopia to use in early sickles, making use of the rich Egyptian soil. After the Sahara dried, Neolithic people started to form communities in the fertile river valleys, centered around the mass production of grain. People developed bronzeworking (combining copper with tin or arsenic) to make tools (iron did not arrive until Roman times).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Religion suffused Egypt. Vitality came from the land, from the river (embodied in Hapi, the god of the flood), the pharaoh regnant (embodied in Horus), the light of the sun (embodied in Amun-Ra), the judgment of the dead (by the scales of Anubis), and the resurrection of the pharaoh (as Osiris, the reborn god). As with any religious system that spans thousands of years, differences emerge: Osiris did not become a significant deity until the Middle Kingdom and later pharaohs experimented with new divinities and even monotheism (Akhenaten sought to implement a monotheist worship of the god Aten).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Egypt's written history begins around 5000 years ago with Menes, which aptly means “he who endures.” According to myth, Menes accepted the crown directly from the falcon-headed god Horus. This was still not the centralized Old Kingdom of pyramids and sphinxes – for that, one has to advance another half-century to the reign of Djoser, the likely founder of the Old Kingdom. Djoser (or more likely his vizier Imhotep) piled stone mastaba tombs one upon another, beginning the tradition of pyramid-building, which would see its height during the reign of later pharaohs. Khufu was paramount among these rulers as he was the builder of the Great Pyramid at Giza. The Old Kingdom fell around 2100 BCE, for reasons that may have been political, environmental, or both. Regardless, a period of de-centralization followed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>In these “intermediate periods,” Egypt seemed to decline, but this was simply a decline of kings as the Egyptian people likely went back to some kind of municipal rule, focusing the kingdom’s colossal powers on improving the lives of living subjects rather than the ambitions of rebirth for its elite.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The most jarring split may have come during the invasion of the Hyksos, a people from the Near East who established a foreign dynasty during the Middle Kingdom. But within a few generations, the Hyksos had adopted Egyptian culture to the point that the invaders became indistinguishable from the invaded. During the New Kingdom (1550-1070 BCE), Egypt's might peaked. At this point, pyramid-building had long since passed, but the massive architecture of Ramses eclipsed these structures. The statues of the god-king in Thebes and Memphis displayed the magnificence and wealth of the time, which continued into the reign of Ramses' descendant, the pharaoh-queen Hatshepsut. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_EGYPT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>This was the last golden age of a kingdom that had shone brightly for a long time. In later years, powers such as Assyria, Persia, and eventually Greece and Rome, conquered Egypt. However, the region was never a backwater and became one of the most prized possessions for any Empire, largely owing to its rich grain sources. When Rome took the region, its riches flowed directly into imperial coffers, making figures like Augustus wealthy in ways they could not achieve from European land holdings alone. Around 640 CE, the Rashidun Caliphate made the final end to ancient Egypt, although centuries of Roman, Greek, and Byzantine rule had already altered it. Today, Egypt remains one of the most iconic empires of the ancient world, its immense ruins a testament to the legacy and ingenuity of its people. </Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_GREECE -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GREECE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Unlike Rome and Egypt, Greece was only rarely a unified polity. Instead, it was composed of a series of independent city-states (poleis) that shared a common cultural and linguistic heritage and sometimes allied in leagues or clashed in bitter wars. Greece only existed as an empire under Alexander. As a shared template of cultural and technological patterns, Greece created one of the bright spots of thought and creativity in the ancient world. Important regions in ancient Greece, such as Halicarnassus, Syracuse, Thrace, and Macedon, are now parts of neighboring, modern-day countries (e.g., Italy, Turkey, and North Macedonia).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GREECE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Homer’s Greece is perhaps the most famous – the world of the Odyssey and the Iliad, of the cyclops and the Trojan Horse. These tales come from before recorded history, during the archaic period, around 2800 years ago. Compared to other civilizations, this is not so old; at the Iliad’s composition, the Pyramids of Giza were already nearing 2000 years old. This is the period of the oldest Greek writing, a period when states were exploring novel political formations: tyranny (the seizure of power by unconventional means), total mobilization (e.g. the Spartan war machine), and democracy. These were variations on older themes. Athens may have written about democracy, but it certainly wasn't the first democratic government (nor would its system be recognized as a true democracy by modern politicians).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GREECE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The fifth century BCE was the height of Greek civilization. After Persia's dramatic failed invasion of Greece – which included the naval battle at Salamis and the famous episode where 300 Spartan soldiers withstood the Achaemenid Persian army at Thermopylae – Greece began to flourish. Scholars such as the historian Herodotus and the philosophers Plato and Socrates charted the political systems of the world and debated the nature of consciousness, reality, and the ideal forms of the state. These proved inspirational for present-day philosophy. Indeed, even words such as philosophy itself stem from this time (the Greek “philosophia” means “love of wisdom”).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GREECE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>However, this was not a period of peace. Athens and other city-states fought wars against threats both foreign and domestic. Sparta and Athens, with their radically different outlooks on life and the state, warred for dominance while Carthage and other neighbors posed a constant threat. By the fourth century BCE, the Greek peninsula was exhausted by constant battle. The northern power of Macedon was not. Alexander the Great rose from Macedonia to lead a united Greece on a world-spanning conquest that extended the empire's borders to India and beyond (but not westward into nascent Rome). After he divided his realm between his generals, however, this united Greece quickly fell into disunity and its successor states soon fell to other powers. The mainland was subsumed in 146 BCE by its western neighbor, Rome.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GREECE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Greek society was hierarchical and granted full rights to men as well as foreigners, enslaved people, and women (whose status was not as free as that of some of Greece’s neighbors). Even in democracies like Athens, only certain men could fully participate. These groups united around the agora, the public forum and market where ideas were exchanged.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GREECE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The Greek world was not isolated. Buddhists in India and in the Indo-Greek kingdoms that were included in Alexander’s conquest developed a fusion of Greek and Indian thought. This is unsurprising as Greek and Sanskrit shared certain vocabularies, Greek and Indian myths about thunder-throwing god kings (Indra or Zeus) often overlap, and their heroic folk tales about quests to win back a stolen bride (Sita or Helen) share some similarities. Danish traders, centuries before the Viking Age, sailed down the Rhine to do business with Greek merchants, and Greek markets carried goods across the Red Sea.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_GREECE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>The legacy of ancient Greece traveled to Rome where Roman writers adopted some Greek heritage. Greek became the language of the eastern Mediterranean. The Romans fragmented into East and West, but the East’s culture was largely Greek in nature. In the Middle Ages, Greek learning was embraced by Arab scholars who built the foundations of modern-day math and astronomy in dialogue with antiquity.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_HAN -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the fertile river valleys of the eastern coast of the Asian continent, a new power emerged around 1000 BCE. Our first clear glimpse of China was with the Zhou Dynasty: a series of powerful military states. Each of these states vied to become the hegemon, the protector of the emperor who was lord of the symbolically powerful yet militarily weak Zhou state. Maintaining imperial authority over a military power was a tricky balance – the final era of this dynasty wasn’t called “Warring States” for no reason. Different states employed different strategies: compromising, growing large and ethnically diverse (Chu), or becoming rigid and martial (Qin). As any who has heard the name Qin Shi Huang could guess, the Qin won out, largely through military mobilization and a basic but effective strategy of making alliances with distant powers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>However, the Qin were poor protectors. They overthrew the Zhou emperor and embarked on a forward-thinking, martial expansion that frightened other Chinese states. Despite Qin Shi Huang’s claims that he would be a universal, timeless monarch, death eventually came for him. The Qin had claimed they were the new, martial future for Chinese civilization, but the other Chinese states put a stop to that. A new era of warring states emerged, split between the Chu state and the Han state. Under the emperor Gaozu, the Han emerged from the Qin’s ashes in 202 BCE and sought to combine Qin efficiency with Zhou legitimacy. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In the early years, the Han struggled with its borders, especially regarding the Xiongnu, Central Asian horse-bound nomads who characterized the western border until the rise of the Mongol Empire. To put a very significant roadblock in the Xiongnu's path and to control westward trade, the Han began constructing the Great Wall. At the time, the structure was largely composed of rammed earth. The Han also expanded trade networks beyond its borders, reaching across Eurasia all the way to Rome.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Han balanced two different philosophical approaches: modernist (as in, forming a brave new world) and reformist (as in, rehabilitating the Zhou tradition). These approaches aligned with two philosophical strands: Legalism (a focus on the ruler) and Confucianism (a focus on everyone’s respective duties). Modernist policies were future-oriented and expansionist.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>As the modernist strain expanded, cracks began to show. The reformists (associated with Confucian bureaucrats) argued that expansion had gone far enough and pointed back to traditional values, roles, and the Zhou for inspiration on how to govern. Memories of Qin Shi Huang’s harsh rule were still fresh for many and this tension resulted in a civil war. By some estimates, this conflict destroyed half of China’s population and resulted in the capital moving from Chang’an to Luoyang (the former Zhou capital). At this time, areas only loosely occupied by the Han – namely Korea and Vietnam – turned to rebellion. The Trung sisters led the revolt in Vietnam, and while this independence was short-lived, it remains an important part of Vietnamese history today. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Back in China, the Han re-consolidated (the “Eastern Han,” so called because of the location of the capital), developing a complex system of court intrigue. Consort families pushed and prodded at the emperor. Eunuchs, a despised but powerful class of court advisers, did likewise. These factions moved into the vacuums created when the emperor declined.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_HAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Conflict broke out during a series of rebellions in 184 CE that would end with the Han Dynasty’s shattering fall, a period epitomized in the “Romance of the Three Kingdoms.” During this time, rival factions controlled different sections of the former kingdom, notably the ruthless Cao Cao, Sun Quan, and Liu Bei. Cao Cao's son, Cao Pi gained control of the former Han emperor and forced the emperor to abdicate the throne, ending the dynasty. Han lasted for over 400 years, from 202 BCE until 220 CE.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_KHMER -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Khmer (Cambodian) Empire was a Hindu-Buddhist kingdom centered within the Mekong River, around the Tonle Sap lake. Its forte was control of land, especially rice-producing land, and it extended its influence across mainland Southeast Asia. Khmer exchanged texts and spouses with similar polities elsewhere on the continent, although the Himalayas and its Southeast Asian spur limited access to China. The Champa empire, in present-day southern Vietnam, also presented a buffer zone between the Khmer and Vietnam. Its historical influence extends today beyond Cambodia into Thailand, southern Vietnam, and Laos.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The first major settlements in Southeast Asia (excluding Vietnam) were city-states centered around a divine king. Academics have debated the extent of India’s influence on this region – were they copies of Indian states, Southeast Asian states observing Indian customs, or entirely indigenous polities taking inspiration from India while going their own way?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The adoption of an Indian model of statecraft might seem strange but it was politically expediency – local animist beliefs (of spirits of this or that mountain or river) were often tied to old lineage systems. A powerful usurper might use a foreign ideology as a new basis for power, often with a claim to (Hindu) divinity. The narratives surrounding these divine kingdoms were often fusions of local and global folklore – a common origin myth (Khmer included) involved the marriage of a Brahman king to a naga (water dragon), thus uniting foreign/male power to local/common axes, laying the groundwork for a divine monarchy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>What is a god-king? The name conjures images of Oz, the Great and Terrible. However, the truth is more complicated. Hinduism teaches that everyone contains a little divinity – but some have more than others. Kings had barami – righteous, charismatic power – and were the kind of people everyone loved. For these people, things always seem to just work out, but they also behave in a way that attracts these qualities. However, a king is not a monk and divine reserve brought about divine puissance – the power to conquer and destroy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>This king was the cakkavatti, the lord of the universe and the quintessential divine king. Additionally, an astrological layout of a city was a claim to this power. O. W. Wolters describes these Indic kingdoms as the “Galactic Polity,” a political system that is a little like a fractal. The capital is built to look like the heavens and the lesser cities are built to look like the capital. This divine organization means that divine power can manifest on earth. In turn, lesser cities far flung from Angkor look like mini-Angkors, with their own mini-kings. These city satellites circle the center and mini-satellites encircle them, just as the Earth circles the Sun, and the Moon circles the Earth. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Unless the Earth were to break free.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Jayavarman II was the god-king who broke free. At the time, Khmer was a satellite of the Shailendra Dynasty of Java, but in 802 CE Jayavarman crowned himself king of Kambuja (Cambodia) and initiated a campaign of expansion. Jayavarman’s conquests extended across mainland Southeast Asia and established a permanent Khmer presence that has lasted to the present (occasional Siamese dominion notwithstanding). </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>This was not always an easy road. Yasovarman, who was a few kings down the line, established the first settlement at what would eventually become known as Angkor. This name is misleading as Angkor Wat means “city of temples,” and it certainly wasn’t the actual name of the place; his city was called Yasodharapura.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Cambodia relied on the Mekong River. The river is a hydrological marvel; the monsoons that smash into the Himalayas (“place of snows”) drop a phenomenal amount of water at an extreme pace, which feeds the great rivers of India as well as those to its east. This Mekong pulse surges downstream where it hits a very flat part of Cambodia (where Phnom Penh is today) and backfills the great lake at Tonle Sap. This model was used by the Cambodians to fill their great reservoirs, the barays, thus solving a problem endemic to the arid region: how to get an additional rice crop when the land dries. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Angkor sits at the edge of Tonle Sap Lake, and its baray reservoir is visible from space. The great temple complexes, built by Yasovarman and his successors, also sit there. In these temples, one can see evidence of a religious change; Angkor Wat is Hindu, but later temples were Mahayana Buddhist and are currently Theravada Buddhist. These religions are related. Both versions of Buddhism are an outgrowth of Hinduism, and all three respect the Hindu gods. In Cambodia, Hinduism was a cult of the monarch as divinity on earth, with Brahmans as attendants. Mahayana Buddhism was similar but had an emphasis on philosophy coming from India. Theravada Buddhism focuses on universal literacy and mobilization of the populace. Chinese traveler Zhou Daguan remarked on the variety of religious life in Angkor – Brahmans attended to the king, Buddhists the common folk, and everywhere there were mediums of the animist spirits of place. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>Yasodharapura was a massive city, carved out of the jungle. While only its stone structures remain, houses along irrigation canals would have stretched into the countryside, supporting a population of around a million people in one city alone. Buildings were temporary. A few teak wood houses and temples existed, but most were thatched structures on stilts with empty plazas for marketplaces. Women took a prominent place in the marketplace. Fish, rice, and tropical fruits composed most of the diet. Meanwhile, Khmer luxury goods included gold, sandalwood, and gems.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>War persisted, and royal succession was always contested. Kings would appoint an heir apparent, but other children of the royal harem often believed they had an equal claim. These lesser sons were often appointed as the kings of neighboring lands, so succession conflicts typically took the shape of large regional wars, rather than a quick and bloody palace assassination. Some lesser sons simply sought to break away and provided legitimacy for new dynasties in new eras. The wars with the Cham people of what is now southern Vietnam were the most bitter and sowed seeds of conflict between two of the oldest powers in the region, and Vietnam mobilized its Cham vassals provoking rebellions from Thais (Siamese) to Angkor’s west.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>Around 1300, something unexpected happened across the world. The Little Ice Age was a period of climate fluctuation that caused disastrous harvests and starvation. It was soon followed by the Black Death, a result of rodent population booms in Central Asia. In Southeast Asia, the Mekong experienced a drought then a sudden torrent of rain, severely damaging an economy dependent on regular floods.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text>Socially, the world experienced a general move toward vernacularization. Far-flung parts of the Khmer empire ceased being Khmer and started being Lao or Tai. Within Southeast Asia, this had a social precedent. First, Theravada placed importance on the common folk, on educating each person in the village, rather than the prestige of the ruler. This may have led to a decentering of power and knowledge in the capital and a rise of local forms of rule. In Siam, the ethnic Tai vassals of Sukhothai and Ayutthaya rose to capture Angkor. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_15">
			<Text>Angkor collapsed and Cambodia subsequently became a lesser partner between Vietnam and Siam, occasionally allying with the weaker against the stronger, often being torn apart in the process. The ruins of Angkor were never really abandoned, although the French “discovered” them during their conquest of Indochina. Today, they remain a potent nationalist symbol, gracing both the flags of present-day Cambodia and the Khmer Rouge. Indeed, as a sign of Siamese dominance, the Thai kings made a small model of Angkor and placed it in the temple of the Emerald Buddha.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_KHMER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_16">
			<Text>Angkor remains a stunning marker of a city in a tropical climate, of the devotion of people to a vision of the heavens, and of hydraulic engineering. “Living with water” is a defining feature of the empire, a lesson we might learn from today. It was a powerful symbol for those who conquered the area, whether they were Siamese, French… or Maoist.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_MAURYA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>India’s history is nearly as ancient as Egypt’s. Nearly 5,000 years ago, great Harappan cities flourished in the Indus River valley and their urban planning seemed almost modernist in its regulation and control. However, the Harappans scattered around the time the Vedic tradition arose, leading to a tension in Indian religious politics and religion that persists to the present. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>After the fall of the Indus River civilizations, India was a series of feuding city-states, disparate linguistic groups, and varied religions, including the elaboration of Hinduism and Jainism as well as the birth of Buddhism. Still, it had little political unity. As one city rose under one dynasty, other cities and dynasties were waiting for their chance. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Enter Alexander the Great, a product of similarly shifting city-states, who marched across this fractured landscape in 327 BCE and encountered the Nanda Empire. Alexander’s troops threatened to mutiny in the face of such a powerful force so far from home, which precipitated Alexander’s march back west. India seemed unconquerable. However, a single generation later, Nanda was fading. Chandragupta Maurya, a king from the Indus region, decided it was time to confront the fading Nanda kings and make a play for power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>From the capital at Pataliputra (Patna), Chandragupta established a kingdom, complete with a council of ministers (amatya) and a system of provincial administration that allowed for regional control. Chandragupta retraced Alexander’s steps and the Mauryans conquered the Greek kingdoms set up in Alexander’s shadow as well as the weakened Seleucid Persians.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>At home, the Mauryans built irrigation systems, industrial systems, and advanced roads stretching from Afghanistan to Myanmar, laying the framework for the Silk Road years later. While various cities kept their system of coinage and a degree of independence, Maurya was one of the most centralized powers to appear on the subcontinent, and its stability fostered trade. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Chandragupta’s power was concretized by charismatic authority rather than force of arms. The Mauryans expanded by convincing smaller polities that they were better off under a central suzerain than they were alone. Religion was also key to this strategy, a feature that became especially important under Chandragupta’s grandson, Ashoka. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Ashoka began as a militaristic conqueror, and his victory in the Kalinga War solidified Mauryan dominance in the east. But this conquest changed him. After a furious battle, in which thousands were killed, Ashoka grew disgusted with violence and embraced Buddhism and a love of peace (ahimsa). He desired to spread this message of non-violence across the kingdom, encouraging vegetarianism and tolerance. Ashoka erected pillars inscribed with his edicts across the landscape, and he dispatched Buddhist missionaries and emissaries to Southeast Asia and Greece.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>At least, that was Ashoka’s reputation. In practice, he struggled to make the transition from world conqueror to world renouncer. In one account, he sentenced nearly 20,000 members of a Jain sect to death after a satirist depicted the Buddha bowing before a Jain saint. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAURYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>New city-states continued to wait in the wings. After Maurya's height with Ashoka came its decline. Within a few generations, the Mauryans were usurped by newer dynasties and the next era of consolidation would be under the Gupta kings. But some cities remained, as did the Maurya’s legacy – Ashoka’s Buddhism became a powerful influence in Southeast Asia.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_MAYA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mesoamerica has one of the longest-known histories in the New World. The earliest evidence for settlements comes from nearly 10,000 years ago, but most details are lost to time. The Olmec (not their word) is one of the most visible of these ancient cultures (existing from around 1500-400 BCE), and they seem to display the classic Mesoamerican features: the ball game, religion centered around blood and bloodletting, and colossal stone art.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The Maya adopted much of this culture – indeed, the term Maya refers to a cultural formation rather than a single state or polity. As such, pinning down the "start" of the Maya civilization is a challenge as there is no single ruler who emerged from the beginning. The Maya speak of the creation of the world, where Heart of Sky toiled to build a caretaker for the animals out of mud and clay. These old forms proved inadequate, but humans (Maya) grew out of corn. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The formation of Maya culture extends from 2000 BCE to the present, and the term “Maya” encompasses everything Preclassic to the Zapatistas of today. In Civilization, we refer to the Classic Maya, between 250 BCE and 900 CE, when some of the greatest structures in Mesoamerica were built.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>By 200 BCE, the Maya were already living in complex cities, with impressive stone artistry and the iconic Maya hallmarks – the script and the calendar. Early studies posited that the Maya were a peaceful, priestly society. The American New Age movement had a notion that Maya cities were merely temples and sites for astronomy that rose out of the jungle. This is profoundly incorrect; LIDAR and earlier studies have revealed dense networks of canals and cultivated zones that extended around cities. Furthermore, cities were not at all peaceful. City-states were frequently at war, and human sacrifice was common. Still, the fascination between pseudoarchaeology, New Age spirituality, and the Maya remains.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Maya cities were relatively large for the time, reaching around 100,000 people, and were enmeshed in complicated political systems of vassalage, suzerainty, wars, and alliances. Internally, Tikal and Calakmul played the political chessboard, maneuvering lesser city-states into their orbit and against their rivals. Externally, the northern (non-Maya) city-state of Teotihuacan exerted both antagonistic and cooperative pressure.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Maya society was split between nobility and the populace. Cities were ruled by an ajaw, a king, or a k’uhul ajaw, an emperor, and a lot of effort was spent on court events. Trade extended to New Mexico and down to Panama, including turquoise, cacao, vanilla, cotton…and enemies unlucky enough to be captured and sold. Cities occasionally took a democratic stance, overseen by a council of elite lineages. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Around 800 CE, things started to fall apart. The environment might have been a part of it. Maya cities rarely depended on rivers as they were built atop the large natural aquifer of the Yucatan peninsula, which was useful for preventing the spread of water-borne disease and provided ubiquitous sources of fresh water across the forest but was also vulnerable to changing climates. During a drought, a river might slow to a trickle, but some form of stream will remain. On the other hand, when underground sources of water dry up, they dry up everywhere. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>The downfall of the Maya also had something to do with a series of fragile alliances with places like Teotihuacan that threw the system into chaos and opened the doors to war. There is evidence of a unique style of warfare, something that didn't produce a traditional depopulation, but an extermination of elites – a kind of Jacobite revolution where elites were deposed in a bloody fashion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Of course, the Maya persisted. Maya society reconfigured around sources of water in the highlands, and temple systems were built to manage irrigation, a departure from the aquifer-related irrigation previously used. Sites like Chichen Itza grew in importance, but many abandoned cities remained abandoned. A political confederacy formed, the League of Mayapan, and various other Maya kingdoms came about: the K’iche’, the Kaqchikel, and others.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MAYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>The next stage of the Maya is well known. Spanish contact occurred around 1511, and the last city fell in 1697. However, the Maya had dealt with disaster before. They have survived under different flags and endure even today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the late first millennium CE and the early second, the Mississippian society stretched from Louisiana to Michigan, and from east Texas to the South Carolina Atlantic. These people were called Mississippians largely on account of the river that ran through their center. Archaeologically speaking, they were a culture, meaning they had commonalities in land use, architecture, pottery, and other tools. However, since the Mississippians lacked a system of writing, our understanding of their culture is missing details: whether or not the group was united or divided, the names of its famous people, and the specific meanings of its symbols and legends. The archaeological imprint of violence (or the lack of it), the movement of goods, and shared iconography suggest political structures and reveal trade routes. Still, several questions remain: were city-states politically unified? Did they all speak the same language? Does the evidence for large public ball games in North America point to the same institution from Maya sites? Archaeologists can make educated guesses, but they are only educated guesses.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Mississippians would not have called themselves Mississippians. Cahokia, the name of the biggest settlement, is named for the people who lived there in the 1600s, but the clearest living descendants of the Mississippians are the Caddo people, who descend from a western variant of the central Mississippian group.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The Mississippians grew out of what archaeologists call the late Woodland period (1000 BCE-1000 CE). During this time, people in this region steadily increased the use of stone and bone technologies, and invented tools like blowguns and the bow (they had previously used spear-like atlatls). Over time, hunting groups developed pottery and agriculture (gourds and maize), though hunted deer remained important. Copper mining in the region began as early as 3000 BCE. Most copperworking involved manually bending the metal until it became warm enough to be pliable, and then riveting it to other sheets. Copper and brass were mostly used for ornamentation, although some tools and weapons were fashioned out of copper.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Around 800 CE, increasing sedentarism consolidated into permanent cities, the largest of which was Cahokia. Prior interpretations of Cahokia placed it at the center of trade routes directly controlled by rulers. But later evidence points to its role as the center of a more indirect empire, what archaeologists call a “paramount chiefdom,” in which rulers lead via influence and networks, rather than direct administration. A paramount chiefdom consists of a series of noble families; a chief comes from the upper levels of those families. This system of rule could be complicated by succession laws or election – it’s impossible to tell. Further, it seems that Mississippian systems were cyclical; nobles from different cities rose to power at different times. In short, this was a region with a high degree of political instability and social fluidity. Cahokian society revolved around class divisions and the appropriation of surplus production, though people who lived lower on the social scale probably lived communally.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>One key feature of Mississippian society was the construction of elaborate mounds. These were built in different ways across the region, as pyramids and platform mounds that housed various structures. In larger, centralized areas they were built annually, but on the outskirts, they would be constructed irregularly (likely according to life cycles or in moments interregnum – at the death or ascension of a chief). Even at the smaller level, cities were fortified with palisades and featured elaborate systems of festivals during which lesser cities sent tribute (deer forelimbs, maize, or prestige goods like copper plates) to their paramount chieftain. Additionally, Mississippians operated extensive trade networks, ranging from the Great Lakes to the Gulf of Mexico, the Atlantic to the Rockies. They also adopted an artistic system called the Southeastern Ceremonial Complex, which included lacrosse and other versions of the ball game (called “chunkey” in 17th century Cahokia).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>After white explorers found mounds in the Midwest, several rumors flourished. Some highly religious 19th-century Americans believed the Lost Tribes of Israel must have been behind the mounds' formations because they couldn’t get their heads around the idea that they'd been built by ancestors of the people they despised (who also seemed weak in the wake of war and disease). This led to a belief in lost civilizations in the American interior and became linked to popular notions of Atlantis. Needless to say, such speculation is unfounded, not to mention harmful in that it led to the disparagement and dispossession of present-day descendants of the Mississippians. The truth is that the Mississippians were the ancestors of many tribes in the area, namely: the Alabama, Apalachee, Caddo, Cherokee, Chickasaw, Choctaw, Muscogee Creek, Guale, Hitchiti, Houma, Kansa, Missouria, Mobilian, Natchez, Osage, Quapaw, Seminole, Tunica-Biloxi, Yamasee, and Yuchi. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MISSISSIPPIAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Remnants of mound-builders lasted until the first few European explorations (into the 1600s), indicating that the devastation of smallpox and the resultant social collapse was the Mississippians’ final blow.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_PERSIA -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Greek writers portrayed Persia as a land of luxury and despotism, full of god-kings who marshaled vast wealth and resources to invade hardy Western outposts. They tell a story of decadent despotism raging against rugged individualism. But it is not entirely the truth.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>“Persia” is the Greek term for the area often referred to as Iran. The region has been embedded in nearly all of Old World antiquity: neighboring Greece, India, China, and northern Europe. The Sumerians overlapped Iran from Mesopotamia, and the Elamite civilization arose in the region as early as 6,000 years ago. However, the story about a recognizable Iranian people begins with the fall of the great Mesopotamian powers – namely Assyria. Ashurbanipal’s final loss of the region came at the hands of the Medes, Persian pastoral nomads who had lived alongside the Elamites since around 1000 BCE.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The scope and scale of the Median Empire remain contested – Greek sources point to a well-organized realm, but this image lacks corroboration elsewhere. Regardless, in 553 BCE, Cyrus (eventually called Cyrus the Great) revolted against the Medes. After he won, he expanded the Persian Empire and defeated the Lydians (led by the famously wealthy King Croesus) and Babylon. In the latter conflict, Cyrus entered Hebrew history and is credited with freeing Jews from servitude before rebuilding Jerusalem.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Cyrus founded the Achaemenid dynasty, named after his family, which came to define Persia for many. His successors expanded the empire into Egypt and Libya, and across the Black Sea into parts of what is now Ukraine and Macedon. That was when they ran into a conflict that defines them to this day.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>At the time, much of western Asia Minor – modern-day Turkey – was composed of Greek city-states, some of which were controlled by Persia. The Greek states were too weak to take on Persia themselves, so the independent Athens helped fund the rebellion of these Aegean states. Persia ultimately regained control of these territories, but later Achaemenid kings, such as Darius (522-486) and Xerxes (486-465), would remember this insult. Xerxes led a massive force into Greece, easily taking most of the northern territories, but fought to a humiliating standstill at Thermopylae, where a force of thousands of Greeks delayed a Persian army fifty times their size. The most dramatic claim was that a force of 7,000 Greeks held out against three million Persians, but these numbers are likely vastly inflated. To make matters worse, the Greeks later routed the Persian navy at the Battle of Salamis.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>At home, the Persians expanded the scale and scope of the empire, creating a common currency and building a regulated system of satrapies – what might be likened to the later system of viceroys, where an appointed governor manages a nearly autonomous part of the empire. Some of these satrapies were minor, others were fabulously wealthy – especially those in Egypt and India (meaning the region that is now part of Pakistan). To foreground the wealth and might of their center of power, the Persians built Persepolis, a city of wonders with palaces and temples so marvelous that historians are divided over whether or not it was actually used as a regular metropolis.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>The Achaemenids spoke Elamite until Aramaic and Old Persian overtook it in popularity. Most Persian rulers were Zoroastrian, a monotheistic religion with influences on later faiths; it emphasized the struggle between good and evil, a world of warring angels and demons, and free will to choose between the two. Zoroastrian priests, or magi, were suppressed under Cyrus, but Darius and Xerxes openly embraced the faith.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PERSIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Ironically, in 330 BCE, the Achaemenids fell to a Greek invasion led by another “Great” – Alexander. After Alexander’s death, the Seleucid Empire (founded by Alexander’s general) established a Greek kingdom in Persia until the Parthians re-established Iranian dominance. Of course, Iran exists today, and Persian influence extends beyond Iran; it had a profound impact on the Abbasids, the Mughals, and most other nations in the area.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- CIVILIZATION_ROME -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rome’s history spans centuries; the most generous accounts place Rome's foundations in 753 BCE. The volume of material written by, on, and about Rome is staggering. Any brief attempt to capture the complexity of Roman history, its twists and turns, and its varied forms of government will be insufficient.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>According to myth, Romulus and Remus were twin brothers – the descendants of Mars and the Trojan hero Aeneas – who were abandoned in the countryside and raised by a wolf. The children played with blocks of brick and stone just as present-day children might play with blocks of wood and plastic. In the process, they built a city. Also like present-day children, the brothers immediately fought over their work. After Remus was killed, the city was named Rome.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Historically, Rome likely began as a collection of outcasts and exiles from neighboring settlements which grew in size and ambition as they attracted people to their community (or abducted them, as in the case of the Sabines). The quasi-mythical Roman monarchy gave way to the decidedly historical Republic. The Republic worked thanks to its Senate. Senators were appointed by locally-elected officials (selected from the patrician class), and debated domestic policy while legislative assemblies of full citizens (a minority) debated foreign policy and other matters. Rome did not have a written constitution, but it had a set of unwritten norms and precedents.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>For nearly five centuries, the system worked well. Depending on one’s status, Roman life could be luxurious or harsh. Slavery was common, especially on large agricultural estates or mines. The enslaved population was composed of war captives, individuals born into the practice, and those who sold themselves into the system to repay a debt. The question over who could become a full Roman citizen varied by region – citizenship was a far-off possibility for those living in areas conquered by Rome, while those in the Latin regions of Italy could more easily become a full member of the Republic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The steady growth of Rome's military might was a common strain on Roman life. Early on, the military was centered around drafts from consuls – an early form of conscription. Later, Rome developed a professional army, one that granted a great deal of status to high-ranking members, which could be leverage for political power. Toward the end of the Empire, Rome increasingly relied on foreign troops, which could end in disaster when these troops were snubbed or went unpaid.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The power of the professional military signaled the end of the Republic. Slighted by political concerns, Julius Caesar moved up the military ranks. When the Senate seemed likely to hold him accountable, he marched that military straight into Rome. While Caesar did not declare himself “emperor,” his rise ended the Roman Republic and heralded the start of the Roman Empire. Still, the end of the democracy (such as it was) did not signal the end of peace; Caesar’s line fostered a period of stability until the mid-first century CE when rival claimants tore the Empire apart.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>As emperors were routinely ousted by coups or assassinations, crisis loomed. During the calamitous third century, imperial assassination, plague, civil war, and economic collapse tore at the Empire. At one point,  three empires vied for control – Gaul, Rome, and Palmyra (under Queen Zenobia) with 26 potential emperors (most of whom were from the military). The crisis ended the city of Rome's dominance. Managing the increasingly fractious empire became an issue, and rule was eventually partitioned between different groups as Constantine moved the eastern capital to Constantinople.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>As Rome became increasingly poor and irrelevant in comparison to other cities, and with barbarians pushing on its borders, the West collapsed. A Germanic king took Ravenna (which had become the western capital) and ended the West by decree.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>In the East, Rome endured, and it would continue for nearly a thousand more years. However, this later empire was different; it was Christian (though the Empire had been Christian since 395), Greek-speaking, and focused on Anatolia, the Near East, and Greece. Historians term this eastern empire “Byzantium,” even though they called themselves Romanoi (Roman). Byzantium fell to the Turks in 1453.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_ROME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Later states sought the title of Rome as a source of validity. The German kingdoms used the title “Holy Roman Empire” through the modern period, and kings from Russia to Turkey to Germany used the title “Caesar,” while changing it slightly to Tsar, Kaiser, or Keyser. Modern capitals, such as Washington D.C. in the United States, used Roman iconography and architecture to create a fictive link with the past while calling their deliberative bodies a “Senate.” Has Rome ever truly fallen?</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>