<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<!--Tier 1-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_WARRIOR_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Warriors are people of violence who perform at the behest of another. Basic stone weapons were usually repurposed from more useful tools, and stone-tipped spears, clubs, and axes are among the earliest weapons found in the archaeological record. However, violence on an organized scale is only about 15,000 years old, from the Mesolithic period. Given enough room, early human societies could avoid others they found unpleasant, although smaller raiding parties (tens of people, rather than hundreds) were a feature of many societies and were used as a matter of politics, honor, revenge, or to capture a significant person. However, once people lay claim to land, warriors truly come into being as a force to defend territory and expand it through conquest. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SLINGER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A sling is often confused with a slingshot. A slingshot is an elastic band between a forked stick, while a sling is a pouch at the end of a rope. This pouch holds a bullet or stone that can be whipped around and thrown with extreme force. Slings are difficult to find in the archaeological record as soft rope and cloth degrade easily over time. Their relative cheapness also meant they were unlikely to be buried and preserved in royal tombs (unlike swords). Yet slings were in use as early as 10,000 BCE, and could be effective weapons in the hands of a trained user. They were significant for the Inca, Egyptians, Greeks, and others around the world. Even today, they are a key improvised weapon for common people protesting against police. They deliver a surprising punch for their small size.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Tier 2-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SPEARMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Spears have been in use as long as humans have hunted for food. The idea is simple – keep your enemy (or prey) at a distance while you thrust the pointy end of a stick at them. Here, the spear represents bronze weapons, made famous in Homer’s Iliad. Spears were the weapon of choice for much of antiquity and the Middle Ages. The Greek hoplite is famous for its spear-craft, but history has seen many other versions, including the Roman throwing spear (the pilum), the African iron spear (the assegai), the Chinese mao, and the Maasai sword-spear. In the New World, Aztecs and others utilized long staves tipped with razor-sharp obsidian, which was less durable than bronze but far sharper. Meanwhile, Polynesians crafted spears from sharks’ teeth. The advent of the firearm finally moved spears and their later equivalents out of the battlefield.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_ARCHER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The bow originated in human history long before nearly any feature of this game, except perhaps the spear. The bow's design is simple: a length of elastic material (often animal tendon but possibly plant fiber) is stretched between two points of a straight wooden staff, often a fusion of supple and rigid wood. As the elastic material bends against the resilience of the wood, a great deal of tensile force is stored, which can be used to propel arrows through the air. Arrows are thus often affixed with feathers for stability in flight. Small bows were and are used by hunters worldwide, but lack the power to inflict much damage on a human body – although poison can amplify the effect. Given the right wood or the addition of other materials such as iron or bone, bows can be made more powerful. The first recorded evidence of bows is nearly 70,000 years old; this technology has likely been with us since nearly the beginning.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The chariot took the world by storm. Ancient horses were not strong enough to carry riders on their backs (making the stirrup or other saddle-based technology impractical), but ancient peoples discovered that two (or more) horses tied to a wheeled cart could provide a fast and effective means of traversing relatively level terrain. As a result, the people of the chariot emerged from Central Asia: Scythians, the Vedic people, Hittites, and others. These populations launched wave after wave of conquest, although their subjects quickly caught on. Chariots outfitted with javelin throwers could race across the landscape – or battlefield. Mounted civilizations conducted conquests around six thousand years ago, and made a lasting impact upon Egypt, Han China, Vedic India, and nearly everywhere a wheeled cart could travel. For obvious reasons, chariots were hampered by forests or uneven terrain, and chariot-fueled charges did not reach the rainforests of the Maya, nor the forests of Europe or Southeast Asia. Still, chariots were a mainstay for many armies, especially the Han, and they were only replaced when more nimble horse-mounted units became practical.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BALLISTA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The ability to create ever-stronger bows increased the need to train ever-stronger archers. However, after a point, machines proved more powerful than muscles. Powerful bows developed into crossbows, which developed into flattened oxybeles, machine-cranked bows with powerful shots. With additional knowledge of mechanical engineering, these weapons were refined into the ballista, a great bow wound by torsion strings that could fling bolts or stones long distances. Ballistae were used in Rome and Greece beginning around 400 BCE, and their ranged attacks were truly devastating. These giant bolt throwers were phased out as warfare grew more diffuse and disorganized, but saw a revival in the Middle Ages alongside larger weapons like trebuchets.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_GALLEY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The galley dominated the seas of antiquity. Powered by both wind and oars (depending on the weather), these ships were capable of fast movement and were versatile in narrow, treacherous waters. In ship battles, such as the clash at Salamis between Greeks and Persians in 480 BCE, galleys could lock together as boarding parties exchanged blows. The vessels were easy to take on and off a beach, meaning they did not require all the infrastructure of a harbor, and they could clear shallow seas where larger ships failed. However, their low draft also created limitations. Their holds were limited compared to the number of oarsmen required for a full crew, and they were vulnerable to rolling swells; they were thus unsuited for ocean travel. Safe intercontinental travel required the development of deep-keeled vessels or innovations such as the Polynesian outrigger and the flexible Norse knarr.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Tier 3-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_PHALANX_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A phalanx was a terrifying military formation – for those facing it and those within it. Greek spearmen, or hoplites, were arranged in a formation with their long spears bristling forward before commencing a charge from which it was nearly impossible to escape unscathed. The phalanx was designed to combat every army's most devastating enemy: morale. It seems only natural to turn aside in the face of enemies who aim to kill you. However, those locked inside the shafts of their compatriots’ spears were thrust forward in an embrace that only ended with the death of their enemy – or their own. The weakness of the phalanx was its rigidity – it was highly effective on open terrain where two formations could square off, but the phalanx was stitched together with wood and bronze, so soldiers had difficulty adjusting to attacks from odd angles. As the Romans discovered, attacks from the side or back were devastating.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HORSEMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It must have taken great nerve to get off the back of a chariot and onto the back of a horse. The exact timing is fuzzy, but the first real historical evidence of horsemen comes from the Parthians in Mesopotamia during the first millennium BCE. These were horse nomads, figures who would haunt Eurasian history until the great khans. They used composite bows and fast horses to great effect against slower and less maneuverable chariots.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HORSEMAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The horse emerges time and again, from the Scythians to the Huns to the indigenous peoples of the American plains of the 19th and 20th centuries. Early cavalry were light and fought with javelins or short spears, which made them well-suited to nomadic peoples. Anthropologist David Graeber argues that the influence of mounted warrior peoples in antiquity transformed urban, agrarian societies into the stratified systems of later years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_QUADRIREME_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A galley was an oar-powered ship – a line of men would man each oar and propel the ship forward (and could seize a weapon should an enemy board). But what is better than a row of oars? More rows. The quadrireme had four rows of oars (two per side), doubling its speed and maneuverability, and allowing for crushing ramming attacks. This also doubled its crew of potential fighters (a career rowing likely made them extremely fit). The innovation first appeared during Alexander’s conquests in the fourth century BCE; Aristotle attributes it to Carthage. The quadrireme’s size also allowed for the mounting of catapults, adding a level of danger that smaller galleys lacked.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civ Unique Military-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BURNING_ARROW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Mississippian warfare typically utilized clubs and stone axes for melee weapons. Clubs were a point of pride and skill – the weapon of nobility. Battles appear to have been significant enough that Mississippians built fortifications around major settlements, although these defenses may have been designed to prevent war via intimidation rather than defend against actual siege.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_BURNING_ARROW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>For ranged attacks, thick bows held a draw of about fifty pounds (about half the force of an English longbow). Mississippian cities were constructed of wood and thatch. This meant that fire was a devastating weapon against them. Evidence from Cahokia shows that fire arrows were used offensively during raids – the resulting devastation and confusion only increased the shock value of such warfare.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DANTINAS_TATHA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>“Yuthahati” is an archaic term, derived from spoken, rather than written, South Asian languages (compare “hathi”, meaning elephant, to the written Sanskrit or Pali “gaja”). Still, it refers to the royal war elephants across the region. As seen in the carvings at Angkor, the king rides on his royal elephant above the masses of soldiers, literally and symbolically above his subjects. This is a fitting metaphor for royalty in Southeast Asia, but it also displays a tactical advantage. Elephants are not invulnerable to spears and swords, but they are hardier than smaller mounts. From their back, a warrior could fire over shields and the front ranks or duel a rival king with pikes. The symbolism continues in this clash of kings that occurs above the common fray, displayed where the entire battlefield could see its outcome. Elephants are also surprisingly quiet and capable of navigating muddy terrain where horses falter. They remained dominant in Southeast Asia even while horse archers were putting an end to the elephant’s dominance in drier climates.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DHOW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Dhow ply the Indian Ocean and Red Sea and have for centuries. The word "dhow" has Arabic origins, but the ships were a vital line of trade between India, East Africa, and the Middle East. From ports such as Lamu in Kenya to Adulis in Aksum, Musa in Yemen, Gujarat in India, and eastwards, the sharp-prowed dhow with its lateen (triangular) sail carried incense, ivory, and tortoise from the African coast to exchange with precious metals and wine elsewhere. Until the 19th century, human beings were also part of this cargo.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_DHOW_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As a general term, “dhow” also encompasses a wide body of similar kinds of ships, from the massive two-masted baghlah (a 30-meter ship with 30-40 crewmembers) that would undertake the longest voyages, to the smaller fishing dhow, crewed by a dozen or so men. The success of these various models created an opportunity for piracy, and many larger dhow formed the core of pirate fleets operating in and around the region.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HOPLITE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Imagine the phalanx – a grid of men linked in tight formation, spears thrust into the faces of their foes. Morale was a key enemy for any army, and the phalanx offered individual hoplites few chances to break and run; the only way through a battle was forward. Hoplites appeared on the field around the eighth century BCE. They wore heavy bronze armor and carried a solid shield and a two-meter-long spear. The phalanx's opposing force was often a mass of sharpened bronze, armored against javelins that offered little room to slip in and use a blade. It would have been terrifying – on both sides. The phalanx moved in a straight, deliberate march. If the formation was flanked or skirmished, the hoplites lost most of their frightening power.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HOPLITE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Greek hoplites were employed as mercenaries across the Mediterranean, Mesopotamia, and Near East. This style of fighting remained effective until later Roman innovations embraced a more nimble, disciplined system.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HULCHE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Javelins were popular among Maya warriors. Tipped with flint or obsidian, they were deadly throwing weapons made all the more effective when paired with a hul’che. These spear-throwing tools consisted of a forearm-length shaft ending in a cup where the butt of a javelin was placed. The hul’che acts as an extension of the arm, adding additional force to thrown projectiles and enabling javelins to travel faster and farther. The Maya were far from the only culture to make use of something like the hul’che; the Aztecs called their version the atlatl, and Australian Aboriginal peoples used the woomera.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_IMMORTAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Persian Immortals became a legendary part of the Achaemenid army. However, there remains some confusion concerning the accuracy of the term "immortal." We know the name thanks to the Greek historian Herodotus, but his sources were limited, and he often preferred a good story to verified fact. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_IMMORTAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>According to Herodotus, the Immortals were not undying warriors, but their unit was intended to be eternal. As soon as a member of the company became unable to fight, he was immediately replaced by another, so that a unit was always at full strength. Descriptions of their exact composition vary but include leather-clad javelin throwers and heavily-armored cavalry. Their arms likely varied over time, region, and battle. Whatever they might have called themselves, the Immortals formed an elite military that swept over South Asia, North Africa, the Middle East, and Europe.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LEGION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Roman legion was a unit of Roman troops formed for a particular war – until the Marian Reforms of 107 BCE when legions became virtually permanent. Legions included more than one kind of unit and were comprised of mounted soldiers and foot soldiers, generally on the order of a few thousand. Poorer spearmen (hastati) were positioned at the front of the line, while better-armed and armored soldiers (principes and triarii) were placed towards the rear. Soldiers were arranged in the maniple – an elaboration on the phalanx – which left empty spaces within the ranks to allow greater maneuverability and create deadly pockets where over-ambitious enemies might be trapped. These maniples were composed of around two hundred men and commanded by two centurions (each responsible for a hundred soldiers, as the name suggests).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LEGION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The legions began as groups of nobles who could afford their own arms and equipment, but as Rome grew into an empire, these military units gave way to a professional (and political) class of soldiers, which had profound ramifications for the development of the Empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_MEDJAY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Medja is a region in Nubia, present-day Sudan, that was always on the frontiers of Egypt. The Egyptians knew its people as Medjay – renowned for their archery skills. Given that the Medjay were just outside Egypt's central control, they could be either a boon or a bane to the pharaohs. These nomadic people from the lands bordering the Red Sea likely spoke a language related to Somali or Oromo. During later years, around 1500 BCE, the Egyptian state began incorporating Medjay units into the empire, as did the Kushites to the south. Over time, the meaning of the term “Medjay” drifted from defining the region and came to represent a particular corps of troops, especially those involved in policing – even if those members were ethnically, culturally, and regionally Egyptian. By the 500s BCE, the Medjay largely disappeared from historical records.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_NU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The chu-ko-nu was a repeating crossbow that first emerged during the Warring States period, between the fifth and third centuries BCE. Its magazine was attached to the top of the weapon and could hold up to twenty bolts at a time. A single pull of its handle drew the drawstring, dropped the bolt in place, and sent the projectile flying. Some models could fire two bolts at a time. The chu-ko-nu's mechanism enabled its rate of fire to far surpass hand-drawn bows and standard crossbows; it was also extremely easy to use, making it a weapon of choice for civilians who lacked military training. However, the chu-ko-nu was not particularly powerful; given that bolts often failed to fatally pierce their targets, they were sometimes tipped with poison to ensure victims met an untimely end.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_PURABHETTARAH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Known as a “city-breaker," the Mauryan war elephant was a battering ram – a living hulk of armored flesh trained to smash, ram, and stomp city walls. The advance of Vedic people across the subcontinent is most clearly associated with the chariot (the wheel being a core symbol of Vedic conquests), but the elephant also left a lasting impact. When Alexander attempted the invasion of India, his exhaustion finally caught up with him after battles with war elephants. The slightly later Mauryans fielded nearly ten thousand elephants in their wars, and elephants remained dominant against all but the best horsemen – their trumpeting would scatter horses and infantry. The Mongols won some brief advantages, turning their highly-trained and nimble horses into mobile archery platforms, but the use of elephants didn't wane until the adoption of cannons (even muskets were relatively ineffective against the behemoths).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_FOEDERATI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Foederati is a broad term that defines people who were neither Roman citizens nor under colonial control, but who were aligned with ancient and early medieval Rome through a treaty (foedus). Initially, this practice was used to keep northern tribes, like the Vandals and the Goths, at bay. The Romans offered food and wealth in exchange for military aid to stave off threats from these warlike neighbors. Eventually, Rome subsidized these payments with land, allowing Germanic peoples to settle within the borders of the empire – heralding the barbarian invasions that eventually toppled the Roman West.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Civ Unique Civilian-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HAZARAPATIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When Cyrus the Great founded the Achaemenid Empire, his army was not a professional force, but one formed through an ancient system of levies. This practice, called the kara, required civilians to answer a ruler’s call to arms and serve as long as war lasted; they returned to their homes in times of peace. As Cyrus consolidated his power and stabilized his empire, he invested in a standing army, the spada, which formed the core of his military might. The administration of this force required a strict hierarchy of soldiers and generals, at the top of which stood the hazarapatis, just beneath the King of Kings himself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_HAZARAPATIS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The duties of the hazarapatis were twofold. First, he was general of the standing army and likely in immediate command of the cavalry. Second, he led the royal bodyguard, the melophoroi, and controlled access to the king. These roles were very different and would have been challenging for a single person to manage alone, so scholars believe there were two hazarapateis at any one time, one for each position.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_JAGUAR_SLAYER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The wolf, the bear, the lion, and the tiger are all symbols of nobility in the Old World, an effort to identify with beasts that seemed to rule the natural order. In the New World, that creature was the jaguar, the largest predator of the Mesoamerican jungles, renowned for its deadliness and its beauty. Jaguar-dressed warriors were a feature of the Aztec military, but Maya nobility also saw itself in that luxuriant orange fur. Like the jaguar, elite Maya warriors were adept at navigating dense jungles and relied on surprise and ambush over the rigid phalanx lines of ancient Old World armies.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_JAGUAR_SLAYER_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In Maya mythology, jaguars represented hostile outside forces threatening civilization. They were mighty, but those who slayed them were mightier still. Yet the legendary jaguar slayers did not traditionally face the animals head-on. To overcome the physical disadvantages of humanity, hunters used tricks to outwit the jaguars. A key element of their toolkit was the jaguar trap, a deadfall set to drop a large boulder on approaching enemies. This trap was a powerful weapon against the jaguar and other foes, inflicting not only injury, but utter defeat.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LEGATUS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The legatus was a senior commander in the Roman army. His primary duty was leading his legion; if he controlled a province, he also acted as the local governor. Before becoming a legatus, one had to have served as a tribune before being appointed by the emperor himself. A legatus was recognizable by his scarlet cape and was responsible for commanding his units, training soldiers, administering discipline, and securing supplies, though he had a staff of six to whom these tasks were typically delegated.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_LOGIOS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Intellectual curiosity played a critical role in ancient Greek society, from early education to the emergence of professional scholars. These learned men and women ranged widely from philosophers and historians to mathematicians and astronomers. The growth of this intellectual landscape allowed Greece to flourish as a center of debate, contemplation, and discovery. Thousands of years later, many breakthroughs of the logioi continue to shape our world, including the Pythagorean theorem and the philosophical theories of Socrates and Plato.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_NAGARIKA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Maurya India, the nagarika oversaw the day-to-day operations of urban centers. The centralization of government divided the empire into provinces, which were further subdivided into settlements. The system had a strict hierarchy down to every aspect of life, from trade and infrastructure to agriculture and the arts. As the king oversaw the operation of his empire, the nagarika managed his city or town. Aided by a committee of officers, he was tasked with keeping his people happy and productive, administering their needs while collecting taxes and taking a census to submit to the provincial leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_SHI_DAFU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In ancient China, before the rise of the Han dynasty, two social classes separated the aristocracy from the common people: the Shì, scholars, and the Dàfū, officials. The latter ranked higher, but the Shì proved more valuable due to the nature of their knowledge and advice, and the two ranks eventually converged into a single class of scholar-officials. The Shì Dàfū often emerged from noble families and obtained power through recommendation. In addition to their bureaucratic duties, their academic pursuits varied widely, from philosophy and history to science and mathematics. Their Confucian education enabled them to integrate their values into the government and provide guidance to the larger populace.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TANKWA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Aksum’s position along the coast of the Red Sea turned the kingdom into a crossroads for maritime trade. Positioned between Egypt, Arabia, and the sub-Saharan coast, Aksumite markets attracted goods from neighbors and eventually farther flung contacts from the Mediterranean and the Indian Ocean. But the system wasn’t entirely fueled by imports; the kingdom also produced lucrative exports like ivory and gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TANKWA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At its height, Aksum was geographically small. Nevertheless, its control over trade routes and its attraction as a destination for commerce flooded its treasuries. In the sixth century CE, Kaleb I established garrisons in southern Arabia, solidifying Aksumite control on both sides of the Red Sea and further tightening its grip over the region’s trade routes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TANKWA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>This booming economy relied heavily on boats, notably the tankwa, a vessel made from dried papyrus reeds that was guided by a pole. Due to its light weight, it was best used in shallow waters and on lakes to transport goods to marketplaces along the shore. The tankwa was cheap and quick to produce, and its timeless efficiency survives today as locals in the Lake Tana region still use them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_TJATY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In Ancient Egypt, the tjaty, or viziers, were second in power only to the pharaohs. The tjaty carried out the throne’s duties, managing the day-to-day administration of the kingdom. Their responsibilities ranged widely from agriculture and infrastructure to legal process and financial management. They were also tasked with overseeing religious rituals and appointing high-level military officers. As a result, they had to be educated and literate and were carefully chosen for their wide-ranging knowledge and abilities. Tjaty were required to be fair and honest, with utmost respect for the law and complete control over their emotions. They were expected to carry out their duties fairly, guided by reason alone. Tjaty wore an amulet of Ma’at, goddess of truth and harmony, as a reminder of the divine order sought by the pharaoh, which they were assigned to protect.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VAISHYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Khmer society was built on the Indian model of statecraft, which was divided into four varnas (social classes): brahmins (scholars), kshatriyas (warriors and rulers), vaishyas (farmers and merchants), and shudras (artisans and workers). Starting at birth, this structure dictated a person’s path in life, and it aimed to preserve order through predetermined social responsibilities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_VAISHYA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The vaishyas were responsible for maintaining ethical trade for the Khmer Empire, both internally and externally. Regional trade was focused along the Mekong River, and international commerce occurred up and down the coast with polities like India, Java, and China. While foreign trade was largely conducted by men, local stalls in Khmer marketplaces were mostly run by women.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_WATONATHI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The consolidation of Mississippian power in urban centers like Cahokia created a natural pull for trade. However, these networks were not as large as one might think. While some artifacts indicate pockets of contact with far-flung peoples, the Mississippians did not typically travel beyond their immediate region. As significant as their cities were, their spheres of influence were limited to urban spaces and focused inward rather than toward administering the surrounding lands.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_PAGE_UNIT_WATONATHI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>As a result, Mississippian trade in Cahokia and similar centers largely focused on the import of local raw materials and the export of finalized products within short distances. Important materials included pigments, raw metals, and fine-grained rocks used to make axes. These were transformed by craftsmen into items that could be circulated by merchants. The result of this tight-knit network was the development of a strong Mississippian style developed in the urban space and distributed to the wider network of villages, uniting the people through cultural rather than political ties. </Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>