<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Database>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_AKSUM">
			<Text>Triangle-rigged dhows cut the waves, as Aksum ventures in search of new horizons and new markets. In their walled cities, the rulers of Aksum carve their legacy in stone and raise it to the heavens. Take the rudder and hoist the sails of Aksum, and steer your crew to luxury or conquest. Raise the hawilti and herald Aksum as the lords of the age. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_EGYPT">
			<Text>From the river-fed fields of grain to the polished limestone obelisks rises Egypt. Nurtured by the black soil that graces its riverbanks, Egypt provides for its people. And in its limestone obelisks and tombs, it challenges the most implacable of foes – time itself. Take up now the sharpened khopesh or the bronze chisel and make your mark - immortality awaits. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_GREECE">
			<Text>Out of many sources – militaristic Sparta, erudite Athens, wealthy Corinth – comes the rich bounty of Greece. Wielding poetry sharper than a hoplite’s spear, the writers and thinkers of Greece describe the beauty and nature of the world, even as the phalanx begins its march. Guide them in their quest for glory and fame. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_HAN">
			<Text>Forged from the legacies of the militaristic Qin and the cultured Zhou, the Han Dynasty of China rules with righteousness tempered with benevolence, with wisdom informed by tradition. Han engineers transformed the land, even as Han philosophers transformed the mind. Go now, and take up the Mandate of Heaven. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_KHMER">
			<Text>Like the monsoon rains, the Khmer give life to the land, and like the monsoon floods, they conquer what they will. The great mandala of Kambuja, the Khmer Empire, whirls with divine grace, and its power flows like water, a sanctuary against the burning sun. Stand on elephant-back, and let the waters rise. They will not touch you. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_MAURYA">
			<Text>Maurya life thrums to the thud of ox hoofs returning from the fields, the clatter of palm-leaf texts, the beat of the bhambha drums, the steady rhythm of monks’ chants, the whisper of court attendants. Lend your voice, lead the song.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_MAYA">
			<Text>Atop stone pyramids, the forest canopy gives way to stars, and from here the Maya plot their fate. In the thrill of the ball-court and in the words of the ancient poems, their heroes enact the drama of creation. Rise to the conch-shell horn, and don the feathered headdress – the Maya set forth. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_MISSISSIPPIAN">
			<Text>A new vision for the world arises from the mounds of Cahokia. The children of Red Horn and the Earthmaker shape the land as they see fit, building mountains out of plains, and cities out of the wilderness. As the burning arrow brings light to the darkness, the Mississippians bring new life to the world. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_PERSIA">
			<Text>Persia sits astride the world, a kingdom so great that its residents call it simply Xšāça, “the Kingdom.” Commanding trade routes and the armies to defend them, the rulers of Persia claim all that is worth having for their own. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_INTRO_TEXT_ROME">
			<Text>Rome: a name synonymous with power. Legend has it that the first Romans were raised by wolves. Seeing the debates in the Senate, the achingly straight Roman roads, and the well-ordered legions, one might doubt this. Seeing the light of ambition in Roman eyes, one does not. Raise the eagle standard, and let the world know the glory that is Rome.  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_AKSUM">
			<Text>Say the word, and Aksum shall perch on the gateway between worlds. May only the worthy pass and know its majesty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_EGYPT">
			<Text>The waters flood again, preparing the lands for new growth. Here Egypt will compel the world to behold the wonders it works.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_GREECE">
			<Text>The people gather together, debating music and politics, poetry and law--envisioning how to build a Greece that will last for ages.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_HAN">
			<Text>Harmony reveals itself through the shaping of energy, the cultivation of order. Now, the Han shall be its ministers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_KHMER">
			<Text>Prosperity falls from the heavens, flows down the rivers to nourish the Khmer, the masters of waters. Where else will their rains fall?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_MAURYA">
			<Text>Maurya life thrums to the thud of ox hoofs returning from the fields, the clatter of palm-leaf texts, the beat of the bhambha drums, the steady rhythm of monks’ chants, the whisper of court attendants. Lend your voice, lead the song.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_MAYA">
			<Text>The people lay these stones as a pathway to the heavens. Come, k'uhul ajaw, and assume the world's throne.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_MISSISSIPPIAN">
			<Text>A great dais rises from the earth, heralding a new day. What the Mississippians build will uphold the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_PERSIA">
			<Text>They will come from every corner of the world to pledge their strength and march under the same banner – the might and glory of Persia, embodied.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INTRO_ROME">
			<Text>A new banner unfurls, emblazoned with triumphal laurels. Rome seeks its champions.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_AKSUM">
			<Text>The Dhow unique Naval Unit can create Trade Routes if you have Open Borders, saving you a Merchant. With the Port of Nations Tradition, you can also receive extra Culture and Gold on all your Trade Routes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_EGYPT">
			<Text>The Riches of the Duat Tradition grants a bonus towards constructing Wonders. The Unique Civilian, the Tjaty, can sometimes add large sums of Production towards Wonders, too.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_GREECE">
			<Text>Use the Xenia Tradition to turn Independent Powers into City-States. Each one makes the Hoplite stronger with the Agoge Civic and grants Culture with the Symmachia Civic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_HAN">
			<Text>The Han dynasty is a scientific powerhouse, in more ways than one: their Science Buildings receive substantial bonuses, the Shì Dàfū Unique Civilians create Codices, and the Tianxia Tradition improves the Science yields of Specialists.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_KHMER">
			<Text>Build your Urban Districts on Floodplains whenever possible, but make sure you build a Baray. These Unique Improvements make Settlements immune to Floods, even in future Ages.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_MAURYA">
			<Text>Use Maurya's plentiful Happiness to support your military conquest, or pair it with the Shreni and Arthashastra Traditions to earn extra Gold and Science.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_MAYA">
			<Text>The Uwaybil K'uh Unique Quarter grants Production every time you research a Technology. Pair this with the Calendar Round Civic, which grants Culture for finishing Technologies and Science for finishing Civics!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_MISSISSIPPIAN">
			<Text>The Burning Arrow Unique Unit creates a field of fire wherever it strikes, whether attacking Settlements or defending your own. But watch out, because it will damage your own Units, too.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_PERSIA">
			<Text>Persia may provide strong incentives for military conquest, but with the Angarium Tradition and Achaemenid Empire Civic, it is also an economic powerhouse.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_CIV_TIPS_TEXT_ROME">
			<Text>Use the Cursus Honorum Tradition to generate Culture when producing Legions, then direct them in battle with your Legatus to earn it experience. After enough promotions, it can settle a new Town.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</Database>